Publisher’s Note

We are happy to place the book of Prof. K. B. Ramakrishna Rao in the hands of the interested public. We thank Smt. K. R. Vijayalakshmi, daughter of Prof. Rao for her passion to preserve the manuscript for more than 30 years and for her permission to publish the book. Her enthusiasm for arranging to publish her father`s book is to be specially appreciated and recorded.

Acknowledgements

Professor Juan Mascaró, who is well known to the world for his English translations of the Bhagavad Gita, the Upanishads and the Dhammapada, and who is devoted to Lord Krishna, took kindly to my writings. When I requested him to contribute a Preface to my work, he did so with all love, and so inspiringly. I may not deserve what he has said of me. I leave it to Lord Krishna to make me deserve what he has said of me. My grateful thanks are due to him.

I should not forget to mention the help that I received from my daughter Ch. Vijayalakshmi in preparing the Index. May her devotion to Lord Krishna increase!

How should I thank the Lord Himself who made me His instrument to give expression to what has been said here? I have nothing but a sense of fulfillment that I have served Him in my small way.

K.B. Ramakrishna Rao
Mysore University
Manasagangotri
Mysore 570 006

6th May 1984
(Visakha Suddha Panchami)

preface

Iam extremely happy to write this note about my father’s book entitled Bhagavad Gita: The Philosophy of Lokasaṃgraha or Cosmic Consolidation. Today (23-12-2016) is the most memorable day for me as my revered father`s book is being released on this date and month, which happens to be his birthday (23-12-1925).

My father saw beauty in everything. He set an example to the saying, “God is beauty and beauty is God.” He was an artist, poet, painter, sculptor and philosopher, all blended in one person. Lastly, he was my friend, philosopher and guide.

The present book was very dear to his heart. It was delivered as a series of lectures in the divine presence of Sri Satya Sai Baba at Whitefield, Bangalore, in May 1973. When Prof. Rao was alive he tried to get it published, but owing to the publishers’ lethargy, the book never saw the light of day. He died on 14-12-1988.

The present work could see the light of day owing to the help rendered by Sri Suresh Babu, Chandrasekhara Babu, Prof. Narayana Moorty, Prof Juan Mascaró and many others.

Sri Suresh Babu and Chandrasekhara Babu are not only family friends of Dr. Ramakrishna Rao, but also the followers of U.G. Krishnamurti, (U.G). U.G. used to spend some days with Prof. Rao during his visits to India. U.G. had seen the manuscript and was of the opinion that it should be published soon. Sri Suresh Babu, out of his love and affection for his uncle Prof. Rao, had resolved, along with Chandrasekhara Babu, that the book should be published. Thereafter, Prof. Narayana Moorty, who taught philosophy in the U.S., helped us by editing the book.

Prof. Juan Mascaró, a professor at Cambridge University, has written an appropriate preface to the book. My grateful thanks to all of them.

My grateful thanks also go to my dear husband Sri Shanmugasundaram and beloved daughter Kumari Harshini and Prof V.N. Sheshagiri Rao for their co-operation in publishing the book. Finally, I thank the great Almighty God who stood solidly behind the publication.

I hope the readers will receive the book with interest. Suggestions and improvements, if any, shall be incorporated in the next edition of the book.

K.R.Vijayalakshmi

115,Gangothri,
2nd stag, 4th cross,
Saraswathipuram,
Mysore 570 009 (India)

Phone (land): 0821–2543902
(mobile): 09164914209

Foreword

THE SONG of the Bhagavad Gita is the Song of the Universe, and the Spirit of the Universe speaks to our soul in this Song.

In the struggle of man for light, Arjuna, the symbol for man, feels his weakness, confusion and despair, and implores his friend, who is God: “Be a light unto me. I come to thee in supplication.’’

If any man goes in supplication to the Spirit of the Bhagavad Gita, with his life as his faith and with his love as his joy, the Spirit of the great Song will gradually lead him on the path of the mountain of the Highest and he will be able to say, like Arjuna to his God: “By thy grace I remember my light, and now gone is my delusion. My doubts are no more, my faith is firm; and now I can say, thy will be done.”

The verses of the Bhagavad Gita can be a fire to burn the dross of our life, and a light in our darkness leading us to a greater joy in remembering those words of light and fire and share their joy with others: bodhayantaḥ parasparaṃ.

Professor Ramakrishna Rao is a University Professor of Indian Philosophy, a thinker and a scholar. He offers his work at the feet of Krishna, and in this act of adoration he shows that he is more than a scholar and a thinker. He is a lover of the Spirit of the Bhagavad Gita. Scholars and thinkers think of the Gita in time, but Professor Rao sees the Gita in Eternity. This leads him to take a single word of the Song ‘lokasaṃgraha’, where the word loka becomes for him the ALL of the universe, and saṃgraha becomes the communion of the finite with the Infinite, in all our moments of life.

By throwing a new light on the word lokasaṃgraha he throws more light on the whole of the Bhagavad Gita. He sees that the great Song is a Song of life, and sees the sublime oneness of the Song. He thus can say that the Sāṃkhya of the Gita is not an analysis of the many, but a knowledge of the One; and sees the light of jñāna, the love of bhakti and the life of karma are three in one, three inseparable parts of the one spiritual body: a light which is also love and life, a love which is life and light, and a life which is light and love. He sees life as a yajña, a sacrifice and a dedication, and considers true life to be a yoga with the Infinite.

Professor Rao gives a symbolical, and therefore, a spiritual interpretation of ‘the path of light and darkness’ in chapter eight of the Gita, suggesting that transmigration of life takes place in one’s mind, here and now on this earth. This leads us to consider that every moment of our life is a new life and an old death. We die in a past that is gone and we live in a future to come, and thus our life on this earth is a perpetual transmigration.

In many of Professor Rao’s ideas on the Bhagavad Gita we find the seeds of what must be the spiritual life of man in times to come. It will be a new life based not on books or on words, but based on the greater life of those who are in true harmony with the Song of the Universe.

Juan Mascaró

Comberton
Cambridge, U.K.
May 1984

The Theme in the Vedic Perspective

Being ignorant, I inquire of the Sages
who know (the Truth). For the sake of gaining (the knowledge,
I beseech):
What is that One, the Unborn, which alone has held these six spheres?

Ṛg. Veda, 1.164.6

I ask you:
What is the outermost end of the universe? Where is its navel?
What is the fecundating power of the rain-shedding steed?
What is the transcendent source of all expression.

Ṛg. Veda, 1.164.34

Sages declare:
That alone is Ṛta (the Law of Being).
That alone is Satya (the Law of Truth).
That alone is the Transcendent Brahman of the sages.
That alone is the act of worship, and even social service.
That alone is the navel of the Universe, and sustains all being which has been and which will be.

Mahā Nārāyaṇa Upanishad, 1.6

None can reason out the Infinite and the mystery of its Being, neither its transcending heights nor its horizontal extension, nor its central dynamics.
Its name could just be Great Glory, and none can limit it by any definition.

Mahā Nārāyaṇa Upanishad, 1.10

Its being is only to be intuited,
(its dynamics) to be envisioned,
and (the glory of its Being)
authentically participated.

Bhagavad Gita, 9.54

A Few Words

This is an attempt to understand the message of Lord Krishna from an angle of one who considers Himself Reality, and how He means to organise His being. It is a cosmic orientation – not individual – which corrects naturally the individual estimates of Reality, but cosmic truth, which does not nullify the individual; instead, it restores his position of dignity and value in a cosmic theme and consolidation.

If one can call the present attempt an ‘interpretation’, it rests upon understanding Reality as a self-consolidating principle, infinite in dimensions and being. The attempt takes its cue from the happy expression found in the Bhagavad Gita viz. ‘loka-saṃgraha’, and expands its meaning beyond the individual, social, ethical or broadly, human reference, treating it only as an element of the larger cosmic theme. In this sense, ‘loka-saṃgraha’, beyond its generally restricted use, is cosmic consolidation referring to the whole range of being. The Lord, who puts forth the philosophy of cosmic consolidation, presents a perspective which is exactly the reverse of what any individual may have of Reality. It is Reality looking at us, and estimating us!

When the Lord touches upon the highest levels of truth, He calls it ‘transcendental dialectics’ (paraṃ bhāva), and guards it with a mystic secrecy by making use of phrases found, perhaps, nowhere else except in the Gita – phrases such as ātma-māyā, ātma-yoga, yoga māyā, ātma-vibhūti. It is in understanding these that great caution is needed, and no literal or prosaic translation will help us until we know by intuitively feeling the pulse of the transcendental dialectics.

Then, the demand is categorical to know the dialectics of cosmic consolidation. One has to participate in the dynamics of Reality, not as a participant from outside, but as the very being that is consolidating! Naturally, the Lord, who projects this perspective, orients our means and methods with certain qualifications, and effects a transformation of them, so that, in accordance with it, even the concept of fulfillment or consummation gets a toning so real and relieving! Under its benignity, even the sunken is lifted and the depraved redeemed, not just the one who is devoted!

Absorbed in the being (which is here called ‘dialectics’) of the Cosmic Truth, an individual finds himself to be a working centre of the Infinite, consolidating value and purpose beyond his immediate range. This perspective alleviates the individual from the limitations of relativism and presents him as a moment or occasion of the eternal being, which he is. How one is himself and simultaneously all other things in the continuity of eternity and infinity of existence is the mystic secret the Lord initiates us into. This is linking us with infinity and making us feel our bonds with the farthest of existents which had been and yet to be in an inalienable theme of relationship and consolidation.

It may be submitted in this connection that more than anything, Lord Krishna projects a philosophy that a man would like to present, but a philosophy that Reality itself presents. The recognition of this unique position of Krishna identified with the very Reality speaking to us will perhaps alter all our estimates of what is contained in the Gita. We are invited here to receive the verdict of Reality on our rights, claims, positions and ambitions. These very often foster a false personality and may set ourselves as anti-forces, as parallel existents against Reality or Truth itself. The vision the Lord presents has always the undertone of a cosmic evaluation of a particular instance or action, and His judgments of matter, mind and spirit, of feeling, thought and will, of religion, ethics and philosophy are always pitched high, and if we miss the illuminations of His analysis, perhaps we continue to tread the path that we have been treading, unmindful of the inner calls for a rethinking.

This humble essay, which is a free exposition of the philosophy of cosmic consolidation, is offered at the feet of the great Lord Krishna, who through the Divine Song has opened for us the vistas of universal or cosmic life and being, and has thrown a spectrum of bliss filling across. There is nothing here that the author claims as his own, except that he has tried to understand the deeper dialectics of the Infinite Being that sustains him both within and without. And if a sympathetic reaction is found around him with regard to his efforts, he is extremely grateful to the very dialectics that have set it in motion.

The scheme of this attempt is to present at first this cosmic perspective in the form of a free exposition – a long meditation, as it were, in sixteen sections – followed by a translation of the relevant portions of the text of the Gita, which bear out the exposition.

K. B. Ramakrishna Rao

Offered at the feet of Lord Krishna
Who through the divine song
has initiated us into the
extremely secret Spiritual Science
and has opened for us the vistas of
Universal or Cosmic life and being
through a spectrum of Bliss filling across.

1‘Cosmic Consolidation’ – The Theme In Perspective

One of the deepest insights into the nature of Reality, and incidentally, one which gives life its deepest significance as participation in Reality, is found in the Bhagavad Gita. The most highly respected of the Hindu scriptures, next only to the Upanishads, it also happens to be the word of the most highly loved of the divine incarnations, viz. Lord Krishna. For a comprehensive philosophic vision, and also for the most personal and intimate pursuits of religion, the Song Celestial gives so much scope that even as non-Hindus find therein the most universal elements of metaphysical, ethical and social values to be respected and adopted, the Hindus find in it their supreme spiritual ideal and the way of realisation enunciated in clear terms. Even as its dignity and charm of the noblest type capture the hearts of the devotees, the text presents a hope of salvation even to the lowest in life, let alone the glory of bliss it promises to the highly sincere and devoted.

Thinking minds all over the world – both Eastern and Western – scholars and saints, have considered it a privilege to find their intuitions and experiences corroborated therein, and so, are inspired to expound, comment and translate the work. With its universal appeal, the Hindu scripture has found its way into all parts of the world and into the major languages spoken around. The text has been one of the truest and most broad-based expositions of Hindu culture laying bare the secret of universal relationship that man has with another, with the Nature around, and with the deeper Principle within, which, at the same time, is the Principle of Objectivity outside.

In a wide sweep of problems that face man – individual and social, ethical and spiritual – an insight is given into the psychological bases for functions or malfunctions, and a cautious evaluation is made linking the overt actions or behavior with the hidden stream of Consciousness. And going further deep, the human problem or situation is linked with the none-too-different forces of objectivity, Nature or Cosmos. The Lord, as no ordinary philosopher may do, links up the whole sphere of life with the wider and deeper sinews of reality, and shows how every element which has come up in life has a meaning and purpose, and shows that nothing is unworthy essentially.

Here is found one of the most fascinating and appealing factors of the text, viz. its catholicity towards the touchy aspects of religious and philosophical pursuits held sacred and inviolable. Where narrow ideas of sanctity attached to individual religious pursuits endanger the values of life, the Lord recognizes each for its merit or value in bringing the different pursuants to the same end, viz. a cosmic relationship. Equally fascinating is the vision of the text giving dignity and a sense of privilege to all occupations within the human milieu by investing each a purpose and value both for the individual and for the community.

But the greatest insight of the text is to be discovered in its intention to metamorphose each individual effort, struggle, success and failure into a cosmic one. It is a transformation which, if properly intuited, makes life the most worthy to be lived. Putting it in another way, it may be said that the most meaningful aspect of its teaching is its insistence that a human being participates in the dynamics of Reality. It is not enough, if one intuits what Reality is. He should see and authentically participate in its being (Gita, 11.54). It is a conscious and understanding participation, but not an unconscious mute following, which is expected of each man. Because, herein lies the distinction of the human being from the other creatures and things – sentient and insentient – which do partake of Reality, but only as raw material constituting the dynamics of Reality. What enriches or makes life sublime is such a participation, which otherwise would be a wasted episode or material like those of animals and insentient beings.

Activity, dynamism, consciousness, and purposefulness – these constitute the very elements of a significant life and take us nearer to Reality, or bring Reality nearer to us. In other words, they characterise Reality. And hence, the eternal being or existence of Reality implies a fact of basic consolidation and conservation of all elements conscious and unconscious, static or dynamic, subtle and gross, finite and infinite. It is the whole of Reality revealed as consolidating itself as Infinity thus.

Can we rise up to grasp this from an obvious position of relativity and finitude? If so, the life we live is worth living. It is worth living from two angles: We are roused to a sense of essential relationship with the Infinite in our actual life, and in our fulfillment of our individual obligations we are made to discover that we play a part in the secret consolidation of the cosmic purpose taking place. A realisation of this ‘dialectic of cosmic consolidation’ through anything that operates within the orbit of the Infinite contributes to an awakening in us of a sense of an essential unity of being over against the relative polarity we normally live in an unawakened life. The most crucial aspect of the teaching of the Gita is to convey this secret of Reality, viz. the finite of our ordinary understanding is the Infinite, fully and totally.

If, on the other hand, one is not up to this expectation, and says that he is, or can only be, an isolated part or an aspect of Reality, it is the purpose of the Gita to make him aware that he cannot live for a second withdrawn from Reality. For what is within and without him is Reality. There is no withdrawal from it physical or vital. He has only the liberty of feeling free mentally, and this only to the extent of making his life adjusted to the rest of Reality. Therein lies his freedom, and serving it is his liberty. An individual, against his own wishes to escape, is made to realize that he is an inseparable aspect or part of Reality and is being sustained, nourished and propelled by the inner dialectics of all beings, viz. consolidation and conservation operating at the individual centre of action. This is an aspect of cosmic consolidation being effected at the individual level whether he knows it or not.[1]

Reality conceived in terms of cosmic consolidation has two sides:

the picture of the Cosmos as witness at the point of the individual unfolding itself as a unique moment or occasion, shaping and reshaping as a fuller and fuller personality (morally, socially, intellectually and spiritually),

and Cosmos whose sphere of influence as not stopping simply at the isolated moment or occasion called the ‘individual’, but also being the ‘trans-individual,’ i.e., cosmic.

As per this vision, an individual man or woman becomes a point or an instance of the whole humanity working towards a consolidation, and in him is to be seen the measure or the extent of consolidation achieved. It is an instance where the ideal, realisation and being coincide, the coincidence itself indicating the way Reality is revealing itself to us in its infinite unthwarted existence. This is the ‘sat’ aspect of reality.

This is the picture of the Cosmos as a whole gaining in its meaning for us in the process of assimilation as the illumined and evolved centres or moments. (i.e. conscious beings) function and consolidate. As these centres go on, the Cosmos as a whole puts up conditions of growth and evolution for the creatures moving and unmoving to exist and function, thereby illumining the unthwarted existence with light and joy. This is the cit and ānanda aspect of reality.

This vision of the Truth both as Reality and process[2] is presented by the Song Celestial and is discernible only when we have the gestalt of the text.

2‘Loka-Saṃgraha’ – The Key Term

The cue for the philosophy of the Bhagavad Gita is concealed behind a most significant expression which is used only twice in the text, but which sums up the whole perspective not only of the philosophy of the Gita but of Reality as such, namely, loka-saṃgraha (3.20,25). There is yet another significant term, which stands for the same, if divested of the narrow colourings put upon it, and that is, dharma-saṃgraha which the Lord terms dharma-saṃsthāpana (4.8). If taken in its widest sense against the background of the philosophy of the text itself and of the personality who says he has incarnated to achieve it, it is not simply overcoming the dissipating forces of irreligion and immorality and stabilizing righteousness of a certain people of a certain kingdom at a given time, but has behind it the very basic truth of consolidating the more fundamental truth, viz. universal order, harmony and growth, transcending the limits of relative grievances and feelings, misunderstandings as well as understandings, customs, practices and even their laxities, linking all these with the larger sinews of Reality operating outside and around human living and extending into the possibilities of all existence. Dharma is not only Ṛta, but also Satya. It is Order and Reality. And how are we to understand the dynamics of it in its being and continuance as being, i.e. in its eternality, other than by the most apt expression loka-saṃgraha?

The present endeavour is a humble effort to grasp the inner meaning of the dialectics of loka-saṃgraha or dharma-saṃgraha as Reality and process, or as ideal and technique, and also to understand the application of these meanings in terms of the Bhagavad Gita, an understanding which makes a difference in the use of the terms. There is a uniqueness in the perspective of the Gita behind the use of these terms, and it will become clear that a division or difference in the meaning of ‘Reality’ and ‘process’ or ‘idea’ and ‘technique’ does not exist in reality as envisaged by the Lord. To put it plainly, they are not different. But for purposes of understanding only – and standing at the relative level – we may make use of them only to be dropped later, and better it would be even for understanding, if their differences are dropped at every level.

As Reality loka-saṃgraha is not different from the very being of the Lord who gives it the boldest and loftiest expression in his embodied life and action as Krishna. There is an identification of loka-saṃgraha and Krishna as Reality, and so understanding the one is understanding the other. If the term saṃgraha is taken as an act or process, it is such a process which helps us to understand what Reality is. And if the compound word loka-saṃgraha is taken as a verb, it stands for the act or process. But taken as a noun it stands for Reality in its dynamic being. However, we should not forget that this process is not in time or space, as it refers to the absolute condition of Reality as Infinity, and the Infinity of the Hindu conception is not a process in time or space. All time and space derive their dynamics and existence from the being of Reality as Infinity. Whatever ontological significance we have as individuals in Reality, time and space or time-space just have. They come up as elements within Reality, and their main function is to link up individuals with Reality. They refer not to themselves but turn their eyes to Infinity (see 7.7). The divisions that they may create are instances where they have not functioned, or when they have functioned, they have done contrarily. That is, they have set up themselves as realities, whereby they have separated us from Infinity. The broken image of Infinity and Reality they project on us cuts us asunder to give us a false sense of independence, but only awaiting ultimate absorption as waste material by the Infinite.[3]

If this much is a digression, it is necessary, for it helps us to understand the intuitions of the Gita in identifying the technique with the ideal in loka-saṃgraha. In the context of process in time, the meaning of the techniques or paths of realisation is evident to us. Take for example, the techniques we name: karma, jñāna, bhakti – and there could be more like vairāgya, dāna, tapas, yajña, ahiṃsā, satya etc. – which are related to individual centres called psycho-physical beings. But there is an angle of understanding Reality not through these techniques operating in time, but of them as aspects of Reality in the same sense as time and space are aspects. In other words, there is an invitation here to check the meaning of a ‘path’ or ‘technique’ or ‘mode’ in the set-up of Reality not as leading to it, but as constitutive of it. Making it clear: if they are paths or techniques leading to it, i.e. the discovery of Reality, they must be by implication not the Reality, or the Reality is not manifest while the technique is on. This obviously is an irksome position, and one may be actually getting on with it without knowing it! We are invited to consider a re-orientation of the meaning of a technique or endeavour existing not outside of Reality but within it. This is the estimation of the value of a technique in so far as it seeks a fulfillment and gets itself validated functioning as Reality.[4]

Does this amount to a radical change in viewing a technique as Reality? If so, that is the sense which brings it nearer to the truth of Reality or loka-saṃgraha consolidating itself. Reality is a self-consolidating Truth, in the sense that it does not allow itself to be its opposite and does not work against its own being, and so points to a being whose dialectics is plainly that of consolidation. It is a self-creative or regenerative ‘sacrifice’ (yajña), but not a suicidal movement. It is Infinity never becoming its opposite. In its comprehensive, indivisible and eternal dimension, it rises above the dichotomies of our individual conception or perception. And so, any description of a process of Reality sadly misses the unitive character of Infinity, which Reality is. And at any point of what we mistakenly call a ‘process’, it is the whole of Infinity that comes up, but missing its dimensions we call it ‘finite’ – a finite thing or a moment – and link such things or moments in a series calling it a ‘process’ or ‘continuity’. Reality cannot become unreality, and unreality Reality (2.16). Infinite being or Infinity cannot go against its own Law of Infinity and become a finite thing. If we could intuit this nature of the consolidation of Being, we would catch the indivisibility of the Infinite Reality and come face to face with it as a whole at any moment, and each moment would be significant in so far as each is an occasion of universal or total consolidation.

Viewed against the background of this understanding, any form of sādhana gets a living freshness in keeping with the structure of Infinity that is Reality, for it goes on ever gathering a moment of meaning within the being of Reality, not realizing something else but itself as Reality. The freshness of this approach is that it reduces to nil the hierarchy of pursuits religious, on the one hand, ‘paths’ (such as jñana, bhakti, karma, etc.) on the other, as superior or inferior, and overcomes prejudices regarding them. The present attempt is an exercise in presenting this perspective, and the success or failure of it can only be judged as we proceed.

3An Academic Quibble

Perhaps what has been said may permit us to denominate the philosophy of the Bhagavad Gita as Loka-saṃgraha Yoga or the Philosophy of Cosmic Consolidation. However, at this juncture, the use of the term ‘cosmic’ may evoke a doubt, and one may ask if it is ‘cosmic’ as distinguished from the ‘acosmic’ interpretation of Reality. No doubt, academic thinking has differentiated between the two. On the basis of the definitions usually given of them, ‘cosmism’ points to Reality as an all-inclusive being in its personal character and ‘acosmism’ points to an all-exclusive and impersonal being or Reality. But it appears from the present perspective that this is too naïve a distinction to be launched and as such gives rise to scholastic or interpretational camps expending on the emotions of the contenders rather than serving the purpose of pointing to what Reality is in itself. Instances are not wanting of such positions and polemics built around defending positions, even associating within their ambit exclusive means or paths serving particular viewpoints. We are only to be reminded of the instances of it when it is argued that for the realisation of the acosmic truth it is only jñāna which can help and for cosmism it is bhakti that guides us. It is needless to expatiate on this.

But with reference to the personality of Krishna, who represents the highest Reality (and does not obviously belong to any camp), if we search for the cue, we find that he is not swayed by any of these academic or theoretic considerations in what he teaches as the reality. For him, as the embodiment of the very Reality, ‘cosmism’ and ‘acosmism’, ‘personalism’ and ‘impersonalism’ do not form opposites of denying or negating each other. The Absolute of his conception is such that, it is not only above these considerations, but by a mystery that is only true of Reality, each is the other! In the all-assimilating being of Infinite Reality ‘cosmism’ refers only to or stresses the immanent character of the Infinite Real, giving or forming the basis for what is commonly called ‘individual’ existence and action. It is here that we find ourselves knit through the warp and the woof of time and space, giving form to our being, warmth to our feeling, and objectivity to our reasoning. Whereas ‘acosmism’ points to the transcending nature of the very Real, giving meaning and extension to existence and action as passing beyond time and space. When Reality pulsates as contraction, we gather our mass as it were, and when it pulsates as expansion, we lose it as it were. It is the same Infinite Reality not limited to/by a point, but extends beyond it. The finite is the Infinite and vice versa, not by a process or movement in time but by being, by identity. The Infinite need not become the finite, it is the finite as well. The boundlessness of Infinity excludes all limitations, and so is acosmic, and the boundlessness is so inclusive that nothing is besides it, and so is cosmic (13.13-17). It is evident, then, that any categorization of Reality either as cosmic (or personal) or acosmic (or impersonal), without doubt, constricts the sense and being of its infinity as well as its freedom of expressing itself, not only at the individual level, but also at the farther end of the macrocosm, and even far beyond it. There is neither a split in its freedom nor a demarcation in its infinity. Whether the Lord preaches a personalistic or cosmic picture of Reality or not is to be estimated thus, and the implications of it are laid bare in the key chapter, the Viśwarūpa Darśana Yoga, which we render as ‘Cosmic Depersonalisation’. The vision we are invited to intuit therein misses the point if we go to it with the literal meaning of the word rūpa. We will have occasion to examine the meaning of it soon, but it will suffice here to say that the expression loka-saṃgraha or ‘cosmic consolidation’ gets amplified in the vision of the Lord, a vision which breaks all limits of comprehension through form, yet keeps every breath of ours, who may be witnessing, going on, for it is Reality itself that is breathing in us!

4The Dialectics Of The Infinite

That the whole conception of Reality as one of cosmic consolidation is gathered in one gestalt has already been suggested. And for this, the discipline required is to lose our bearings in the boundless, inexplicable Infinity itself – i.e. on the canvas of the Cosmos depersonalised. Actually one ought to seek for the intimations of Reality, for its extent and nature, in the most luminous experience presented in the chapter Viśwarūpa Darśana Yoga, and feel or see for oneself how he is disintegrated or depersonalized and yet picked up, as it were, in flesh and blood, and placed in a position only to be demanded of him that he has his assignments to fulfill and he fulfills his assignments: individual, social and cosmic. It is fitting then, to acquaint ourselves with what the Lord means by viśwarūpa – a cosmic form which is not something that we see as on the stage being played, but as in a stage being ourselves as the players. It is we who constitute the viśwa or the universe, and the rūpa or the form it makes is the indefinable mode of our being as Reality. We have to return to this theme perhaps more than once, but we make a start of knowing it now.

The impact of this mystic vision on anybody is so great that one is dissolved into the deeper dialectics of existence – even as Arjuna experiences it. If one is fortunate, he gets into that vantage position and from there sees what Arjuna sees: the Lord as everything, conceivable and inconceivable in His incarnate and discarnate forms. Reality is presented as His multi-forms – personal and impersonal, terrestrial and celestial, life and matter, moving and unmoving, atomic and cosmic, material and spiritual, immortality and mortality, existence and non-existence. It is the vision of the Infinite which engulfs all, yet transcends all either in time or in space or in both. It is the vision which destroys the illusion of a separate existence, and devastates the feeling of an immutable identity of one’s self under the pressure of an expanding, all-pervading being and vision. It is the vision of the infinite potency and freedom breaking all the logical and existential contradictions and oppositions found in such exclusive treatments as of the finite and the infinite, human and divine, the living and the non-living, mind and matter, atomic and cosmic. It is also the vision which transports one to the condition of being a living pulse in the Infinite Being through and through. In this grip of the mystic identity, there is nothing that the Lord is not, does not touch, does not sanctify and does not redeem.

Cosmic depersonalisation is the culmination of an exposition by the Lord Himself of what constitutes Reality. It is Reality explaining to us what Reality is. And when it does, it can plunge us in a direct participation in its dynamics, far beyond the insulations we often build around ourselves. An individual is torn off his covering and rendered into a nameless and formless existence with boundaries non-existing, but astoundingly making him feel the pulse of a dynamic reality in himself.

It is not an objective or outside vision of Reality which the Lord projects before Arjuna, but a vision which occasions an intimate authentic and existential experience in Arjuna of what constitutes Infinity, ever consolidating or expressing itself as Infinity.

Now, under much direct intimations of the all-comprehensive and all-inclusive Reality which excludes all exclusions (which is the real meaning of acosmism), the Lord invites us to share a cosmic responsibility to act as instruments to serve the cosmic theme and purpose, a theme which is ever dynamic, expanding and consolidating in meaning and expression to an attuned consciousness; whereas left to ourselves in our isolation and ignorance, we do not fulfill even our individual and narrow responsibilities.

Can we rise up to the expectations of this Infinite way of living, and of this Cosmic Law? The instance of Arjuna refusing to fight is in point. Until one gets the full picture of existence, he cannot understand the wrong score he is making on the workings of Reality. Arjuna’s fear of sin and his denial to fight are instances of discordant notes struck in the rhythm of Reality. It is a failure to find one’s place in the scheme of things. Also, it is a failure to know the cosmic design and purpose beyond the visions of an ordinary truncated life. When awakened to this reality, Arjuna gets a sense of responsibility and so of fulfillment, by picking up his bow and arrow to fight. From the point of view of the theme of Reality, it is really not getting up to fight, but an awakening to the truth of life, not of the individual but of the Cosmos.

5Other Readings

Perhaps, against the background of this cosmic demand of the Cosmic Law (viz. the Lord Krishna Himself), we are to know the meaning of our sharing the cosmic burden, i.e. loka-saṃgraha. We may, however, benefit by noting what interpretations the saints, philosophers and mystics have offered to this expression. Perhaps in the light of them we would be in a position to appreciate the value of the widest application of the meaning of the term we have attempted to provide.

The term as such occurs twice in the third chapter of the Gita, the Karma Yoga (3.20, 25), and here are some of the most important or prominent readings:

Persuading people not to go the wrong way (Śaṃkara).

Guiding people (Rāmānuja; W. D. P. Hill).

Guidance and control of the world, or taking the world along with one (M. Rangacharya).

Holding people together (Aurobindo).

Sticking to one’s dharma and avoiding the wrong one (Madhusūdana Saraswati).

Welfare of the people (Annie Besant).

Keeping people (in their duties) (K.T.Telang).

Control of the world (Edgerton).

World maintenance, i.e. the World Order (Radhakrishnan).

Welfare (and coherence) of the world (Zaehner).

Integration of the world (Natarajaguru).

Performing action with an eye to universal welfare (B.G.Tilak).

Though this is not an exhaustive list, yet in these prominent interpretations, we find two or three stresses laid. We find:

Interpretations referring to people or human beings – holding them together, guiding them to select the right path in life and avoiding all wrong action or behavior, or generally referring to the welfare of people,

Interpretations which refer to the maintenance of the world order or to its integration, and,

Interpretations which refer to the welfare of the world in coherence with the welfare of the people.

It is clearly evident that the reference in the first category is exclusive, in the sense that it is confined only to people or human beings, and does not refer to the other elements in the universe, which share and build up human life. In the second category, it is not clear whether the ‘world order’ or ‘integration’ refers to the world as a physical entity, or generally has reference to the order of life in the world. The third seems to be comprehensive, but is too vague to convey any definite sense, but seems to be referring to the universal welfare of people.

From these interpretations it should be quite clear whether loka-saṃgraha stands for any Cosmic Law or cosmic preservation, or it could be restricted to such special or narrow aspects of existence. Perhaps, we are to move beyond the limits set by these interpretations and comprehend by loka-saṃgraha a cosmic order covering all that exists in the physical and psychical, material and spiritual, gross and subtle aspects having direct or immediate, indirect or farfetched influence on us. What is aimed at by the present endeavour is to widen the implications of loka-saṃgraha to cover the universal order of being, beyond our ordinary application to the human welfare only or to a geophysical mass called the world. Human welfare, if we inquire deeply, is not simply physical, material, economic, social and political, but something more. A man is linked with the rest of Reality and with a Cosmic Law, which is interested in him in creating and maintaining conditions for his existence here, and in the possible growth of him with implications of cosmic consolidation.

That this larger implication is nearly the truth would be evident if we examine the idea of dharma-saṃsthāpana (4.8), of which we have noted earlier. It bears a repetition here. This is consolidating dharma when the fissiparous tendencies act at the subtle and gross levels of thought and action having repercussions not limited to human beings. For example, degeneration and destruction of the human kind is not the only loss to man’s being, but destruction of the animal and plant life is equally dangerous, for, in their destruction, the upkeep of the human species becomes difficult. And all these form integral aspects of the physical and supra-physical, and non-spiritual or spiritual whole demanding equal protection and nourishing. It is a wider perspective of loka-samgraha that throws illumination on the preservative necessity of even the one section of Being, viz. the human kind. Dharma-saṃsthāpana is consolidation of the Cosmic Law, even as loka-saṃgraha is. Dharma-saṃsthāpana or dharma-saṃgraha is not the whole business of stopping varṇa saṃkara (mixing of castes), kula kṣaya (degeneration of sects) or of continuation of oblations to the manes (1.40-44). This is only one aspect in the whole scheme of Reality, but it loses its basic significance if it is isolated from the rest of the cosmic milieu. So also, if loka-saṃgraha is meant to set up a moral, social or intellectual precept for others to follow, it seems not to be the whole business of loka-saṃgraha expected of a typical person like Janaka. And it is so facile an argument and example to set, and, from that standard, even Krishna’s is no better than anyone else’s, one who thinks he can be example to others (3.22-23). More is hidden behind the statements of the Lord touching upon dharma-saṃsthāpana and loka-saṃgraha than is obviously visible to the literal mind. Perhaps, we are missing the real import of the Lord by a casual treatment of the subject, that is, by limiting its extension.[5]

6Cosmic Dynamics – Its Meaning

We may be permitted to go a little further on the theme of loka-saṃgraha to understand its implication. There is no contention about the fact that when Krishna speaks we hear his authentic voice as the very embodiment of the transcendent truth,[6] the omni-pervasive Reality, the ordainer and destiny of all creation, and the goal of all endeavour. Perhaps what makes us forget about this Reality is that it is not reached as the result of endeavour, if we consider such endeavour to be different from Reality or as only a means leading to Reality. Such a separation of endeavour from Reality, which is taken as an ideal and as something distinct from (and untouched by) the turmoils involved in the movement towards it, renders both of them abstract as against their inner dynamics of non-duality. One wonders if this movement, this ‘throbbing of the heart’ (call it ‘bhakti’), the ‘heat of the mind’ (i.e., concentration, call it ‘tapasya’ or ‘yoga’), lack the character of a cosmic function and not share the cosmic dynamics or throbbing or heat. This is the mystery hidden from our ordinary sight, namely, the ‘throbbing’ or ‘concentration’ is the working of the cosmos at the individual centre. How can it be denied the character of a function, if we realise that by its simple persistence it is extending beyond itself to something that lies inherently in the very structure of the centre from which it has started? If the ‘throbbing’ did not function, or if it had functioned without the proper intensity or purity, or generally, if the turmoil had not been, the goal would not be.

What is important to notice is the presence of an organization or order in the bowels of each endeavour of the individual having a natural link with, and pulsating accordingly with, the rhythm of the Cosmos. To put it plainly, there is a local consolidation at each centre of pursuit, and given less than minimum order and concentration (i.e. packing of energy), the propelling would not be. Understood thus, the dynamics of Reality, both at the individual and cosmic levels, is the same, and loka-saṃgraha touches the core of this truth as taking the individual beyond himself in a graded fashion. It is this order, this sustained rhythm and moment as Reality, which is represented by the person of Krishna, the symbol of cosmic order and law of operation (śāśwata dharma goptā 11.18). And how can this afford to be idle, either as the individual centre or as the cosmos? Imagine a situation when it comes to a standstill, i.e., did not act or function. What would happen? The Law itself should tell us, and Krishna as the Law speaks:

If I do not function (or act), the worlds[7] will collapse, and I will be responsible for all dislocation of cosmic functions, and I will have destroyed all creation (animate and inanimate), (3.24).[8]

It should be evident at the first instance that this is not too much for an ordinary man to claim, and the Lord only could say of the collapse of the worlds and of the dislocation of the cosmic functions or destruction of all creation. That this is no ordinary mortal speaking, and that too casually, is evidenced further on, first, when he gives the word-picture of the infinite potency behind the capital ‘I’, in the chapter on Vibhūti Yoga which can easily be rendered as the dynamics of Self-projection, and further on, when he gives to Arjuna a taste of an authentic experience or participation in/of the dynamics of Infinite Being or dynamics of Self-existence (ātma-yoga) in the chapter on Viśwarūpa Darśana, already alluded to. But from the point of actual participation the experience of depersonalisation of an individual (like Arjuna) caught up in the vortex of cosmic-depersonalisation (as shown in Viśwarūpa Darśana) puts us straight on a point from where the pulse of this capital ‘I’ is felt, and so is worth a repeated elucidation.

Though the word-picture of the manifestations of the Cosmic Potency (in Vibhūti Yoga), is itself sufficient to become aware of what it is actually, yet, it is in the Viśwarūpa Darśana that the subject (may be Arjuna, or anyone for that matter) is split up into the marrows of one’s being, only to be gathered up and reconstructed, as it were, as the warp and woof of the Infinite or Reality as a whole. Here is the meaning of Reality – intuited participation – a Reality which absorbs or projects all elements, all beings, all forms, all actions, and a Reality which exists within and without (in the cells of one’s own body, and in the pigment of the petal of a flower) a boundless Infinity, the immeasurable and incomprehensible existence, the basis of all that exists and moves.

It is here, in the dialectics of Reality, shines the luminous vein of the cosmic purpose and consolidation expressing itself so vividly for one who can intuit, but hidden from the non-participant mortal. And so, evidently, Arjuna felt he had nothing left to accomplish in the battlefield, which has not been accomplished by the Law.

What the Lord showed to Arjuna was the other end of the thread hidden in the bowels of the future, but a future already accomplished by the dynamics of Timeless Infinity. It is extraordinary that for one who enters the Infinity the phases of time are revealed as if they are pages of a book in hand which could be turned back and forth. Viswarūpa Darśana is the splitting of the present instant, or properly, exploding time, and catching it at a given second and spreading it along on the canvas of Infinity, wherein time is shown as a tottering actor keeping pace as commanded by Destiny. It is as if capturing the dynamic time of seconds, minutes, hours and days, and projecting it on a more dynamic Time, which has none of these divisions. This is the Infinite against the background of which the fastest time runs slow, and could be shown as in a slow-motion picture moving backward and forward. It is thus Arjuna could see the future of himself and of others in the battlefield revealed as an event at a single point of non-relative time, the Infinity, the Lord Himself (11.26-30). It is this unique experience which Arjuna gets of the temporal and relative time of the past, present and future projected just as an event in the immeasurable structure of Absolute Time (11.32). The ‘I’ is depersonalized and is presented as the whole of Cosmos wherein even Arjuna is depersonalized and shown as losing his bearings. No wonder he cried for a restoration of a relative body normalcy (11.40-51). However, it should be noted that what Arjuna could see was only a fraction of the Infinite Being that the Lord is (10.42).

In the light of this meaning of the capital ‘I’ in the statement of the Lord: “if I do not act” (3.24), we may perhaps gather the significance and weight of the phrase loka-saṃgraha as applied to Krishna Himself (3.22-25).

What happens if the Cosmic Law itself does not operate? Perhaps water would not flow or would not quench thirst, neither could it put off fire; fire would not burn and would not shine; wind would not dry; truth would not act; and purity would not purify. This is dislocation of cosmic functions, which the Lord means, when he says: saṇkarasya ca kartāsyām (“I will be responsible for the dislocation” 3.24).

If such dislocation happens, what next? The destruction of these worlds and the ending of creation, which means destruction of all beings (3.24). Now aptly one is reminded of the spirit of the words of Yajñavalkya when he propounded the praśāsana of akṣara (Brihadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad, III.8.9):

By the command of Akṣara, the Sun, the Moon stay where they are keeping their order; Heaven and Earth stay keeping their respective positions (in the scheme of values); the instants, hours, days, nights, fortnights, months, seasons and years exit measured out (in the scheme of Infinity). Some rivers flow to the east and some to the west (in the strict obedience to the Law of Directions).

And what else, even human values get their recognition: “By its command chastity is praised!”

What happens if this Principle of Unalterability (Akṣara) of the strict Cosmic Law is countered? The attempt becomes futile and one who tries becomes a pitiable waste. But one who knows this, and follows this, attains the rhythm of Infinity (Brihadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad, III.8.10) as a chord vibrating to the tune of the Unalterable. As though in continuation of this theme, Krishna says, giving a hint of his cosmic stature: “Under My presidentship (and direction) Prakṛti creates, and the moving and the unmoving behave (9.10).” Perhaps all our estimates of this human friend of Arjuna get blurred, deficient and defective if we forget the deeper significance of his warnings:

Those who are ignorant do not know Me who has taken up this human form. They do not understand My Transcending Being (or Dialectics) (9.11).

I am Myself every creative function (yajña) that goes on; I am the enjoyer (bhokta) and the Master (prabhu). But those who do not know Me truly fall (9.24).

The Lord makes it plain that every element in this creative function is Himself:

I am Myself the will (behind all offerings). I am the creative act (i.e., the offering). I am the sweet libation too. I am the herb, I am the sacred formula as well. I am the ghee, I am the fire (and what more), I am the burnt even (9.16).

These statements should set us thinking what the Lord is: ahaṃ hi sarva yajñānām, ahaṃ kraturahaṃ yajñāḥ. The significance of these statements not only touches the core of the cosmology of the Gita, but also happens to be the ontological truth.[9] And it is in such statements that we must collect the deep implications of the truth behind the cosmos expressing itself, that is, maintaining itself as Cosmos. What we may see ordinarily is the being of the Cosmos involving us in it, but what we ought to see better is the illimitableness of the dialectics working through the Cosmos and even extending to its own region beyond the visible limits, namely, the primordial Will (kratu), whose dimension ever eludes us. When we speak of consolidation of cosmic purpose, we can only intuit how it is working within the realms of the Cosmos, but whether what we see as the Cosmos is necessarily the whole of the Creative Will is beyond our comprehension. This is the Transcendental Dialectics of Reality, a mystery hidden from our rational and empirical gaze, but yet a mystery which forms the foundation of all that we may gauge. This is the ‘paraṃ bhāva’ to which the Lord refers more than once as not being understood by mortals.

7The Creative Act

There is yet another way of understanding the dimension of loka-saṃgraha, and it is significant to notice that the Lord Himself prefaces the concept with reference to it. This is yajña, which constitutes the Creative Act – a manifestation of the Creative Will (kratu) mentioned earlier – behind all existence, and is compared to the unceasing movement of a wheel which while rotating keeps itself going. Call it yajña or loka-saṃgraha, both refer to the Reality in its dynamic nature or to its creative continuity and creative existence. Looked at in this light, what we see as cosmos is an ever revolving, assimilating and expanding being described in terms of a dynamic wheel: evaṃ pravartitaṃ cakraṃ. Of this the Lord says: “Whoever does not follow and understand this Law of Cosmic Wheel leads a deluded and a wasteful life” (3.16). The metaphor of the Wheel of Creation is so full of meaning that a literal rendering of the elements constituting it will take away the real significance that it is expected to have. It is the Cosmic Wheel standing for eternal creativity or newness symbolically expressed as ‘yajña’. If this is translated as ‘sacrifice’, then, creativity is sacrifice, and sacrifice is creativity. They are not only coterminous and involve reciprocally, but constitute the very Infinity (brahman) eternally (nityaṃ) in an unalterable (akṣara) chain of creativity. It is sṛṣṭi, and yajña which form the eternal truth. If Infinity is taken as an entity, such an entity is established through eternity in its own creativity (sarvagataṃ Brahma nityaṃ yajñe pratiṣṭhitaṃ – 3.15). The Infinity is so fixed in its roots of unalterability or immutability (brahma akṣara samudbhavaṃ – 3.15), that what we call elements in the Wheel are so well assimilated into the structure of Infinity that they never alter the constitution of Infinity or affect its dimension in any way. It is such an unalterable Infinity of an unfathomable potency, which is the source of all creative action, karma, and karma is the name for the act which emanates all existents (bhūta bhāvodbhavakaro visargaḥ karma samjñitaḥ – 8.3). And naturally, this act is rooted in Infinity or Infinite Existence (karma brahmodbhavaṃ – 3.15). And all creativity is rooted in its own fruition (yajña karma samudbhavaṃ – 3.14), as it were, of Infinity (brahma) moving towards creativity by an act of self-regenerative sacrifice or yajña. Metaphorically, all these elements, viz. the Infinity, the movement or fructification or regeneration gather like clouds only to pour down the nourishing liquids (rain, parajanya), and create solids (matter, annaṃ) for beings to come up and live on them. Highlighting only the most prominent elements of the Wheel, the Lord describes the entire act as one of yajña – a consolidation (evaṃ pravartitaṃ cakraṃ[10] ). The Creative Wheel gyrates on the pivot called yajña, and by yajña alone the spokes and the rim are given a direction, an onward motion, and yet are always held towards the centre. Thus yajña is both the centrifugal and centripetal energy. Even as it throws itself out centrifugally (i.e. expansion), it checks itself in when acting centripetally (i.e., consolidation). In any movement of a wheel both these unique features are integrally found keeping the identity of the thing from breaking down.

And it is equally interesting to notice, in another way, how the brahma or Infinity and the Creative Function or yajña are related in the series making the various events in the turn of the Wheel. Established in yajña, the brahma moves, and established in brahma, the yajña moves. The starting and the end points being thus brahma and yajña, one can never distinguish them in the circle or the wheel. Where the circle begins, it ends; and where it ends, it begins. This is the beauty of the wheel, viz. at the same point the extremes meet. That is, they are not extreme ends of a linear movement, but are like the indistinguishable points of fuses in an electrical circuit or ignition which keep the propelling on, and as such lose their differences or identities as connecting or disconnecting links. That is, none can say which is which in the Wheel of the Cosmos. And the various elements or points in the Wheel, viz. matter, creatures with mind, nourishment, action, etc. are so integrally ingrained that one can start from anywhere and, passing through others, come back to the same point. In this Wheel everything is interlinked: matter or mind, the inert or the dynamic, the solid or the liquid. And whoever helps it going is verily acting in terms of consolidation or loka-saṃgraha, but not others.

In this scheme of yajña or brahma, if consolidation of cosmic purpose, viz. loka-saṃgraha, is taken as an end, it is achieved by yajña as an act. Forms of this yajña are many and can be jñāna, bhakti, karma, vairāgya, ahiṃsā, satya-vacana, ārjava, etc. But yajña being the same thing as brahma, it would not be proper to take it as a means to loka-saṃgraha. And so, the implication is that loka-saṃgraha is itself brahma or yajña. It is significant to note that the Lord Himself says that He is yajña, Himself the kratu (9.16). This is the insight we are after.

Whatever constitutes Reality is sacrifice itself, whatever is Life is sacrifice itself – sacrifice, not in a limited literal sense of a liturgical ritual, but as an act of creative function or creation through dismemberment of brahma. Creation is an act of self-sacrifice, not in the sense of self-immolation, but as self-continuity. Continuation is by an act of sacrifice. It is in this original sense that Prajāpati is sacrifice itself. He is the first to sacrifice, and so is its first victim to be offered. As sacrifice Prajāpati is creative, and through ‘sacrifice he creates’, that is, by offering himself he creates.[11] The Lord refers to this sacrifice of Prajāpati in the Gita: “The universe that we see – the animate and the inanimate – is the result of this sacrifice (offering) of the Lord (3.10).” It is the sacrifice of the individual that the Lord teaches so that continuity is kept up (3.9.11). It is this which makes for consolidation. Our living, eating, acting and everything must form essential elements in the offering or sacrifice we are expected to make. In a word, whatever we do must be offering or libation at the altar of sacrifice (9.27), so that sacrifice continues, and with it, the life that libates. Hence the Lord says: “With yajña Prajāpati created all beings at first, and said, “by yajña you prosper,” “let yajña be your fulfiller (3.10).” It is clear, therefore, that yajña which is self-sacrifice is the act of self-continuity, self-preservation, and self-enjoyment. And anything that does not involve self-sacrifice is bound to go against the interests of this continuity, or more specifically, consolidation of being, and so stands condemned. Then, it is rightly said that all action (cognitive, conative and affective) is to be oriented to be yajña; otherwise, it binds one to the fruits of one’s misdeeds (3.9). This is the meaning of ‘self-destruction’. Then, all karma is intended to be yajña in this sanctified sense (yajñārthaṃ karma, tadarthaṃ karma) and to gain the sanctity of yajña each karma is to be done with dispassion, and to say the least, liberation is not separate from acting thus (3.9).

At one stroke two things are won: karma which is freed from sin (3.13), and liberation from karma (fate) through performance of karma (action) as yajña (4.31). This is the soul of all yajña, karma and mokṣa; and we are invited to catch this soul or ātman and are asked to abide in it (3.17). This is attaining Infinity or Eternity (brahma sanātanaṃ) (4.31). One sacrifices oneself out into Eternity or Immortality!

The participation, then, in this yajña, i.e. work (i.e. reality), is the act of identification and assumption of a conscious responsibility in the being of Reality. And contrary to this, any kind of laziness, indifference or separateness is an act of suicide and not sacrifice (3.16; 9.12). Individuality in the sense of isolated living and development from the rest of existence is false individuality and is suicidal, and the true sense of individuality is attainment of unity in existence, where the small, egoistical individual ceases to be, and assumes the individuality of Infinity. And so, the real individual is the Infinite itself. It is the fructification of all action, all sacrifice. And what more, the Infinite is the boundless existence wherein sacrifice and work never stop at any stage. It is an existence of an eternal consolidation and assimilation always pointing not to a finished end. It is an adventure wherein every thought, action, and feeling are themselves offerings – and these offerings have no end other than themselves, for they themselves form brahman or Infinity:

The sacrifice is the act of the Infinite (brahma). What is sacrificed is the Infinite. What burns (as the offering) is the Infinite. What is burnt is the Infinite (too). And what is aimed at by the absorption is the Infinite only (4.24).

The insight of this passage clinches the issue and lays bare the indistinguishable identity of existence and what we may ordinarily cognize as individual or separate acts. In this sense, none can specifically identify and point out which is brahma (Infinity), which is yajña (sacrifice) and which is offering, in existence. For each is the other in the process of self-extension or self-dismemberment into another, and its self-creation and self-continuity. This is the wheel which rotates (3.16), and rotating, it sustains itself steadily. It is the steady balance of the Wheel kept up in its movement, and if the movement stops it falls. The Lord represents this Wheel, and even so, Reality stands for this Wheel. The Lord is acyuta, i.e. unfallen.

And so, if we are able to grasp the significance of yajña as reality consolidating itself, perhaps we are getting near the truth of loka-saṃgraha, whose supreme demonstration is the Lord Himself as the Cosmic Law, not resting for a second or even a fraction of it.

A vision that is not in tune with this secret of being or does not approximate to this is prone to come up with a difficulty: What is one’s freedom if one is inextricably linked with this eternal, infinite, indivisible dialectics of Reality, in this ever-rotating Wheel of Reality?

From what has been noted so far, one’s being or existence in this Wheel is native and inescapable. And inescapability is not an indication of one’s loss of freedom. Bound up with Infinity or with the movement of the Wheel, one’s destiny is oriented towards Infinity, and what can be freedom other than that? If one is not deluded, freedom consists in being the whole, and bondage in being small or finite. Whereas self-sacrifice is the duty in the structure of self-continuity, it gets fulfilled in being the Whole, which is being free. The opposite of this, viz. escaping from one’s natural destiny (i.e. from being the Infinite) is suicide. This is ātma-hatyā in the real sense. Ignorance of the nature of Reality as the Infinite Being, wherein no individual is finite and useless, and dereliction of one’s duty or function as an aspect of consolidation of one’s own self, is sin – intellectual and moral – that one accumulates. It is this, which constitutes and perpetuates a parallel or anti-momentum of an egoistic separateness from that of the Wheel. While freedom is not escape from the brahma-cakra, bondage is to set oneself up against the cosmic force by the suicidal act of resistance, laziness, indifference, and so on. That is, technically, avoiding one’s karma or function, one’s contribution or sacrifice is denying to one’s self the joy of participation in the momentum of the Cosmic Wheel. While all parallel and anti-movements lack a self-regeneration (for they cut themselves from the cosmic dynamo), they ultimately waste away being crushed by the greater force of the Cosmic potency (18.58, 59, 60, 61). This is the wasteful life (mogha-jīvanaṃ) which the Lord deplores (3.16; 9.12). While suicide results in one’s getting wasted, sacrifice results in one’s getting recreated!

Thus, in this cosmic picture or existence of an ever- dynamic Whole, everything is and by being everything, it functions. And so: 1. the one who aims at sacrifice, in the real sense, is (i.e. exists), and continues (and that which continues ceaselessly is the infinite), and 2. the one who aims to act contrarily becomes wasted materially, trying to build up wasting hopes, wasting actions, and wasting knowledge. These men are demons by nature, who set themselves against the divine and do not participate in the Divine (9.12).

8 The ‘Ways’ – What They Mean

If what we have tried to know is the perspective of Reality as an Infinite Self-re-creative Existence, it is worthwhile to discover from its point of view the meanings of karma, jñāna, and bhakti as forces of non-resilient consolidation and equilibrium. Against the background of what has been presented as loka-saṃgraha the discussion is essential and relevant.

To start with karma. The most direct meaning of ‘karma’ refers to the creative or dynamic phase of the self-projective Reality in its resplendent glory, and so verily, points to the Law of Movement and Creation:

bhūtabhāvodbhavakaraḥ visargaḥ karma samjñitaḥ.

Karma is the name for bringing into being the existents, and points to their discharging of functions (8.3). This is the objective and physical dimension of movement and creation.

The second meaning refers to the initial will, kratu, at the base of all action and creation. It has the touch of sentience, and verily, belongs to the Infinite Whole with a design and purpose, and is represented by the Lord Himself. And its extension is found in the will of the sentient agents. This is the subjective and conative dimension of Being.

There is a third meaning of ‘karma’ as the Vedic ritual, which the Gita mentions, but with which perspective the Gita is not involved. The use of the word ‘yajña’ is not as an alternative to the Vedic ‘karma’, as it is relieved of all its narrow implication and refers to any function or disposition at any level of life and matter in the scheme of Reality.

Karma in its creative and conative aspects not only provides the cue for the dynamic basis of existence, but also links up all activity with the resultant effects both physical and moral, and fixes a responsibility. The concept is so comprehensive that while analyzing it, the Lord introduces us to the varied contents of existence or being – the spiritual and the non-spiritual, or the subjective and the objective. The concept generally touches all subtle and gross manifestations or forms of existence, and binds the whole of Reality as a structure of undivided existence. We shall try to know how the Lord does it, phase by phase.

The Reality which the Lord presents is so overwhelmingly infinite that it includes even the blind and the insentient principle, prakṛti, ever dynamic and active, but acting under the guidance of a conscient purpose, call it ‘God’, or ‘Brahman’ or ‘Self’ – it is immaterial. That is, prakṛti presents both the subtle and the gross states of force and manifestation, wherein we find both the abstract and the concrete illumination and buoyancy (sattva guṇa), change and dynamism (rajas), and darkness, inertia and retardation (tamas). These are the maintaining and driving forces of the universe, and never can one stop them from acting. They refer to the principle of activity or karma at the objective or physical level. It is the inconscient or the unconscious agent of consolidation of the cosmic energy in man and animal, living and non-living, static and dynamic, sub-atomic and galactic, putting forth new forms and new species, new existential situations of physical and biological nature. This energy, which goes by the name of prakṛti, is so universal and pervasive, that any attempt at individualizing it as a packet or a body belonging to either X or Y or Z is a mere presumption built on illusory egoism of a separate existence and separate order. That nobody can stop the physical processes of growth, decay and death, and that all our respiratory, circulatory, digestive, excretory and nervous systems are not managed by us, will bring to the forefront the fact that only so long as the vital energies (the prāṇas) (i.e. manifestations of the cosmic inconscient energy called prakṛti) keep them going[12] we have an arrogant claim of possessing a body, and of having a mastery over it. None can, in his arrogance, stop this, is the verdict of the lord: nigraham kim kariṣyati? (3.33). One of the meanings of ‘karma’ in the Gita is this aspect of the objective dialectics of the cosmic energy beneath the individual and the universal, microcosmic and the macrocosmic. That one cannot idle away uselessly his energies or forget his share of the cosmic function localized at the individual centre is the meaning of a relentless process of karma or Reality consolidating itself. And if one were to dabble with this process or being, he will be devastated in this course of the onward march of the cosmic purpose.

But what is more significant is the treatment of karma at the subjective level of the individual, i.e. of karma as willed action and karma as the result of willed action. It is here the Lord shows Himself as the supreme artist laying down the guidelines for converting what is obviously a routine function or work into an art of cosmic consolidation. That is where karma-yoga comes.

To make one’s life meaningful, the Lord prescribes karma-yoga, the art of subserving the cosmic purpose by smooth-sailing methods of adjustment and harmony, that is, by making perfect the machinery of objective work with no reference to the results or allowing the results to take care of themselves. For, if the machinery is perfect, by the law of necessity, results would be perfect. Hence karma as art (i.e. karma-yoga) is disinterestedness with regard to results and interestedness in attaining perfection at the level of basic operation and consolidation – a crucial qualification for making all work a yoga. Karma-yoga is the wholesome art (yogaḥ karmasu kauśalaṃ) of submitting to the dialectics of the dynamic Reality within oneself and outside, and helping to speed up the process of consolidation, which is not only individual but also cosmic.

What transforms karma into karma-yoga is the additional qualification in the dynamics of function, which goes by the name jñāna (wisdom). Jñāna is not, as is ordinarily taken, an exclusive ivory-towerish intellectual pursuit of any reality, nor is it any academic or theoretic analyzing of what the Self is and what it is not, or what the perishable is and what it is not. It is not even the cultivation of intellectual Puritanism to keep one’s fingers locked up from material dirt. If we are to understand the true perspective of the picture of depersonalisation of the Lord and of dismemberment of the Cosmic personality, and of how the Lord Himself is involved in the act of sacrifice, which is the regenerative creative activity, we may be able to understand that jñāna is sentience (another aspect of the very Reality that is dynamic) giving a direction to the cosmic existence and purpose, and energizing the movement at cosmic consolidation. It is Consciousness at work in its most universal meaning both within the lowest of the creatures and in the most highly developed. If at the cosmic level, all activity we see in prakṛti is because of the direction given to it by that principle of Consciousness, at the individual level, jīva is the sentient manifestation of that consciousness brought into being to illumine and consolidate a comparatively smaller field, a localised field of reference, with all its potentialities to subserve the purpose of the non-local or universal Reality (9.8.9; and 7.5; 15.7).

Where exactly karma and jñāna come together as aspects of cosmic consolidation is quite evident in the Lord’s teaching. What is inconscient or mechanical is to be illumined by a light that is not physical. This is the place where sentience comes in: an activity (karmic or dynamic process of Reality) is now understood as such, and a conscious participation in the working of the cosmic theme is intended. This is jñāna-yoga or buddhi-yoga. If karma-yoga is dexterity in action, jñāna-yoga is intelligence in action. Action and intelligence both being aspects of a self-consolidating Reality, a successful individual is one who lends himself consciously to the purpose, i.e., who works to bring about what is obviously a factor contributing to the consolidation of a universal purpose. So, he works with a luminous disposition, and his work is a duty and a responsibility, but not ones imposed by an external agency. The duty and responsibility are expressions of an inner dialectics of the cosmic theme working itself under the illumination of the conscious principle which is primordially behind all existence and action, a principle which is not different from the individual now acting. This is the deepest significance of the phrases ‘ātma-rataḥ’, ‘ātma-saṃtuṣṭaḥ’ (3.17). He is a ‘dhīra’ both in intellect (i.e., wise) and in courage (i.e., brave). He is the one who has his senses under control both during the best circumstances and worst of tragedies. He is the one who is fixed in and about theoria, and never wavers to apply it, as others are prone to, at each turn of action. Undaunted by anger or hate, greed, love or egoism, he is the supreme example in manifestation (i.e., as a man) of the Cosmic Law operating. He is fully awake to Reality and in this he is totally different from the rest of humanity – he is a sthitaprajña, a bhakta and a jñāni (2.54-72; 12.13-19).

If karma is the objective Reality in its dynamic aspect, karma-yoga is a conscious serving with dexterity of skill. It is spiritual lubrication causing smoother flow of things. It is planning. It is carrying out the movement of consolidation without waste. Likewise, if jñāna is the principle of illumination and sentience, jñāna-yoga is consciousness of the dynamics or dialectics of Reality as a whole, requiring one to consciously participate in its purpose by giving it the glow of intelligent responsibility, and investing meaning to all action and manipulating into a helpful technique of service. (4.6-9, 13-14, 19, 20-24). On the plane that is envisaged, and in the scale that is held out, Reality is the unending, unexcluding and all-sustaining principle (as is shown by the Lord in the chapter of Viśwarūpa Darśanaṃ, wherein each individual is assured a meaningful existence, provided a harmony is struck in him of jñāna and karma. This is the view of Reality one is invited to have through a heightened vision (divya-cakṣuḥ, 11.8).

Now, turning to bhakti. The application of jñāna and karma to serve the cosmic theme in thought and action with an unswerving concentration and absorption is bhakti. What gives intensity to a purpose and warmth to a participation is this absorption, which is bhakti. The widest and the most universal application of it or the practice of it covering the whole of cosmos – the far and the near, the living and the non-living, form and the formless – is the test of its efficacy in achieving the cosmic purpose (6.29-31, 9.55, 12.12-19, 9.29, 18.54). No single part or aspect of Reality is exclusively reserved or selected for its pre-occupation. If so, to restrict its meaning and treat it with an exclusiveness of an identity and form (i.e. a conceptually understandable form of a person, for example,) would be to render it weak and not strong. Calling bhakti a technique is to deprive it of its identity and directing it to the universal, formless or impersonal is to miss the purpose behind. It has been a manifestation only to serve the largest and the inscrutable dimension of the Real or Reality. And in this, bhakti does not lose, but gains. What may be lost as emotional content is gained by the basic experience of the Infinity by absorption. He is the bhakta who sees the finite as the Infinite and Infinite in all the finites (6.29-30). What is lost as one’s separate identity is gained by the expansion of being the whole or in its all-inclusive identity with Reality. What shapes this vision or bhakti is the illumination regarding the dimensions of the Real arising out of a first-hand participation which is so basic, deep and universal that nothing could stand comparison to it. This is the real participation which the Lord recommends and gives it a distinction by calling it ‘My Yoga’ (madyogaṃ), as if it were different from all the other types of yoga we may be speaking of. An elaboration of the nature of what the Lord calls ‘His yoga’ will occupy us a little later.

Now, with regard to the success or failure of an endeavour consciously pursued: while karma is rendered into karma-yoga and jñāna into jñāna-yoga[13] , i.e. where skill and intelligence are utilized in the scheme of consolidation, one may develop an egoism which is undesirable, viz. developing an over-confidence that he would and is bound to succeed and not fail. However, the problem of success or failure is to be viewed not only individually but from the point of view of Reality itself. The Lord directs us to develop this perspective and says that even to think of succeeding is wrong. He points out that for anybody’s success the individual is not solely responsible. There are more causes than one, at least five (pañcaitāni kāraṇāni – 18.13), to be specific, which include the adhyātmika, adhibhautika, and adhidaivika. The purpose of the Lord in drawing one’s attention to this is quite clear: to point out the insignificant or minor part of an individual effort in the accomplishment of a deed, and to show how the responsibility is dispersed over a larger sphere and on different subtle or gross conditions constituting Reality in its unfathomable dimension, because it is the whole of Reality that is operating at any particular point of existence. And so, it is not so much the desire or calculation of success as a result that should be the objective of a conscious act, but work itself.

This is karma-yoga. Looked at from the larger perspective of Reality, there seems to be absolutely no difference between success and failure. It is as if that the Lord asks us not to take to him a list of our successes, but those of our failures. Perhaps, He values these latter more because of the element of disinterestedness which will have gone into the endeavour. Also, it is valued more for the element of cautiousness in avoiding a wrong. But really there is nothing like a failure in this Reality, if ever the intensions are pure and unmixed with egoism, and directed to serve the Cosmic function.

This amounts to saying that no work or function is purely individual, but is cosmic. And in this, failure is not lost, nor even the failing (2.40; 6.40). No one absorbed in this dies (na me bhaktaḥ praṇaśyati – 9.31). Perhaps, the Lord expects us thus to be lost in it! More than once He seems to demand this and calls a person thus lost a ‘Yogi’. And this ‘losing’ is the absorption which the Lord speaks of as ‘His yoga’. It is surrender to the highest wisdom without any tinge of an arrogance or conceit that may be lurking beneath the attitude of a jñāni egoistically trying to participate with an absolute sense of success. It is surrender total and complete of one’s individuality or personality, without the sense of a residual self that may be lurking in the heart of a bhakta. It is surrender of indifference and laziness to gear up the best of skills in manipulating things that may be lurking in the action of a karmin (18.57-58, 66). A participation, if it is wholesome, requires a rounding off the edges between and amongst what we ordinarily take as exclusive ways, viz. jñāna, bhakti, and karma. At each stage, the Divine purpose or consolidation requires these to be refined and be made complementary (3.4, 4.18-19). With the transformation of a mechanical action into an enlightened duty, and with the dislodging of egoistic arrogance by surrender and absorption, the individual is metamorphosed into the universal or cosmic. That is, he is lost, but really he is not lost. This is the meaning of the Lord’s assurance: na me bhaktaḥ praṇaśyati (9.31).

The transformation which comes over the individual centre of action is that it ceases to function as an isolated factor or individual, but becomes the Infinite working at any centre (matkarmakṛt – 11.55, 12.10). The law of infinity is such that any point in it is its centre, and from anywhere it can work, and while working, can consolidate and conserve. This is the state of the Lord. He calls it madbhāva and says that anyone who lends himself to be the centre of an Infinite existence is doing matkarma (‘my function’). Such a vision should naturally rouse a sense of fulfillment in each centre (i.e., the individual beings), for as it functions, it shares the being and purpose of the Infinite, and success and failure are just immaterial (2.38, 57). This is the sense in which the Lord says, obviously in contradictory terms:

I have no work to do in these three universes, but if I do not function, the world will collapse (3.22-24).

I have no wants, but I want people to follow me (3.22-23).

This is the philosophy of Karma-yoga or Recoilless Action, which the Lord is presenting. And He does it not in the way a human being presents a speculative description of Reality, but as an actual analysis of the dynamics of His own being and of how He exists and functions.

9The Lord’s Dictum – “Nothing Less Than My Yoga”

Perhaps this is the proper place to elaborate on a point of very great importance raised a little while ago and follow up the argument to show that the Lord’s most significant evaluation of jñāna, karma, and bhakti is that they are not to be unconditionally accepted just because they bear the appellation yoga, for if they do not answer a particular description or do not work themselves up to a pitch, they cannot be called yoga as such. This is of crucial importance in view of the fact that the Lord speaks of a ‘yoga of His own’ (madyoga) (12.11); He declares: “Behold My bountiful yoga” (paśya me yogamaiśwaraṃ – 11.7), and showed His mystifying and bountiful dimension of being (11.9).

What is this yoga which is His own, a bountiful one, of which He is the Īśwara (Yogeśwara)?

Perhaps, here is a hint we should gather that His Yoga is not a means to an end, but is essentially an ontological state of existence. This sense gets confirmed when the Lord says: “See My yoga,” and unfolds what is known as ‘Viśwarūpa’. Obviously, then, from the simple meaning of ‘yoga’ to what the Lord calls ‘His yoga’ it is a long way, and we are to discover the inner meaning or dialectics of this ‘Kṛṣṇa yoga’, if we may call it so, and perhaps, in the illumination that may dawn on us we gather what we are after.

Let us start with simple statements which occur in the Gita about the meaning of ‘yoga’. An ordinary study will make us think of yoga as skill in action (yogaḥ karmasu kauśalaṃ – 2.50), or as harmony or balance (samatvam yoga ucyate – 2.48), even as the Lord helps us to pick these phrases as possible definitions.

However, are we to go by the colophon and take the despondency of Arjuna (viṣāda) a yoga? Would that be consistent with the above definitions suggested of ‘yoga’? As per the colophon, each of the chapters is called a ‘yoga’, and note that the term is not limited to things well known as karma, jñāna, and bhakti.

Then, shall we understand by ‘yoga’ the one enunciated, for example, by Patanjali? The Lord seems to refer to breath control and control of mental states (8.12; 6.20), but that is not yoga which the Lord is expecting from us. Had it been so, the Gita would not have added anything more than the Yoga-Sūtras in our understanding of Reality. While Patanjali’s yoga is a means or technique to achieve a viyoga or separation, we cannot with any sense of propriety apply it to karma, jñāna and bhakti. In fact, these imply anything but viyoga, and certainly, chapter titles like Puruṣottama Yoga, Viśwarūpadarśana Yoga and such do not imply viyoga, i.e., disconnection.

Then, what of yoga as balance or harmony, i.e., samatvaṃ? Is it equilibrium of the mind? If so, how can viṣāda in Arjuna-Viṣāda Yoga be a yoga? Is it equilibrium of the mind as in Patanjali Yoga? We have seen that it is not. Or is it balance among things of equal potency or power or status or of any other form of being, or balance between opposite and unequal things or forces? What is obvious to the eye is that things are not equal, nor are forces equal. Is equilibrium equipoise of some sort? If so, insentient nature can attain it, and a pond of muddy water in that way could be equivalent to an undisturbed mind achieved by concentration! And if all these do not mean samatvaṃ, we ask, in a scheme of Reality what is balance between the temporal and the non-temporal, the finite and the infinite, the one and the many? Are these opposites, and if so, how are they held? Is it that they cancel out their opposition by what is known as the dynamics of opposition, as we find it in the electromagnetic field, wherein a reconciliation or balance is arrived at in the form of a unity, i.e. samatvaṃ?

Evidently, yoga is not simply to be disposed of as a simple skill or balance (and ‘skill’ in its baser sense can be vile craftiness, and, as such, cannot be recommended by the Lord). The skill and balance that the Lord speaks of are of a higher order where cancellation by the dynamics of opposition is ruled out by the mystery which constitutes Infinity, which assimilates varieties and opposites by a law normally unavailable in the realm of abstractions, that is, when individual elements are torn off a structure and viewed as distincts or opposites.

The implication of yoga as samatvaṃ is something more of an incommensurate and infinite character, and should be viewed from the point of Reality, which not only does not cancel anything, but also does not stop at anything. The dialectics of samatvaṃ of the Lord’s conception goes beyond the synthesis of a logical opposition between a thesis and an antithesis, and of the physical opposition between the positive and the negative, and resolves the tangle of opposition on a higher plane of ekatvaṃ or unity[14] , the mystery of which the Lord alone can tell us:

The attuned (yogī) who is thus absorbed in Infinity sees himself in every existent, and every existent in himself always and with equal intensity (whether a being is small or big, subtle or concrete, animal or man).

Whoever sees Me everywhere (i.e. in everything and as everything), and everything in Me, him I never lose, nor he ever loses Me.

Whoever adores Me as existing in all existents in a super-identity (ekatvaṃ), in whatever conditions he be, is an attuned (yogī) and lives in Me.

Whether it is pleasure or pain, the one who sees the same everywhere as like unto himself is the highest attuned (parama-yogī), according to Me (6.29-32).

He who is in unity sees unity. That is the yoga which the Lord points out through these verses. He has set before us an ideal of all yogas, viz. His own yoga, having an import wherein separation and imbalance are dissolved at the existential level of Reality. This is virtually His being, and no end is higher than this state and no values higher than this Yoga.

If one tries to recapitulate the occasions when the Lord speaks of His yoga as the ‘highest’ (paramaṃ yogaḥ) and of that Yogi as the ‘best’ (yuktatama), one will be astonished not only at the number of times when this Yoga is mentioned, but realizes also how one will have missed its import in the gamble of the other yogas not tuned up properly, the often-mentioned of them being karma, jñāna and bhakti, which are mistaken as techniques of reaching ideals.

There has always been a warning in the teaching of the Lord that within the cosmic field and with the potentialities available for every man, he can gear up his strength, intelligence, cleverness and concentration to attain a siddhi, but it may after all be ill-oriented. In one of the most suggestive pieces of his disclosing the highest truth (Jñāna-Vijñāna Yoga), the Lord remarks how very easy it is for men of great ability to fall a prey to the obvious, i.e., to the concrete, the empirical and the worldly (all these are connoted by prakṛti or objectivity and its manifestations), and how difficult it is to overcome the delusion of these lesser ideals or even achievements. The warning is so very implicit (7.13-15), yet, if we pass it by, sure as it is, we are condemned to relativity. And what makes for this relativity is to be sought not only for understanding the end by which the delusions of the world are overcome, but also for evaluating the worth of every bit of the lower values, or for assessing the existents (7.4-5).[15] We come across in our spiritual life and experience such existents, viz. the abstract and the concrete, the inner and the outer, the dynamic and the static, the elemental and the godly, and the source of all being which is Infinity, and how it maintains, conserves and consolidates itself over and above these opposed and contradictory elements.

… those who seek refuge in Me can know everything: the Infinite, the Self, the dynamics of being. Whoever knows Me along with the basically elemental, the basically Divine and the basic Sacrifice … know Me (7.29-30).

There is a pole star here which should orient all our march, viz. the Me (mama). We have seen earlier the significance of the capital ‘I’ as the ontological dynamo sustaining everything that has being, and now, it is ‘Me’, and all other forms of this pronoun which should be understood as the state towards which all aspirations, movements and conditions tend.

Look at these terms, the Lord repeats:

matparaḥ, mayyāveśya, maccittā, madgata prāṇā, manmanā, matkarmakṛtu, matparāyaṇa, madāśrayā, matsaṃsthā, mayyāsakta, etc. etc.

The Yoga that’s oriented thus is madyoga (13.11).

And there has been a clear indication in the teaching of the Lord that a Yogi of this qualification is superior to all who may have the capacity to be a tapasvin, a jñāni or a karmin. Arjuna is directed to go beyond these to be a Yogi (capital ‘Y’ – 6.46), and is told, “Whoever among all the yogis dissolves everything (including himself) in Myself and is lost in devotion to Me is the superlative Yogin (yuktatama)” (6.47).

A buddhi-yoga, a saṃnyāsa-yoga or a karma-yoga which have no fundamental understanding of this are just skills and not Yoga in the real sense that the Lord is anxious to convey. He indicates that there is a cosmic or divine purpose, and that one who is not in the grip of its dialectics is wasting his time, if he is merely straining to attain citta vṛtti nirodha. Such a one is only showing a skill. The Lord says, “I bestow buddhi-yoga so that he may attain Me.” And there is something more. The Lord speaks out to the dismay and discomfiture of the highly cultivated in all yogas and in moral conduct that even without these, or bypassing these, the end could be attained by the unsophisticated and the lowly:

Even if one is of mean character (or of bad manners), if devoted to me unflinchingly, he is to be known as good-souled, as he is fixed in the right order or theoria (9.30).

And by this right devotion he becomes transformed. He is to be considered a dharmātmā (‘good-souled’), i.e., essentially a carrier of the cosmic law which sustains and nourishes all beings, and he attains undisturbed peace.

Know, My devotee is never lost! (i.e. not wasted away) (9.31).

And the same is true of people born sinfully, or if one is a woman, a business man or a śūdra (9.32-33).

Renouncing all dharmas (resorts) surrender to Me (the final resort), and I shall redeem you from all sins (18.66).

And these sins are not merely moral, but can also be lapses in any field of one’s being – intellectual, concentrational or devotional. The implication is quite evident: chastity and perfection are naturally his who is faultless in thought, feeling and action, and no birth or depravity affects him who has the resolve, the right dharma, the Me.

And, now, returning to the original question – though it is answered by now – “What is this Yoga which the Lord said He is going to present (paśya me yoga maiśwaraṃ)?” He says, it is not only to be seen, but also to be authentically entered into, i.e. experienced (…draṣṭuṃ ca tattvena praveṣṭuṃ ca – 11.54). What is that intuitive vision of Reality and experiential knowledge which one gets of such Yoga and by which the Lord expects each yogin to think of Reality as Reality itself may think of him? We will have to find the answers in the very Viśwarūpa which the Lord is and which is not present only at a particular time or occasion as we may ordinarily presume. The answer is to be seen in the unity that is constitutive of Reality – including the individuals that may be gazing, even as Arjuna did. It is a unity which is so overwhelming and basic that, within the sweep of its being, each element, movement, impulse, direction, and so on, become inextricably one with Reality, and never can be alien to the being of it. The depersonalisation of the Lord is not the disappearance of the individual, but is the appearance of Him as everything, wherein everything is fitted into the pattern of a wholeness (surpassing considerations of logical consistency), and nothing is pitched against the other. How many ways the Lord chooses to drive this point in! We are required to ponder over statements such as: “The Lord is everything” (sarvam vāsudevaḥ) (7.19), and see that the yogi should understand this unity, and “be established in it, worshipping Him as abiding in all,” and that “he alone is a Yogi who lives in the Lord, whatever be the mode of his being (6.31).” “The Lord is the Cosmic-acosmic law,” and sharing the dialectics of the law (brahma yoga yuktātmā – 5.21) is the real Yoga. It is hardly necessary to elaborate.

Still, what is pertinent to understand and feel is that karma, jñāna, bhakti – and innumerable other ways – are points of consolidation of energy and purpose of that law, that they are ontological or existential, having value in themselves, and that they are not to be treated as techniques by which something else is realized in time through a process of operation. Forgetting this, we may commit an underestimation of what the Lord calls ‘My yoga’. It is a state of existence which has no orientation other than this. And if that is so, at any level of existence and operation, any element, function or impulse is in its purest form, and is a sample of being in its non-temporally eternal harmony (śāśvata śānti – 18.62); that is, when effort is, but with no idea of a result, when work is not just physical, but has a glow of sentience, when sentience is, but is with an absorption which is never partial and individual but universal. Is it possible to achieve this by anyone at any single moment? If so, that seems to be the state (yoga) which the Lord speaks of as ‘His’. How can there be something beyond it, for Infinity is concentred therein? Perhaps, if we can have the picture of our bosom projected on a screen in a three dimensional fashion, and have a look at the elements constituted within and working, we may have the approximate vision which the Lord gave to Arjuna in which the individual is shown to be working within as an element, and shown how that element is being asked to acquire a condition of Yoga fulfilling the demands of the plan and purpose of the universe in which he finds himself.

This is the demand of the Lord: to convert karma into a Yoga, jñāna into a Yoga, and bhakti into a yoga, where yoga is existential, where skill is natural, wisdom is the beacon light, absorption is the ticking breath, and undisturbed harmony is the law. This is a demand not to run for an end in the far off distance, but to convert each second of existence into an end in itself, and to treat each strife as the goal.

When the Lord declared: “See My divine bountiful Yoga,” he gave us the first phenomenological intimation of a super existential or natural state. We are initiated into a pre-logical, pre-relational state wherein all the possible logical and relative quibbles fall out of their oppositions and find their natural or spontaneous resolution. One who comes to possess such a gifted eye to witness a state of natural harmony of things which are apparently contradictory is not only relieved of his logical doubts, but also overcomes an existential self-alienation, which constitutes his liberation. We shall see of this immediately.

10Liberation – Freedom In Participation

Against the background of the philosophy of cosmic consolidation of yajña, yoga and karma that has been set forth, the idea of liberation in the Gita turns out to be very unique and dynamic: liberation is life itself! If liberation, in the ordinary naïve sense, is an escape from life, and life a degenerate condition of the Self, the Gita presents a perspective which is the reverse. The expansion of the meaning of ‘life’ and ‘liberation’ here is so vast and basic that it is seldom grasped, and so, with that the significance of the active participation of an individual in the cosmic dialectics (which has set up every form of living or life) is lost sight of. One is brought in here to life to lead a life of liberation. For, the occasioning of life is according to a cosmic plan, and one who lives according to the plan is an instance of the cosmic truth fulfilled in freedom. This is exactly the opposite of the normal conception by which we think that one’s birth is only a fall from an original freedom and perfection.

If life is living with Reality in a way that is yoga, ‘yoga’ standing for the most harmonious, most balanced way of a wholesome art, with a consciousness that none lives for himself, with the implication that that man’s being is built into the core of Reality of a self-regenerative sacrifice and continuity (Yajña), and with the demand that one to lead a trans-individual life at all times, the meaning of both ‘life’ and ‘liberation’ gets widened and clarified. Any significant life is to be in tune with this, and no liberation can be true liberation if this is forgotten. The hopes of a heaven hereafter, of getting into a loka after death, is perhaps foreign to the spirit of the teaching of the Lord. If one keeps track of the way the Lord asks anyone to be a Yogī, he finds Him ruling out the meaning of mukti as an eschatological ideal.[16] The svarga (or heaven) the Lord offers to Arjuna to win by fighting is that of living well as demanded by the Cosmic Law (svadharma of a kṣatriya)[17] in a spirit that is yajña, and/or of dying a death, by which one does not reappear.[18] The setting of this world in the scheme of things – the extent of which is, however, not to be limited to the geographical or global limits of our understanding – seems to be so planned that all divine functions can only be done here and that heaven is not elsewhere than in fulfilling one’s functions. In this unusually set world the Lord Himself commissions the fulfillment. This is a significant reversal of the common idea of escape from life, which is nurtured in ignorance.

But this is not making the world much or making it the centre of all aspirations. The philosophy of the Gita is not materialism of the sort which considers nothing beyond the purely physical and mundane. By ‘world’ it only means the field of work (kṣetra)[19] and beyond that no materialistic import is to be found in the spirit of the Gita. The ‘material’, no doubt, is coterminous with the ‘spiritual’, but only from the point of view of life which is occasioned by the cosmic theme (13.19). According to the Gita, to live with matter, but not be bound by it, is the cue for a transcendental living, which is existence, and is the cue for understanding what liberation is. The Lord points out very significantly:

Whoever sees the secret of the Field and the Knower by the (intuitive) eye of wisdom, and the way of freedom from the elements of Nature goes to the highest limits of being (13.34).

This is transcendental living in which the distinction between the subject and the object is clearly kept in view, but both are kept engaged in the service of the cosmic theme. It is also transcendental living, where transcendence is not going beyond or escaping the field of cosmic dynamics. With reference to the Lord Himself, there is the transcendental life, wherein He lives with prakṛti, for it is His nature (svabhāvo adhyātmaṃ ucyate – 8.3). Understood thus, perhaps we have here an unparalleled conception of what constitutes life in its most divine or metaphysical sense, far beyond the physical or biological living. The Lord is the symbol of this unique metaphysical living in which His svabhāva is never His master, but acts at His beck and call (prakṛtim svāmavaṣṭabhya visṛjāmi – 9.8), and works under the direction of the Lord (mayādhyakṣhena prakṛtim sūyate – 9.10). Can we understand this perspective of life and mastery? If so, we will have understood what liberation is in its most comprehensive, trans-individual and transcendental sense.

It is on this pattern the individual being is expected to live and be in liberation. And there has been a recurrent theme in the Gita which tells us that the physical and the values that are physical – the lure of matter – should always be set at naught (indriyārtheṣu vairāgyaṃ – 13.8). In fact, the entire philosophy of the Gita centres round the theme of understanding what constitutes the root of all Reality hidden beyond this gross materiality (yoga māyā samāvṛtaḥ – 8.25), a materiality which always throws a screen of delusion on the ignorant (7.15). A direction is given to discover the transcendental existence (paraṃ bhāva) beyond the smokescreen that materiality throws around. To attain the condition of param bhāva is salvation, but this is not a hereafter or a hypothetical condition of a heaven. To cut the veil of māyā of the guṇas and to participate in Reality is the same as being in the brāhmī sthiti associated with the life of a sthita-prajña.

11The Human Example

The concept of liberation in the Gita is to be understood from two concrete illustrations available in the text itself – one is that of Krishna, the transcendental Lord Himself, and two, that of Janaka, a human being implied in the text as serving the best example of a sthitaprajña.

At the level of the Lord, who is the transcendental principle, the source of all being, life consists in being everywhere and being within everything, and liberation consists in not being subjected or tainted. This is transcendental or metaphysical life and liberation, and the Lord elaborates them in great detail and emphasis (8th and 13th chapters). We shall be devoting ourselves to this in the next section.

But, for the present, we shall consider what it means to live and have liberation at the human level, as exemplified by a person, a sthitaprajña of the type of Janaka. However, the best prelude to the understanding of the state called sthita- prajñatva is to clarify it in terms of what is called samādhi, a state, which is more often mistaken for quietude or, in a lesser sense, inactivity, as in a person – with no prejudice to his evolved condition – who may be in meditation and lost in it, but pinned down to a static position. For all practical purposes, the stativity of one in samādhi is physical, but not the whole of it. To be more precise, it does not touch the core of what constitutes the essence of samādhi. For the Gita, samādhi is a state of full awakenness or awareness. It is the attention fixed in the theoria or the truth of the Self or Existence. It is consciousness not getting split by the divisions in the objective world. And a person in that state is all active (if ‘activity’ means anything physical) like any one of us. He eats, speaks, walks, and so on (5.8-9), but with an orientation completely different and not available with us who may be constantly doing all those things.

This state of samādhi, to which the Lord refers, is not simply a possible experience of a philosopher’s conception of an experience always ‘around the corner’, but is an actual one lived here. One who has risen to that level lives in the immediate presence of Brahman or Reality (brahma saṃsparśa – 6.28). It is an experience available here, and one is ‘lost’ in it (abhito brahma nirvāṇaṃ – 6.26). He is a person whose consciousness is turned into a transcendental condition (paraṃ bhāva), which ordinary imagination fails to grasp. As contrasted with one who is in brahma yoga (5.21), those who are after kāma (desire) speak of only svarga (heaven) as an idea and wish to be born there; and so, they perform many and varied rituals seeking pleasure and comfort (2.43). This is desire for life unconnected with Reality, such as life lived by those who do not have intuitions of the Real. The significance of the Lord’s statement: dharmāviruddho kāmo’smi (7.11), is lost sight of by us. It is kāma or desire in consonance with dharma, the Universal Law of Being. At this stage, and in this capacity, kāma becomes universal love as expressed in the other statements of the Lord: “with no ill-will to any being, being friendly and compassionate, with no attachment and with nothing like selfishness” (12.12); and “with no hatred toward any existent” (11.15). And all this flowing from an understanding that the principle of dharma exists in all equally (6.31). The reward for such living in tune with Reality is peace, the aspiration of all aspirations (2.71), which a sthitaprajña or a Yogī has in abundance.

There is yet another point which may require mention here. There has been a reference, no doubt, to a ‘travel’ through uttarāyaṇa or dakṣiṇāyana, or through śukla or kṛṣṇa paths (the northern and the southern, or the white and the black paths, 8.24-25). But these do not suggest a crossing over a distance to attain a place of one’s highest aspiration. Even in the passages where they do occur, the end that has been laid down is symbolic and suggestive of the dynamic philosophy of cosmic consolidation wherein all are absorbed (the living and the dead) and assimilated into the being of Infinity, which, as being, ever is, and is an ever inexhaustible ideal. It is said that one who travels by the ‘black’ path (both literally and metaphorically) is reborn, i.e., gets back his physical body (āvartate punaḥ – 8.26), for obviously, it has not served the purpose or is not utilised well while living; and one who travels by the ‘white’ path (both literally and metaphorically) is assimilated into the dynamics of Reality, or becomes Reality itself, and is not reborn, i.e., does not come back to have a body in a physical context (yāti anāvṛttiṃ – 8.26). It is the end that is not physical, but an end to be the basis of all that is physical, and an end to be the power which keeps or sustains the physical. It becomes the real living force which sustains the universe and is not subordinate to it (jīvabhūtāṃ yayedaṃ dhāryate jagat – 7.5) – call it the cosmic law (prakṛtīṃ parāṃ – 7.5) or the Lord’s nature (adhyātma), it is immaterial. This is the life of Spirit, which is liberation.

If we are to understand this picture of Reality and life in the manner we have tried to do, it would be easier for us to grasp the import of liberation as active participation in its dynamics, which is to be attained by living a life of the Spirit rather than that of a carnal body, and by living up to a purpose that is cosmic beyond the logos of private existence. Such people are the Yogīs or the ‘always liberated’ (sadā muktaḥ – 5.28).

With this preliminary or basic understanding of what constitutes life and liberation at both trans-individual (or cosmic: parā) and individual (iha) levels, it would be interesting to know how a sthitaprajña as a living human individual keeps up in his life a running bond between the two realms of his own being, the transcendental or the non-relative and the empirical or the relative, and always keeps clear of the snares that the latter may throw on a person. A sthitaprajña presents a reflection in him, or is himself an epitome, of the Cosmic Person, living here with the physical, yet undaunted by the empirical contingencies of life. He stands for one who is a master in managing the affairs of life, viz. matter and spirit, in a way in which his spirit is not cowed down, and he lives above the dualities among which he lives, but is not caught up by their snares. Not allowing himself to be a slave of instinct or impulse (sensual or emotional), he is the master who causes the mind to serve him (2.64), for it is the mind which is the ‘enemy on the way’ to be controlled (2.60, 67).

Rooted in the unity of the Self and finding all fulfillments in it (ātmanye atmanā tuṣṭaḥ, 2.55), he sees across pain and pleasure, and through hatred and love, and rises above them, for he is established on the bedrock of equanimity natural to the Self, which has found its depths or dimensions, as it were (12.16-19). He has ātma prasāda, and his mind is prasanna (2.64, 65). This is being in peace with oneself, and on the strength and illumination of it he sees peace outside (2.66). This is the metaphysical awakening (i.e. real jñāna which the Lord calls ‘jñāna-vijñāna), which is beyond the merely psychological in which the mind functions with the aid of the indriyas and passes for a state of consciousness (jāgrat), which it is really not. The Lord asks us to discover the real principle of consciousness which is always awake beyond the wakeful and sleeping states. And it is in this sense that the sthitaprajña is called an instance of a consciousness fully and always awake, i.e., operating at all times, but with a natural mastery over all that is purely material and worldly. Under the illuminations of this awakened condition, the polarity or parallelism of the mind faking itself as the principle of consciousness is broken. That is, it is not made to act as the Self, but for the Self. Thus broken of its vital existence, the dichotomizing effect of the mind is subdued, and for the person thus awakened metaphysically the “night of the ordinary folk is day, and the day of the ordinary is night” (2.69). That is, he sees the truth when others are blind to it, and when others indulgingly see, he is withdrawn (2.58). This is an evaluational attitude of a sthitaprajña who has discovered the most basic standard by which all the empirical and contingent is judged. From the awareness that he has, he orders and groups things in life, fixes their interrelations amongst themselves and with Reality, but keeps himself away from the entanglements of the lower existents and values.

Thus a sthitaprajña is one whose prajña or awareness is in a state of unaffected chastity or purity with regard to both truth and existence, and while he exists in life, he is unaffected by its divisions and dualities. In other words, leading a life with us, he shows what it is to be a master and not a slave to life. The indifference (udāsīnatva or anāsakti) that such a person is found to be showing towards the world and its forms does not stem from a weakness, but arises from a strength which helps him ably to manage them. He is dakṣa or strong (12.16) where others are weak, he is steady (sthita) where others are shaky. Free from all desires of a carnal nature, he moves about untouched by any egoistic taint and verily qualifies himself to a state of peace (2.71). This is liberation or freedom, for it is the life of the Spirit in which the Spirit lives as Spirit and never as something else.

For a superficial eye the teaching of the Gita, in this aspect, may seem to be one that advocates asceticism or escapism hardly relevant to the situation where dynamism is needed. But for a deeper understanding, this asceticism of a sthitaprajña is no asceticism of a weak-minded man, but of a strong man who has risen above the strongest of infatuations, the pulls of personal gains and losses, and of personal glory and power. It is the symbol of the power of equanimity over the weakness of will and mind, which ultimately leads to a disaster even the non-ascetic cannot invite on himself (2.62-63). An activism that does not have an inner calm is bound to bluster away into withering, and the calmness (śānti, manaḥ-prasāda, prasanna-citta) that characterizes the sthitaprajña is the symbol of the power hidden underneath. It is a calmness that comes with truth, a calmness which can bear all the flutter of the world, including its destruction!

And, with regard to pessimism ascribed as a characteristic of the ‘indifferent’ sthitaprajña, it is again a misunderstanding of the state of being in which he is. It is not only that the transcendental state of the Lord is missed by such ascriptions, but the state in which the sthitaprajña lives transcendentally and functions passes beyond the comprehension of such estimates. It is forgotten that here is an awakened person (a jāgartī – 2.69) who is fully aware of the course of things beyond the horizons of ordinary perception.

Not that a sthitaprajña is pessimistic nor that he lacks initiative, but being an active participant in the hidden dialectics of Reality, he is not to begin a work afresh, for he has begun it long ago. The significance of the Lord’s statement, sarvārambha parityāgī, is lost on us (12.16; 14.25). He picks up a work and only continues it, for in the logos of the Cosmic consolidation the work is going on, and what is the beginning of it? Perhaps, there is no beginning! Can we understand this meaning hidden in the bowels of the Law of Infinity? The understanding of sthitaprajña crosses through the divisions of time (like the Lord Himself – 2.12) by which alone the ordinary mortal measures himself and all his activity. He, in his cloistered vision between one’s temporal birth and death of the body (2.18), thinks a work is begun by him at a time and finished at a particular time. But the sthitaprajña knows and sees that no work is ended in the dynamics of existence. This is a consciousness of continuity running through moments called ‘individualities’ (2.20, 22) on the canvas of Infinity.

And, with regard to the feeling that overruns the mind which thinks that all endeavour or effort is going to be absorbed in the final vacuity of a predestined scheme, it should be said that such a feeling sadly misses the point. For nothing is absorbed and made effete, but is built up into a larger whole which gathers mass and meaning in the shape of the cosmic theme working itself up (nehābhikrama nāśosti pratyavāyo na vidyate – 2.40). The Lord assures us that in this scheme no life is lived in vain. For the best in each species, the Lord says, is His manifestation (vibhūti) and is the result of a multifaceted sacrifice. If once we understand the subtle shades of the description of the Lord’s glorious province (see the Vibhūti Yoga), we come out with a sense of fulfillment far beyond our isolated and individual existence. We realize that we are a continuation of the past, that we have assimilated into our present and individual being the sacrifice of the millions, or of our own previous births, and that we continue into the future.

With this understanding, we may come up to live a life of hope with a sense of fulfillment. In the scheme of cosmic consolidation no work is individual, nor is it begun individually. No achievement is individual, nor does it come to an end shattered against the walls of predestination. Whoever understands infinite life (2.16-30) understands the state of a sthitaprajña as surpassing evaluations by the temporal and empirical standards, even as the ways of the cosmic or the divine law cannot be submitted to these standards.

We find in the Gita a significant equation made of a sthitaprajña with a Yogi, a bhakta or a jñāni in the true sense. They are interchangeable terms, and this is true with regard to those in whom the ideal of liberation has found its actualisation. We find in such a person a rare instance of an ideal, realisation and being coinciding indivisibly. The insight of the Gita as to what constitutes liberation is to be seen in the descriptions of the life that such people are shown to live.[20] We have already noted much of this description, but how they assess the world of their living, the values empirical and material, and how they live among them yet untouched by them is significant for us to know. Standing on the bedrock of essential truth – call it ātman (Self) or Brahman (Infinity) – they know what is relative or contingent and see them as such, allow them to play, but not taking anything from them or taken in by them. For them the earth is there, but the lure of it is gone; relativity is there, but its necessity is overcome. This is the power of the Spirit over matter, the devaluation of the latter’s strength to involve the Spirit. It is the mastery of the Spirit over the necessity of the object and the consequent enslavement of it.

That liberation of a person is not to be sought beyond the physical death is the implication of the person called sthitaprajña, described as being in the brāhmī sthiti. Hardly do we understand this. We ought to know that physical death is not the evidence of liberation, and that the physical is not the only death. Any liberation that is hoped to be achieved after physical death (videha mukti) is to be evidenced here and proved against bondage, or else, it becomes simply hypothetical.

Against the background of the philosophy of the Gita, wherein the existence of matter is not denied, the picture of a sthitaprajña stands out proclaiming to us that liberation is not from the relationship between the Spirit as the subject and the matter of the world as the object (one aspect of it is one’s physical body), but from the necessity of such a relationship for the basic existence of the Spirit. The feeling of necessity is bondage and overcoming it is liberation. In the dualism (as one may be inclined to infer from the Gita) of the Lord and His Kāyā, the element of His dependence on Māyā is purely contingent and not necessary for the being of the Lord. It should be so even at the individual level, as is evidenced in the life of a sthitaprajña, who is free from the necessity of the contingent and the relative, while he is yet with them.

A sthitaprajña is an instance of the Spirit which from out of its fundamental experience of the unity of being fuses, as it were, his physical body with the rest of the world of objects even while living with it. This is the significance of brahma nirvāṇa. And, so, one in that situation does not find a necessity in consciousness to treat his body as having a being different from the rest of the objects even while he sees, hears, touches, smells, eats, goes about, sleeps, speaks, throws, grasps, opens, closes, and so on (5.8-9). This is freedom he will have gained from the physical body, and the unnecessity of treating it as different from the rest of the world, which, again, goes on in a similar mechanical way. The essential law of life of a sthitaprajña is that he has no individualised body as distinct from the cosmic material, and this equally refers to his attitude towards the unity of his individual self with that of the universal. This identity is so much achieved by him in life that we, because of our attachment or enslavement to our own body, argue about his physical body – a lump of matter, as he treats it – which has been released by him as of no consequence! It is no more than a carcass for him who is freed from the necessity of it. The fact that such a liberated self lives among us, with a physical body hanging about him, should be a great blessing to us, for we, who are bound to the necessity of the body, can have a physical contact with him, and have the benefit of his example and intuitions to know with conviction how an individual can live as a factor of cosmic design and serve to consolidate its purpose. This we forget unfortunately and think that he lives like us confined to that body, not seeing the infinite dimension of his growth beyond the physical frame.

At one point the Lord suggests that liberation is not simply from gross matter, but should be from the subtle as well (2.59). This is the mental or the egoistic aspect. Freedom from the mind and the ego has been a repeated theme of the Lord’s instruction, and the sthitaprajña or a Yogī is one who is liberated from these bonds even though he is found with the physical body. He is with the body – sthūla and sūkṣma – and free from the bondage of their limitations. That he is free is to be seen in the way he lives his life. He stands to be witnessed by anyone as having a changed vision or a heightened vision (paraṃ dṛṣṭvā – 2.59).

Liberation, especially that of one’s liberation-in-life (jīvanmukti), has a direct bearing on the thesis of loka-saṃgraha, understood in its widest connotation, viz. as consolidation of the cosmic purpose. A sthitaprajña who is in a brahmī sthiti represents in his way of life what it actually means, viz. a cosmic theme of a movement in the direction of the Infinite working through the individual and society, a theme of which the sthitaprajña is conscious, but not so the others. Not only is he conscious of his position in society and the rest of the cosmos, but he also knows that each man is placed thus. It is this cosmic theme which works up also the division of men into classes (2.13) on the basis of a natural law with a purpose of effecting a consolidation in the smoothest way possible. And, apart from this social classification, the cosmic law demands men to pursue duties in life (3.8) in accordance with the classification, to be devoted to that pattern however harsh and uncongenial the life and duties may be (3.35), and to attain salvation by holding fast to that pattern (3.20; 18.45). The individual himself has to tread this path of serving a cosmic purpose and be himself an instance in his life of a cosmic purpose attaining fruition. A sthita-prajña is the measure of the capacity of man to effect lokasaṃgraha or consolidation in one’s own life and being a stage himself in the direction of its fulfillment. He is an example to society demonstrating that the future of life is linked up with the cosmos in a positive relationship, a relationship which does not stop with the individual and the local, but extends even to the living and non-living existents beyond the narrow, selfish fortifications of ordinary living.

Liberation is a condition of one’s being or existence not involved in relativity or in its implications of space, time, finitude, etc. Not reducing the world and its associated features to an abstract nothing, liberation implies a realisation of the most basic truth behind all experience, with reference to which it recognizes the worth of the world as simply of a relative nature. Ultimately, liberation has an existential import, even as the Self has, and one may go to the extent of saying that it would be a contradiction to speak of a self that ‘attains’ freedom, for a self that is not naturally free is no Self at all. Self and liberation are co-terminous or interchangeable existents.

12The Infinite Being – Its Dynamics And Freedom

The most difficult yet pivotal concept in the Lord’s teaching is about His Infinite Being referred to in personal tones as parama puruṣa, puruṣottama or uttama puruṣa. The infinite dynamics of that Being is referred to in the Gita as paraṃ-bhāva. In fact, the only problem that exists before the human being is to understand the dimensions of parama puruṣa and the dynamics of paraṃ bhāva, both hidden in a mystery. The Lord says that one who unravels the mystery attains to the highest condition of the Infinite Being itself. It is termed variously ātma-māyā, yoga-māyā, etc. and could be rendered only as ‘mystery’. Its inscrutableness is brought out by the Lord’s statement that “it is very difficult to (grasp it) and escape from its hold or transgress its Law” (7.14). This mystery runs all through and touches the being of the Infinite in all its transcendent and immanent aspects, and is also at the basis of all failures in describing the Infinite through words, for it is attempting to express something which transcends all verbal communication, let alone mental comprehension. It is that which baffles all rational analysis and construction. Where we think we are in possession of it, it will have eluded us. “Wonderful,” is the only description, and ‘Wonderful’ is the only expression and reaction towards it (2.29).

It is usual to translate the term paraṃ in parama puruṣa as ‘transcendent’. But this may convey the sense of mere transcendence creating a feeling of distance. A being that is transcendent this way is hardly comprehensive. In the case of the Infinite, transcendence should imply existence beyond a certain sense of immanence. Hence immanence is as much a character of transcendences. The highest being cannot be just transcendent, but should be immanent also. And so, paraṃ is to be understood as the Infinite Being, implying both transcendence and immanence, for the limits of immanence are not the limits of being, and it is this which transcendence implies.

Now with regard to puruṣa, it is usual to take it as a person, thereby giving it a personal touch. But there is a greater reason in understanding it as the existential principle in its most universal and impersonal character, as the ‘Being resident in all beings’, and as the ‘Primal sentience and will’ (jñātṛ and kratu, respectively). For being the Infinite, nothing can be besides it, both in extension and intension.

Puruṣa is puri śayate. This Being is spoken of as Kṣetrī (13.33), for he resides in all kṣetras, i.e. all bodies (13.2). Naturally, in tune with the Infinite, we will have to reckon: as is the Infinite, so is the kṣetra. In its transcendent and immanent character, the Infinite kṣetrī is in Infinite kṣetra. This is because there is no point where the Infinite is not, and there cannot be a kṣetra without a kṣetrī, and vice versa. The dynamics of the Infinie Being (ātma-yoga) is such that to bifurcate it as the kṣetra and the kṣetrī is merely verbal, and any distinction between them existentially conceiving one as the spiritual and the other as the non-spiritual would be logically inconsistent. It is exactly in this sense that the Veda speaks of it: puruṣa eva idaṃ sarvaṃ (“Puruṣa is all this verily”). Whatever that is, pulsates with the living touch of Puruṣa, and there cannot be an idaṃ (this) without puruṣa being in it, puruṣa not being it. Keeping this dimension of the Infinite in view, we will have to examine the problem of transcendence and immanence with reference to time and space or time-space, or broadly, the empirical context.

There are many statements in the Gita which convey immanence and all-pervasiveness of the Infinite Being:

Īśvaraḥ sarva bhūtānāṃ hṛddese tiṣṭhati (in the hearts of all existents, the Īśwara exists – 18.61).

Samaṃ sarveṣu bhūtānāṃ tiṣṭhantaṃ (who exists in all beings – 13.27).

Ena sarvaṃ idaṃ tataṃ (by which all this is pervaded – 8.22).

Vāsudevaḥ sarvaṃ iti (all this is Vāsudeva – 7.19).

Tvayā tataṃ viśvaṃ anantarūpaṃ (the infinite form of existence is pervaded by Thee – 11.38).

Are we to understand by these descriptions that the Infinite pervades spatially, as we are prone to do? We are easily stuck, if we are to bring in the imagery of spatial pervasion or occupation of the type we witness in empirical experience, say, of water entering the pores of a sponge and being there, or the pervasion of ink on a paper when it is spilt, or the pervasion of light or air in a room. Is the Infinite immanent in this way? If we yield to the temptation and say yes, we are treating it as a commensurable entity understandable in terms of our knowledge. We have then a commensurate Infinite. What we forget in our ignorance is the fact of its transcendence, i.e. it does not fit into the spatial application. Immanence is ontological, not linguistic or literal, and points to a basic existence of the Infinite as the metaphysical ground and being of all existence. If it is spatially pervasive, as in the case of ink spreading on a paper, when we cut the paper, we will have cut the Infinite too! And so, any pervasiveness of the Infinite will have to be understood metaphorically, if we are not to affect the existential and non-logical implication of the immanence of the Infinite.

How about transcendence? It cannot be different. We find in the Gita statements which convey the sense that the entire extent of the universe empirically available to us forms only a fragment of the Lord’s splendor, springing out and supported by a fragment; and that the Infinite itself has no beginning, no middle and no end (11.19). “There is nothing that is equal, how can there be something greater?” (na tvat samah asti, abhyadhikaḥ kutaḥ? – 11.43). The Infinite is so incommensurate that nothing we think of can be a match to it, and our choosing a metaphor or example from what we know can only be a pathetic show. At best it can suggest, but it will not give us the feel of the unequalled Incommensurate. The dimensions of this Incommensurate Infinite are so surpassing that the whole of the universe looked so pitifully small to Arjuna who saw it lodged in a small nook of the ‘body’ of the Supreme Lord (11.13). Arjuna was so bewildered and dumfounded at the expanse of the Infinite that he pleads for a restoration of his normalcy. However, we should not be misled by the imagery of the body of the Supreme Being.

That which spreads beyond the extent of the universe is not spatial. Does the Infinite transcend the given in a way that a nose sticks out of one’s face or in a way a lotus sticks out of the surface of a lake? These are spatial and commensurate examples, and any extension of the Infinite in this way makes it commensurate with space. The Vedic statement: pādosya viśwā bhūtāni, tripadasyā aṃṛtaṃ divi, should not be taken to mean that the three quarters of the Puruṣa are spread out in ‘space immortal’, the space in relation to our space-time conception. In the same way, the figure of the Viśwarūpa understood in terms of spatial extension or dimension is a poor attempt to grasp the non-spatial Incommensurate (aprameya –11.42).

In the same way, the transcendence and immanence of the Infinite should not be understood in terms of the time we know. For the dynamics of the Infinite, even here, is incommensurate to the extent that it will make all our metaphors effete. The mystery or this aprameyatva is well revealed by innumerable statements in the Gita, and we may find samples of such thus:

What is outside is also inside.

It is everywhere, in all, but nothing touches it.

Nothing contaminates it.

It moves and it moves not.

There is nothing that it does, but there is nothing that is not done by it.

It is indivisible but found equally (and in equal intensity) in all divided things.

It is itself, it is the other too.

Is it mathematically countable as ‘one’ or ‘many’? Its existence or pervasion is inscrutable (avyaktaṃ – 9.4; māyā – 18.61; rahasyaṃ – 4.3). Its mysterious dynamics is deepened and intensified when we are told:

All things exist in It, and they do not exist in It (9.4-5).

All things exist in It, but It is not in them! (9.4).

How to understand this, which, though not contradictory for an Infinite logic, is so for human logic? The Infinite is its own law by which it can be its very opposite in a dialectic of ‘super-identity’ (ekasthaṃ – 13.30) which transcends all oppositions of ordinary logic (11.7; 3.30). It tells to our face: “Look at my beautiful Yoga” (paśya me yogamaiśwaraṃ – 9.5; 11.8). The logical mind is baffled by the contradictions it finds there: the macro being the micro, the Infinite being the finite, the far being the near, the spiritual being the material, and so on. But the non-logical or translogical is simply drawn towards its mystery and loses itself in this numinous truth! There can only be one response to it, i.e. horripilations at the sight of the Mysterious (11.14) and a cry “How Wonderful (2.29)!”

Can we pierce through the mystery by considering a metaphor just as a metaphor, and so, only as a means of gauging the mystery behind the metaphor, or are we to remain caught up by the literal meaning of the metaphor and equate the Incommensurate with the commensurate of our knowing? We are committing the error that we are to avoid, if we interpret the verse:

Divi sūryasahasrasya bhaved yugapadutthitā yadi bhāḥ sadṛśī sā syādbhāsāstasya mahātmanaḥ – (11.12).[21]

as meaning “increase the kilo-wattage of one Sun to a thousand times and you get the required brilliance!” It is just a metaphor, and the truth is just incomprehensible.

The numinous that is spoken of here is akṣara, avibhakta, avikārya, abhedya, avyaya, etc. But in what way? It is akṣara, not in the sense that an ingot of gold kept in a place does not disintegrate; it is avibhakta, not in a sense that something is hard to divide; avikārya, not in the sense that a certain thing refuses to be converted or transformed; acchedya and avyaya, not in the sense that something cannot be cut into pieces or is imperishable. The dialectic of the Infinite is not of the language we are familiar with. Can we rise to the state of understanding what is aprameya (unknowable, incommensurate) in terms of prameya (knowable, commensurate)? If we think we can, we are just deep in the net of a mystery, and never can we escape from it. It is not an exaggeration if the Lord speaks to us thus:

Those who are ignorant do not know Me who has taken up this human form. They do not understand My transcending state of dialectics (paraṃ bhāva). I am the Supreme Lord of all existence (not a creature born) – 9.11.

The transcending state is too transcendent for human comprehension. The limits of knowledge can never be the limits of being. It is not strange, then, that whenever the Lord touches upon His transcendent state He repeats this warning (7.24-25).

Finally, ‘transcendence’ is not limited to either the qualitative or the quantitative senses with which we are familiar. Its connotation with reference to the incommensurate should naturally far exceed the meaning and application of this term (or even of ‘immanence’) current in human usage. It is sat and transcends in sat; it is cit and transcends in cit; it is ānanda and transcends in ānanda. This is transcending transcendence (paraṃ bhāva) whose dialectics when applied to immanence transcends the immanence in sat, cit, and ānanda. This is the implication of the Infinite metaphysics the Lord wants us to intuit when He declares that the region or limits of immanence is out of a manifestation of an infinitesimally microscopic quantum of the transcending Being that He is (10.42).

Not being commensurate in terms of space and time or any determinant of the type, yet being pervasive; and being pervasive, yet not being tainted is the mystery of the transcendental Being described by the Lord as yoga-māyā (mystery of the state of transcendental existence). It is by this the Lord ‘sits’ (tiṣṭhati) in all beings, but not physically; ‘supports’ (bibharti), yet not physically; ‘shines’ (bhāsayate), yet not like a physical luminary; ‘knows’ (vetti), yet not psychologically. The means and methods of the infinite ‘doing’ or ‘not doing’ these are invisible (avyaktaṃ), unthinkable (acintyaṃ) and indefinable (anirdeśyaṃ). Transcendent to the commensurate, it is yet the cause of the commensurate. This is the mystery (yoga-māyā). It is the way it exists!

It is pertinent then to remember what is implied in the dynamics of Self-existence (ātma yoga), i.e. that whenever we speak of immanence or transcendence there is a case of hypostatization. Existentially the idea of immanence is a hypostatization of the finite on the Infinite. It arises as a result of the presupposition of the existence of the finite as such, but accommodating the Infinite as a pervading entity within and about, and so is an anathema to an Infinite Existence (11.11, 16, 38, 47). The entire eleventh chapter is devoted to the description of this Infinite Existence. For, it makes for the pervaded as distinct from the pervading. As within the limits, we think, we exist, we invite the Infinite to enter in terms of immanence so beyond the limits of where we think we do not exist, and allow the extension of the Infinite in terms of transcendence. Evidently, the basis for determining immanence or transcendence is the hypothesis of the finite existent, and therefore is relative. Thus the Infinite itself cannot justifiably be described as immanent or transcendent, or as both. It can only be an eternal, undivided existence, consciousness and bliss. This is the ‘truth-constant’ of reality, which the Lord is, and we should not miss it.

If, then, the dynamics of the Infinite Being is ungraspable and mysterious, the problem arises as to how else are we to intuit its being and dimensions.

There could only be one way, and that is, through intuiting the dimensions it brings into being and sets into motion within the commensurable limits of our being, but revealed to our consciousness during the attunement of our being with it. However, the idea of our being is to be understood conditionally.[22] For, nothing is brought into being in the realm or being of the Infinite. And any point of being that we may feel as ours can only be an instance of our inviting the whole of the Infinite to lend us a self-feeling, when we think we exist and operate. We forget that it is only the dialectics of the infinite kṣetrī in the kṣetra.

Even within the conditional field of self-feeling there are subtle shades which pass beyond metaphor and example, and therefore, our understanding can only be a limited human approach to the Infinite Reality; and beyond the human what exists of Reality we may not be able to know at all. And so, the pointed demand of the Infinite Being on man is one of absolute humility or a demand to reduce one’s self to naught. The real implication of absorption or surrender is this dissolution of our being in the Being of the Infinite whereby the pretensions of parallel existence or anti-existence are ruled out. I am not, It is. The dialectic of Its being is the theme of the Lord’s teaching set forth in the Puruṣottama Yoga. And any element that comes up in the explanation is just incidental to the exposition of the dialectics of Its being, not that the element which has been brought in has a being of its own. In other words, the consideration of the elements like puruṣa and prakṛti has reference beyond them, and any being they get is because of their participation in Its dynamics. We shall see of this in the next section.

But before we pass on to consider these dimensions (vistāraṃ – 13.30) of the Infinite, we will have to bear in mind that any relationship the Transcendent Being is said to possess with regard to them should not be confused with ordinary relationships available in empirical experience. Expressions like mātā, pitā, dhātā, pitāmahā, bhartā, prabhu, sākṣi, suhṛt, nivāsa, upadṛṣṭa, anumantā, kṣetrajña, etc. used in this context are metaphors having meanings beyond the personal implications of such terms used by us. It is a relationship that is not commensurate with the empirical husband-wife relationship, master-servant relationship, and so on. It is ontological and refers to the being of the Infinite in its transcendent and immanent characters. The relationship indicates a transcendental logic and dialectics of the Infinite, which bind ‘all this’ with the Infinite in a way in which the Infinite is not bound with ‘all this’.

As an ideal of comprehension, the Infinite is avijñeya, yet it is end of all knowledge, jñeya. There is an obvious logical antithesis here, but the invitation is held out that it is jñeya-gamya (13.17) on the ontological dialectics of the absolute whose nature is to transcend the oppositions of logical dialectics, yet be revealed as the very soul of all beings. The mystery is whatever oppositions the dichotomizing empirical reasoning or logic may find in the facts of experience, they are resolved into a higher or transcending unity at the level of the Infinite, so that each ‘opposing’ (as ordinarily understood) aspect works in such perfect ‘togetherness’ that to have a doubt itself of their mutual anti-thesis would be virtually wrong. The dynamics of the Infinite Being gives us the indication of how very unfortunate and misdirecting it is to establish the thesis-antithesis movement of the logical dialectics and transport it into a field which is governed by a different dialectics.

The dynamics of the Infinite Being can be intelligible to us only when we find its application with reference to a concrete instance, viz. jīvaloka or the sphere of life, which is a dimension projected by the Infinite Lord before our consciousness.[23] Its study is relevant for an accurate understanding of the issue, and so, occupies us immediately in the following section, which is virtually a continuation of the present one.

13The Infinite Theme In Application

In a very significant verse the Lord makes the basic demand for understanding the Infinite Theme in application. He says:

yadābhūtapṛthagbhāvam ekasthaṃ anupaśyati |

tata eva ca vistāraṃ brahma saṃpadyate tadā || (13.30)

It is a demand to see the manifold existence lodged in the unity of a single Being (ekasthaṃ), and to see them only as its dimensions or expansions (vistāraṃ). It is such a perception which makes one attain the Infinite. It is the demand for the intuitive experience of the Infinite that sets aside divisions and oppositions imposed on Being by the sectional or partial perspectives of logic and empiricism. The Lord values the gestalt (samagraṃ, as He calls it – 7.1) of Reality and wants us to catch the ‘thread which holds the beads’ (7.7) in any assessment of the working of even a section available to our ordinary experience. This gestalt or thread is the puruṣottama or the Infinite, and the Lord opens up for our observation its operative existence, as it were, in an instance called the ‘universe of life’ (jīva-loka), with all its incidentals or expansions, viz. puruṣa, prakṛti and their contingents.

The total perspective naturally grasps the structure of the Infinite Being and treats the incidentals as only constitutive elements within a purposive theme. It is very significant the Lord calls prakṛti (the elemental insentient) and puruṣa (the sentient, which enlivens the prakṛti) ‘His two natures’ (7.45). These do not ‘belong’ to the Infinite, as ordinary possessions belong to a human being in an external relationship (saṃyoga). They are constitutive to the structure of Reality and have their being as functioning elements in the consolidation of the cosmic theme. Not being alien to the being of the Infinite, the Lord calls them ‘Mine’ (me – 7.4-5), and calls the things that emerge out of their interaction as nothing but His own ‘expansions’ without breaking the unity of Being at any stage (13.30). The tragedy of the classical Sāṃkhya was its losing sight of this unity of the Infinite Being and considering puruṣa and prakṛti as distinct and opposite entities. The sāṃkhya which the Lord teaches in the Gita is not the enumerative Sāṃkhya but is the knowledge of the Infinite with its inalienable dimensions; call them ‘vibhūtis’ or ‘vistāras’, it matters little.

It is only as matters of detail that shades have been presented of these two, with their synonyms:

Puruṣa is akṣara, kṣara and kṣetrajña.

Prakṛti is parā, aparā, and kṣetra.

In both these what is transient and what lasts is shown. The akṣara puruṣa is non-transitory, and is the jīva or prtyagātma (the illuminating principle) within the sphere of life (jīva-loka). The kṣara puruṣa is the tractable form of puruṣa, i.e. what we call the physical personality which a balance can weigh and a tailor can measure or a physician can treat. This is perishable, and what perishes is the kṣara puruṣa, what does not and keeps up continuity is the akṣara puruṣa. At physical death, it is the body (kṣara puruṣa) that is burnt, but the Self (akṣara puruṣa) is not subjected to burning or cutting. It is adāhya and acchedya, etc. (2.23-25).

It is the same with prakṛti. With regard to the parā aspect, there are two meanings we can gather from the Gita. When it says parā prakṛti is jīvabhūta (7.5), it means the puruṣa, the life-giving principle. The other meaning is the subtle and unseen aspect of prakṛti, also called avyakta. The other names that occur of it are: sanātana avyakta, and mahad brahma (14.3-4), akṣara brahma (3.15). This prakṛti is the base which persists throughout as the infinite potential source of all manifestations of energy and action, into which all the created beings dissolve or ‘enter’ at the ‘arrival of night’, i.e. at cosmic dissolution (praḷaya) and ‘come out’ at the ‘dawn’ or creation (sṛṣṭi).

The Lower or aparā prakṛti is that visible (vyakta) physico-chemical matter drawn from the elemental bhūtas: earth, water, fire, air and ākāśa. It is these and their combinations that give rise to the concrete world of our living.

This is only giving a simple catalogue of the details of the facts of the Infinite Being in so far as it refers to the jīva-loka. But it should be borne in mind that the Lord is not concerned much with enumerating them as such. There is a grander theme which we are invited to discover underneath them and witness. The ‘show’ is not so much of these details as it is of the theme itself. But it is usual to miss this main theme and be caught up in the details that fluctuate, the ‘beads’ rather than the ‘thread’, which binds them together and gives them an existence and meaning beyond their narrow identities.

What is pertinent is to know how they enter into a Cosmic theme and serve a purpose which transcends them, for they are not independent either in existence or purpose. It is usual to be lost in the labyrinth of set notions about the eternality of prakṛti and puruṣa and claim that their eternality implies categorical existence. When the Lord speaks of them as ‘eternal’ (and if we are not to forget the gestalt of His teaching) in the context of the sphere of life (jīva-loka) in which He mentions these elements, we find Him speaking of them in the sense that they are not His newly acquired characteristics. It is the Infinity that sets into motion the incidentals (and there can be a million of them), and one such incidental is the jīva-loka. To this are related the incidentals of puruṣa and prakṛti. They have relevance in the context of life, and in the absence of life they do not come into the picture. This is the meaning of their ‘eternality’, and they are not the ‘eternal two’ with the Eternity itself besides them, making the ‘eternal three’. For, an Infinity which sets against itself two other eternals cannot itself be Infinite.

The exposition of the kṣetra-kṣetrajña or prakṛti-puruṣa by the Lord has relevance only in the context of the Infinite or to the theme of Puruṣottama. If we miss the emphasis laid by the Lord on Puruṣottama as the object of all endeavour, we will have missed the theme. Being incidental to the dynamics of the transcendental purpose, puruṣa and prakṛti are instrumental and make us feel the ‘pulse’ of the Infinite Being. To forget this is to forget the vital meaning of the Gita. The dictum the Lord proclaims to us is: “Know Me, the Highest, and you will have known the rest – brahma, adhyātmā, karma, etc.” (7.29-30).

If one is not already awake to the situation presented by the Lord in the chapter of Viśwarūpa Darśana Yoga, wherein He virtually breaks the egoistically constructed boundaries of separate existence and dissolves all identities and individualities in an Infinite numinous, it is appropriate now to recover oneself and see that the field of the Infinite is not confined only to the human world. And it is better to submit to the understanding that the dialectics of the Infinite operate even outside human life. In other words, Infinity does not end with mankind or in mankind. When the Lord puts before Arjuna the analysis of puruṣa and prakṛti, He only takes from an infinite expanse of existence one that can be understood, viz. the sphere of life, to show how life and the elements that make it up are subject to His law of working. As a perfect scientist would take out a cell out of a body and place it for study under a microscope, so the Lord selects the field of life and holds a magnifying lens on this isolated area, as it were, and asks us to peep through it to discover for ourselves how the Infinite Being is operating therein as the eternal transcendent impulse. The analysis is confined not necessarily to the microscopic but applies to the macroscopic elements as well and other inanimate existence involved within the field. But we forget and assert that it is all about man! Puruṣa is not man that we know of, nor is he confined to the human individual as an individual, nor prakṛti is that which we see as our body or the world. When we are not able to understand the movements that are so gross in the world, how can we ever understand the subtle moves or forces that constitute even the small universe of life on the canvas of Infinity and link them up with the larger, wider and deeper cosmic truth symbolized by the Lord Himself in his paraṃ bhāva? Let us be rooted in this perspective before we try to understand the dynamics of jīva loka.

It is essential, then, to follow up the Lord’s presentations of the Infinite as the ‘cosmic-acosmic’ truth transcending all logical calculations:

It has no beginning (in the sense that we say something has a beginning). It is neither existence (that we know), nor non-existence (which we can comprehend). Its omnipresence is so single and indivisible that we encounter its faces, hands, eyes, ears, etc. (all over, so that we can never miss its immediate presence). It exhibits all functional qualities of sense organs, yet has no sense organs (that we can recognize). It is the cause of all (not in the way that something ordinarily is the cause of the other). It is interested in none (in the way we know). It is beyond the guṇas, but enjoys (without being bound). It is inside of everything, yet, outside, there is no place where it is not. It is in the moving, and equally so in the unmoving. It is subtle (in the sense that we cannot grasp it as we grasp a concrete one). It is indivisible, yet we see it existing in different things as if divided. It is the protector, yet is the destroyer of all things. It is luminous, yet beyond all lights. (It is in darkness) yet, it transcends all darkness (13.12-17).

Is it transcendent in the sense that it is away from us? No. It is established in one’s own heart as the supreme unity of all knowledge, knowable and the known (13.17). To know that It is our being is jñāna, and nothing else is (13.12, 17).

What is most puzzling about all this is that such an expansive Reality which defies all expectations of our grasping is located in one’s own heart! It is the truth of the Infinite that can be discovered in its entirety in any one point of existence! As a centre of Reality – and it is only the Infinity which can have centres all over itself – a man is linked up with the rest of existence.

Against this wide sweep of the Infinite background are presented the pictures of puruṣa and prakṛti.[24] The Lord says:

With reference to the universe of life – jīva loka, the element which is at the core and sustaining life is a fragment of My eternal Self (15.7).

We should remember here that the Lord selects a sample field of the Infinite Being to focus our attention on and to help us learn to what dynamics the subject is submitted. The Lord continues:

Being the centre within the field of activity (prakṛti or kṣetra), it operates by drawing all the senses, with the mind as the sixth (15.7).

This is to be known as My higher nature, and associated with life (jīvabhūtam) (7.5).

And there is a lower nature (aparā prakṛti), the dynamic or the non-spiritual, of eight elements (7.4-5).

All living beings are to be traced to these (two Natures) (7.6).

The Infinite Lord speaks:

Understand that all existents (or creatures) have their source in this. But I am the originator of all creation as well as of destruction.

Besides My being there exists nothing whatsoever.

The last of these statements is so significant that at one stroke it conveys the sense that “all this that has been said is Me only, as I am the Infinite,” or that “there is none superior to Me.” Both are true of the Infinite.

A further analysis of the universe of life (jīva loka) is presented: “There are two puruṣas in this universe (loke): kṣara and akṣara (15.16).”

What is this universe or sphere (loka)? Obviously, it is the sphere of life, and is as such indicated earlier in the same chapter (15.7). And it is relevant to remember that the Lord selects this sphere of life out of the Infinity, as that is the nearest to us for elaboration. And in the ‘womb’ of the Infinite there may be incalculable number of such spheres. In the Vibhūti Yoga, for example, the Lord says that he is the acme of manifestations in many spheres: the Āditya loka, Vasu loka and so on. It only implies the negligibility of human life in the scheme of Reality, without knowing which we think of ourselves to be of great consequence to Reality and its existence. It is Reality itself speaking to us (in the form of the Lord) as to how it estimates us as insignificant, and our estimates of Reality cannot be approximate unless we are identical with it:

(In this universe of life) there are two persons (forms): the destructible and the indestructible. All beings that become are destructible (kṣara). The one firmly established in them (kūṭastha) is called the indestructible (15.16).

He is the kṣetrajña who knows the kṣetra (13.1).

… and is in prakṛti (15.7).

… enjoys the guṇas born of prakṛti, and so in turn, born in good or bad wombs, as the case may be (13.21).

The Lord (Īśwara) occupies a body, enjoys and leaves it (15.8-9).

The ignorant do not see Him either while He stays or departs or enjoys the guṇas (15.10).

And it is to be remembered here that the narrative about Puruṣa does not end with this.

It is said that lying deep is the transcendent aspect of puruṣa. It pervades the three spheres – the two puruṣas and one prakṛti – and sustains them. That is the Uttama Puruṣa (15.18), the Transcendent Puruṣa (puruṣaḥ paraḥ) (13.22). This is not seeable in terms of either the living (jīvabhūta) or the non-living, i.e. in terms of either the akṣara or kṣara puruṣas, but transcends them, and so is called anya, the other, and paramātman (the Supreme Self) (15.17). Whereas the jīvabhūta akṣara puruṣa is subject to transformation, the Uttama Puruṣa is not. And, whereas the kṣara puruṣa is combustible matter and disintegrates at death, the Uttama Puruṣa is not, and therefore is spoken of as the ‘transcendent’ in the field (15.18).

It is important not to miss the dialectics of the Infinite in this analysis. The Infinite though transcendent is not wholly absent in the field, nor is it wholly away from any point of its being. It is that which shines as the illuminating principle within the body (13.33). It is a point of concentration called dehin or kṣetrī. It is seen as living and making use of the senses and enjoying through them within the prismatic perspective of life. And thereby, the Infinite is not away from the epicenter or cut off from the main stream of the Infinite Spirit. An aṃśa is not a part in the ordinary sense, for it refers to the incommensurate Being, in the context of which a finite characteristic such as being a part cannot be applied. It is the incommensurable indivisible (aprameyaṃ and avibhaktaṃ). The epicenter has a ‘prismatic’ effect, i.e. it can throw off or project the picture of the three dynamic principles of individuality, or it can equally put forth a single-rayed perspective of the three. And so, the trans-logical description of the Infinite as sarvendriya guṇābhāsaṃ is also the sarvendriya vivarjitaṃ, etc. We shift the angle of the prism, it is now sarvendriya guṇābhāsaṃ; shift it the other way, it is sarvendriya vivarjitaṃ. At one angle it is the jīva and at another it is the prakṛti.

The Lord makes this clear when he declares that the Infinite is the Kṣetrajña in all the fields (13.2), upadṛṣṭa (supervisor), anumantā (consentor), bhartā (supporter), bhoktā (enjoyer), and maheśwara (great lord) (13.22). Whether it is the kṣara puruṣa or anything that is destructible (vinaśyatsu) or the akṣara aspect of the puruṣa or anything that is indestructible (avinaśyastu), the Infinite is equally present, and its Infinity is not affected in any way, for it is not transformed into a different being (avikārya), nor tainted by projection (alipta) (13.31).

Before we close this section, it is interesting to note that in any field of the Infinite Being, say, jīva loka, and select any centre therein, say, a microscopic cell, we have the basic consolidation taking place. Even in a small unit like this, there is the concourse of the aspect of Infinity, viz. the Brahman, the adhyātma, the adhibhūta, the adhidaiva and karma, and in that unit we find the adhiyajña going on!

Arjuna asks: How in this body does the basic yajña, i.e. self-regenerative sacrifice, take place? Who is there when it takes place (8.2)? The answer which the Lord gives applies universally to the micro- as well as the macro-cosmic bodies (śarīra). In any unit there is a combustion that takes place of the elements. That is the kṣara aspect of the body. It is ‘spent out’. There is a resident divinity who sets the spark, as it were, because that is the light or the fire within, and with that the movement is set. And what takes place is the sacred act of yajña or sacrifice. The sacrifice is Infinity itself (8.3-4). It is Reality splitting itself to be Reality. Being is sacrificed for being. What is burnt or combusted (kṣara) is not lost, but is assimilated in the whole Being beyond that unit where burning takes place. Taking a unit individually, burning away (kṣaratva) is necessary for the unit to survive; otherwise it ceases to be. A food that is not digested and the undigested that is not thrown out are not consistent with the survival of the individual. The Lord says, “I, by becoming the Vaiśvānara, cause food to be digested (15.14).” In a unit, it is not that something is kṣara and is to be discarded, but that it exists to be burnt just in the same way coal is taken for burning in a steam engine to give it a movement and so is associated with the unit. The heat which burns helps the assimilation or the upkeep of a body. What is called ‘death’ (mṛtyu) is this burning of the physical body, and is necessary and meaningful in the larger context of continuity; and whatever is meaningful for consolidation is the Lord Himself (10.34-39). What is burnt (hutaḥ) is He Himself, as also the basic Will (kratu) behind the act of sacrifice (yajña) (9.10). And all the elements are involved in this self-regenerative process which the Lord compares to a Wheel that eternally rotates (evam pravartitam cakram) (3.16).

14The Individual – Cosmic Illumination And Energy Localised

There is a collateral issue connected with the dynamics of the Infinite, namely, the problem of the individual, the finite. What has been noted now is the functioning of the Infinite as a triadic ensemble of a state called ‘living’ or ‘life’ of a being – the puruṣa-prakṛti-Puruṣottama confluence. It is an instance of a packet or a unit of existence depicting how the Infinite is. Now, the problem is whether one can call this functional unit an ‘individual’ in the sense we ordinarily mean.

The issue is not a variation from the cosmic theme of the Infinite existence and operation, but only concentrates on localised units (within the framework of time and space), and calls them ‘individuals’. To have a full grasp of the meaning of the term ‘individual’, and of a sense of fulfillment, a conspectus of the cosmic or infinite dynamics is necessary. We find the keynote of the truth in a significant statement of the Lord:

janma karma ca me divyam evam yo vetti tattvataḥ

tyaktvā deham punarjanmanaiti māmeti so’rjuna.

The Infinite exists as the Infinite and operates as the Infinite. And at whatever level it may exist and operate, its dynamics passes beyond measurements of the finite, and so is incommensurate (aprameya). Its incommensurate self-existence is called ātma-yoga (11.47), and its operation is termed yoga-māyā or ātma-māyā (7.25; 4.6), a secret by which the Infinite is seen to put up varieties of forms and movements – sentient and insentient, macro and micro-, sustain and propel them in a way that nothing escapes the law of Infinity or damage its being as the Infinite. In one of the most difficult, yet penetrating, statements the Lord makes, referring to it as His paraṃ-bhāva or ‘transcending dialectics’:

The unmanifest has now become the manifest, so think the unwise of Me. They do not know the (secret of My) transcending state of the dialectics (paraṃ-bhāva) of the undiminishing and unsurpassing (avyayaṃ and anuttama) being (7.24).

Shining from within my creative mystery (yoga-māyā) I (i.e. My existence and operation) am not visible to one and all. Me, the unborn (aja) and the undiminishing (avyaya), the unwise of the world do not know (7.25).

Yoga-māyā is the creative mystery by which the undiminishing is seen as diminishing, the unsurpassing as the surpassable, the unmanifest as the manifest and the unborn as the born. In this creative dialectics which is the mystery of the transcendent Being, none of these latter affect or cause a diminution of the supreme glory (tejo-rāśi) (11.17) that the Infinite is. And it is the very mystery which passes all comprehension, because it is by which one is the other: the undiminishing the diminishing, the unsurpassing the surpassable, etc.

The implication seems to be that there is no transformation of the one into the other, nor a creation of something new. And the appearance here is no appearance; it is a total being from first to last. Perhaps, the meaning of yoga-māyā or creative mystery of a Being which is Infinite – infinite in potential and infinite in operation – will be sadly missed by us in describing its dialectics either as ‘creation’ (sṛṣṭi), or ‘transformation’ (pariṇāma) or ‘appearance’ (vivarta). It is an unalterable Infinite whose transcending dialectics we are expected to intuit. While the unwise doubt it, those who see the truth – as the Lord says – blissfully experience the glory of the Infinite in its invisible and indivisible wholesomeness (9.4).[25]

The implications of this undiminishing and unsurpassed Infinity are to be seen in the fact that nothing is set up as a parallel theme against it to become a reality in itself. It is blasphemous to think of a manifest, born or finite existent being a reality or real in an infinite existence. It is as if cutting something out of being and calling what remains ‘Infinite’. The secret of universal consolidation of the Real is to be seen here. Nothing is finite in the scheme of the Infinite! Every instance of being, every movement of being is to be seen on the canvas of the unsurpassable, undiminishing Infinite. Time, space, individuality, name, form, number, etc. are all drawn into the all-assimilating Infinity, which speaks to us thus:

Never was there an occasion when I did not exist, nor you, nor these lords among men, also; never shall we cease to be in the future (2.12).

Besides My being there exists nothing whatsoever [26] (7.7).

But what puzzles us most is the concrete individual in our experience, who is obviously so finite both in being and potential. How does it happen, if it happens at all? However, from the point of view of the Infinite, the individual is just the unique, and stands for a level the ordinary tends to be. By a Law of Infinity – for, it is Infinity which is operating – the Infinite is everything (11.40); yet it is pointedly so in its bounty and grandeur in the unique (10.41). Think of a plant, an animal, a mountain, a star, a seer or a god. The unique in each of these “is verily Me,” the Lord says in the chapter of Vibhūti-yoga (or the Dynamics of Self-projection). How can a finite exist, if existence is Infinite?

Perhaps, the perspective of the Gita is to be gathered in two ways to answer the incidence of what we may ordinarily call an ‘individual’.

In one sense, there is no individual at all, if ‘individual’ means a separated entity, because all individuals are only unique points of the universal Spirit itself – ‘ātma-vibhūtis’, as the Gita puts it (10.47).

In another sense, it is not the individual that matters, but the species that it represents. This truth is very often ignored or not noticed at all.[27]

For in the scheme of universal consolidation, the individual is just a species consolidating a value. And these, the species and the value, are universal. We shall see of this soon.

With regard to the individual and the finite, perhaps we are baffled and seek comfort in speculative philosophies, and square up difficulties of their incidence on the basis of empirical analogies, such as that the Infinite changes into the finite by a transformation; or that the finite is the creation of the Infinite from out of its own self or out of a different material. It is not unusual to find such theories within the range of Indian speculation. But a keen investigation of the text of the Gita reveals that none of these is asserted as the answer.

With regard to creation, if it were to mean production of new things, we cannot say, on the premises of the Gita, we have our expected answer. All creatures are put out and absorbed by the law of periodicity or cycles, wherein birth is no beginning and death no end (8.16-19; 9.7-8). Not seeing the law of continuity and indivisibility, we see birth, origination and change, etc.

The dynamics or the dialectics of the Infinite Being is that by a law of Infinity, it is the other, and does not become the other. The Lord would say:

If I am a Kapila of the Siddhas, I am as well Vāsudeva of the Vriṣṇis and Arjuna of the Pāṇḍavas, let alone the other beings animate and inanimate at the same time.

He tells us:

How I take birth is divine, and how I operate is divine. Whoever knows this in truth (4.9) can know how the unborn and the undiminishing that I am can occasion Myself by a dynamics of self-measurement (ātma-māyā – 4-6), and how I do so on several occasions, when there is dislocation in the cosmic order, to relieve those who are well intentioned and good and to destroy those who are against it (4.7-8).

It is no wonder that when the Lord spoke of His disclosing the truth to Vaivasvat, Arjuna was bewildered, for he was measuring from the human angle and not from the divine. Obviously he could not know the dimensions of the Infinite existence and its dynamics of operation running far beyond and far before the personalities we are told as having historical lives. Consideration of distance in time between personalities or differences of their individual existences are transcended here. The Infinite is the other at any place or time, but is its own undiminishing Self ever untouched by these relatives. Can we grasp this magic, as it were? Nonetheless, the Lord asks: “See My divine Yoga,” and He blasts the human mind of its preoccupation with the notions of the finite, of space, of time and of kind in the chapter of Viswarūpa Darśana Yoga (Cosmic Depersonalisation). Individualities that we call as such are marked punctuations only in the vibhūtis of the Lord, but not distincts of the Infinite. This is the incommensurate nature of the Infinite by which it rests indivisibly in the divided, as the One is the many, where the divided and the many are not distincts from the Infinite Reality.

This is actually rendering a transformation of the history of an individual of his own being. The individual of our ordinary conception is metamorphosed into the cosmic with links and responsibilities which are cosmic. This is where the theme of cosmic consolidation is to be seen. The note that Lord Krishna strikes at the heart of every individual is this: whether we know it or not, we are elements of a huge or infinite mass of Reality gearing up at each point of its own cosmic being. In this theme of Being, it is not that the individual men X, Y, Z are, or animals are, but that the species is. It is not that groups of beings collectively (or individually) are, but that life is. In this scheme, it is not who that matters but what. For example, it is not who (such as X, Y, Z) builds up values that is important, but it is value (such as truth, goodness, uprightness, harmony, peace, and so on) that is important, and what value has been built up. And the crux of the demand is: can anyone be that individual who builds up this value? If so, that is being a Yogī, and one should aim to be that (tasmāt yogī bhavārjuna – 6.46), and he becomes a cognizable instance or vibhūti in the scheme of consolidation – a Kapila, a Vāsudeva, an Arjuna, etc. worth the name. Reality is another name for value and its existence is the consolidation of value (dharma-saṃgraha or ātma-saṃgraha). Should this be determined in terms of time or individual personalities? Or does it speak of a transcending existence consolidating itself?

The metamorphosis of the individual into the cosmic places the individual in a position of greater responsibility both in being and in function. It makes him realize a relation far more universal than he ordinarily thinks of, and makes him shape and share a function beyond his immediate range. The highest sense of this realisation makes him throb with a feeling that it is not he that exists independently, but that he is continuous with a Reality which has no beginning or end, and that he is only a functioning occasion in the Infinite existence. It is only a sublimation or elevation of character that the Lord works up in the individual called Arjuna. Elevated in character, an individual feels that he is working in accordance with a law not of the moment and that one does not start a function anew. This is the sense of continuity of the self or personality, and one picks up a function or work which he has laid down on a previous occasion and perhaps far beyond the mortal conditions. This is infinitisation of an individual character and expansion of the meaning of the individual as a cosmic existent.

How the Infinity involves itself at all levels of its being we have seen in the previous section, wherein we have drawn attention to how the Lord points to a situation called ‘life’ (jīva-loka). It is an individual instance of how the Infinite operates. At this level of the individual, the effective meaning of life is to be in tune with the Infinite, which the Lord calls yoga, and is shown as an expression of a cosmic dialectic effecting a consolidation of being and purpose. We are only to remember how it is not that there are three elements in the field – puruṣa, prakṛti, and Puruṣottama – in an eternal scheme of pluralism or dualism, but that Infinity has ways of preserving itself beyond distinctions. An intuition of this truth will make each concrete finite individual – we think that we are – a transcendental individual with dimensions of Infinity itself. We are asked to intuit that any distinct is not conceived independent of the Infinite being. From this point of view, one may call himself a ‘reagent’ (i.e. an agent with a consciousness of purpose) in the scheme of cosmic consolidation – for these distincts last only so long as the relevant universe of life lasts. This is the meaning of the Lord when He says that prakṛti and puruṣa are anādi or eternal (13.19). In relation to life and dynamics of being, jīva or puruṣa is the name for the localised centre of illumination, and prakṛti is the name for the localised field of manifest energy and action. In accordance with the consolidation of being, it is the instance of life that puts up the implements of puruṣa and prakṛti, and beyond these two what matters is the cosmic theme of life. The values that emerge, viz. truth, goodness, harmony, understanding, selflessness, peace, etc. form part of the consolidating theme on the canvas of Infinity. From the perspective of infinite Being, life itself is a cosmic state or poise, an aspect of ātma-yoga, and the Lord indicates it as an order of his vibhūti: “…of the existents, I am life” (10.22). The universe of life (jīva-loka) cannot be a purposeless accident, but is interested in serving as a crucible for a manifestation of values such as those which make Reality not an arid, dry and desert-like existence.

It is in this connection that the teaching of the Gita gets a significance in placing a demand on each individual not only to act in such a way that in his life the cosmic forces achieve a balance and harmony (physical, psychological, moral, intellectual and spiritual), but also to become the instance of the species registering a raise in the quality of the stock called ‘life’ and the value thereof. This is the meaning of the Lord when he points to several instances of His vibhūtis as marking consolidation of being and value. Perhaps this is a pointer to evaluating what constitutes human evolution, i.e. to be judged in terms of this ‘rise’ registered in his accomplishments in yoga, which is nothing other than the universal or cosmic balance or harmony of/in Reality as opposed to discordance and imbalance.

However, we should never for a moment forget that the vibhūtis or the unique occasions we are speaking of, and shown as consolidating in time, add nothing in the form of a new dimension or growth in the inherent structure of the Infinite being, but have implication of being just revelations to our consciousness as to how the Infinite exists as the Infinite and operates as the Infinite.

15Yoga-Māyā And The Spectra of Bliss

Yoga-māyā or the mystery of Infinite Being operates in two ways: either it reveals itself or it does not. In the latter case we go by the mirage it casts and lose ourselves in the desert it spreads and lose all our discrimination (māyayā apahṛta jñānaḥ – 7.15). It is this we encounter ordinarily, and of which the Lord speaks: mama māyā duratyayā (“My māyā is difficult to overcome” – 7.14) and by which we are overcome. This is what deludes us.

But then there is the other aspect: rūpamaiśwaraṃ, the splendorous form or the state of the Infinite Being (also called ātma-māyā by the Lord) which when intuited we become joyous. And as the Lord says, those who intuit it blissfully enjoy: tuṣyanti ca ramanti ca (10.9). Such is the difference between the first and the second.

With regard to the first, in a person who sees a mirage, there is, no doubt, happiness. But soon the person is disillusioned. Its enjoyment is an illusion. Whereas the one who sights real water is not only happy at the time, but his happiness is sustained. “The anchor which very well holds the boat without letting it go by the blowing wind and the surging waves is Me,” the Lord would say.

It is they who are absorbed in Me, both in thought and breath, that eternally enjoy the bliss of being: maccittā madgata prāṇā…nityaṃ tuṣyanti ca ramantica (10.9).

It is these men who have intuited the soul of the Infinite that are immersed in the bliss of it. They also ‘lose’ themselves, but in the sweep of the bliss of the Infinite Being. At each moment, and at each instance of existence, they face the Infinite. It is this bliss that greets them at each turn. This is the spiritual aesthesis, and one becomes a poet, a seer or a yogi, and responds to the glory of the truth that reveals itself and engulfs one’s being. It is the freedom of being, expressing itself as the beauty of being and experienced as the bliss of being. In it the māyā, the erstwhile hindrance (or cover) is measured out and its veil rended. No more does it distract us, no more does it land us in falsehood, bondage, suffering and mortality.

But either one knows the dialectics of the Infinite Being (ātma-yoga or yoga-māyā) or one does not, as the Lord indicates on several occasions. Those who know the transcendental dialectics of the Infinite Being (paraṃ-bhāva) are safely on the other side of the deceiving complexes which fasten the unknowing to the realms of division and its logic. While he who understands the being and operations of the Infinite blissfully enjoys the glory of Being and its indivisible and undivided harmony, he who is caught up with the mundane is always ridden with the contradictions of divided existence. The implications of the statement, janma karma ca me divyaṃ yo vetti tattvataḥ (4.9), refer directly to the being of the Infinite and its inscrutable ways of operation in a self-consolidating or undiminishing scheme. But cut away from the basic continuity and eternality of the theme, we wander away from the truth and are perplexed as to how things can happen with such obvious limitations and oppositions. How can one ever understand the sincere yet naïve astonishment of Arjuna when he asks:

Your birth (i.e. manifestation) is obviously recent, whereas the origins of Vivasvat are unseen. If you say you have taught this to Vivasvat, how should I understand? (4.4)

The entire teaching of the Lord is an answer to such naïve questions about the mystery of Infinite existence and how it operates beyond the visions and levels of human perception and understanding. It is comforting to us, the ordinary, to have it from the Lord:

Neither the gods nor the maharṣis know my origins (10.2).

The gods are eternally anxious to have the sight of My being (11.52).

It is significant that the Lord asks Arjuna: “Are you interested in knowing Me as a ‘whole’ (samagraṃ)?” (7.1) And as if it is a boon to Arjuna, He projects the unifying vision of the vibhūtis and Yoga (vibhūtiṃ ca yogaṃ ca) (10.7).

The key chapters, Vibhūti Yoga and the Viśwarūpa Darśana Yoga, slip through our ordinary understanding if we take them on a par with the episodes drawn from mythology, to satisfy the fancy of an untutored young mind. The Lord emphasizes the significance of the chapters as portraying the kernel of His ‘being and exension’ (vibhūtiṃ ca yogaṃ ca), and Arjuna confesses that he has been initiated into ‘the extremely secret and symbolic metaphysics of the Infinite Being’ (paramaṃ guhyaṃ adhyātā saṃjñītaṃ) (11.1), and desires to have a ‘factual’, i.e. a mystical vision (dṛaṣṭumicchāmi – 11.3). And the Lord graces him with that privilege of the ‘super-vision’ (divya-cakṣuḥ 11.8) besides giving him the firsthand experience of participating in the dynamics of Infinite Being, by effecting what may be called a ‘depersonalisation’. We will have missed much if the Lord’s statement, “One should know, see and authentically participate in the Infinite Being” (jñātuṃ dṛaṣṭuṃ ca tattvena praveṣṭuṃ ca… – 11.54), does not strike a note in us.

Throughout the Gita the Lord makes us see how the human situation is only one element, and how hidden behind are forces that are subtle, recondite, yet always attuned to keeping Being as Being and not turn it into non-being. In the two chapters mentioned above, the soul of the consolidation of Reality makes itself felt so clearly for one who has this vision of the dialectics of Reality held to Arjuna.

Obviously, the vision of the one who is relieved from the momentary impacts and bifurcated attentions revels in the glories of the very being which is ever in peace and balance. For him the obvious contradictions – the divine and the human, the living and the non-living, the moving and the static, the temporal and the eternal, the material and the spiritual, the luminous and the non-luminous, birth and death, love and hatred, etc. – are all occasions in the play of the Infinite, and are looked upon as component nuances of truth stretched beyond their mutual tensions and oppositions to form a magnificent tune. He not only sees through them, but sees beneath them to catch the hand of the contriver, the law of the Infinite Being, in the eternal theme of consolidation, like the ‘thread which holds the beads together’ (7.7). No wonder Arjuna, who had this privilege, had happy horripilations at the sight of the mysterious (vismayāviṣṭaḥ hṛṣṭaromā dhananjayaḥ – 11.14) and declared: “My illusions are set at naught, my remembrance regained; I come to be myself burying my doubts.” (naṣṭo mohaḥ smṛtirlabdhā … sthito’smi gatasaṃdehaḥ – 18.73). The vision of the Infinite Being, of its dimensions and operations, is a salvaging agent, and it is significant to notice Arjuna saying: “I come to be myself,” and “I remember.” The real inner connection with the reality recovered, he feels that he is not new, but only as being eternally there, yet lost in the mirage of delusion and forgetfulness. This is consolidation of being – a metaphysical rejuvenation or restoration of personality and value, which had been lost in the confusions of ‘ontological amnesia’.

For one who does not have this and the joy of ontological recovery, values are just empirical and emerge out of mutual oppositions. But for one who has this recovery of his links with eternity, conflict is only an occasion of growth or standing up gearing himself to the challenges of eternal Infinity appearing now as strength, courage, duty, truthfulness, kindness, peace, harmony, etc. While the unsalvaged, who is caught up in the mesh of empirical evaluations, sees these contingent values to be let gone as individual only, the one who has recovered himself sees them as accomplished elements in the infinite theme, beyond his life-limits and ego-achievements. He sees value in everything, beauty in everything, and the luster of the Infinite shining through the starry heavens and the pupils of the earth-born. He enjoys it as the overflow of grace, as the bliss of Being. A devotion intensified by the knowledge of the whole truth gets converted into an ecstasy of love, and one who knows is lost in admiration, enjoying the wondrous object of his love in each and every being. This is consummation which no ordinary living being can have.

16“Do You See As I See?”

The Lord’s incessant question throughout the Gita seems to be one like:

“Do you see as I see?”

Evidently, the demand is for a total transformation of the vision far beyond the individual human calculations of Reality. The implications of the Lord’s grant, “I will give you the divine vision or perspective (11.8),” seems to have had its effect on Arjuna when he declared:

My delusions are set at naught, my remembrance regained and I come to be myself burying my doubts (18.73).

Arjuna had the mystic vision of Reality, and nothing less than the divine vision could have worked this transformation in his thought and being. Perhaps an invitation is here for us to pass beyond the rational and empirical standards to mysticism or intimacy with Reality, which breaks open the individual from the defenses of psychosis and dividing intellect and delivers him into a boundless freedom and existence. Mysticism effaces the fortress of definitions of being, yet bestows meaning and value on things hitherto unrecognized, even as it bridges the chasms of the disconnected and the unconnectable. Mysticism is restoration of the contact (saṃsparśa) lost in the ordinary life with the boundless state of existence rendering one to be himself, overcoming, as it were, his ‘ontological amnesia’, as it happened in the case of Arjuna.

There seems to be a grandeur or significance about the mystic vision of Arjuna, for he overcame his rationalizations about his immediate surroundings and personal considerations of losses and gains within the human situation he was in, and enters into a ‘trans-aesthetic’ condition of joy and admiration at the beauty of being his own infinite Self. Aesthetically, his feelings were a thousand degrees more intense than those of a poet or an artist, as they involved his whole personality, and made him, as it were, run back to the recesses of the unconscious forming the larger background of his contemporary existence, and go forward to the influx of consciousness of the yet-to-be. This was the experience of the boundless past and a boundless future making itself available in the vision of a divine moment. It was a point in his experience, but unlike any marked on a paper, for example. It was a ‘pinhole’ through which he peeped out of the customary time and space to a ‘beyond’ where time-space complex vanished. When he declared he had ‘regained his being’, he had passed through the ‘pinhole’ and got his vision ‘reversed’, as was evident in his confession. He is now blessed with a mystic vision which is a point-to-point converse, a converse which is not ‘distorted’ and which does not stop at the surface – as the normal vision stops at phenomena – but penetrates through and through, establishing a relationship with Reality most intimately. Arjuna had the first intimations of immortality and eternity. That is a direct knowledge, and we can make this out as the unique stuff of a mystic’s perspective: Where we see out, he sees in. Where we reflect and reason, he feels. Where we feel, he enjoys. These converses are mysterious to us, but mysticism is not mysterious. It is a perspective which a personality takes of the roots of Consciousness issuing forth as the world and life or the universe of thought and being, with interconnections well established. A perspective such as this is neither ‘mysterious’ nor ‘transcendent’ in the mistaken sense of obscurity and unrelatedness. It is, in a real sense, coming down to the brass tacks of Reality with the clearest of visions. Neither is it ‘supe-rnatural’ in the sense of going away from the natural. But it is ‘ultra-natural’, for its aim is to be conversant with all existence and, therefore, a bridging between the ‘infra-’ at one end and ‘ultra-’ at the other. The range of vision is multi-dimensional and takes an infinite sweep. With no impediments of a physical retina, it sees things as they are, bereft of their relativism. No wonder Arjuna was in a thousand raptures when he saw as the Lord saw.

The Scheme Of The Translation And Its Perspective

This is a fresh attempt at presenting the text of the Gita. In offering this work, the approach to the text of the Gita will have to be stated. The size and extent of the text is not questioned, and what the tradition has accepted as a full-length dialogue of seven hundred verses is followed. But against the traditional practice of accepting the divisions of the text into chapters in order to grasp its philosophy, a gestalt is sought out over and above the schemes of the scholiasts and colophons. It appears to the present writer that considerable harm has been done to our understanding of the text by the chapter headings.

Further, the classification of the chapters into ‘sixes’, as is sometimes done, does not help us in the correct appreciation of the philosophy. We see it clearly that the philosophy is expounded by the Lord as and when the topical problems were raised by Arjuna, and we should not forget the fact that at the time of the exposition the Lord was not bound by the designations the colophons have set on His themes.

Naturally, when the Lord expounded His philosophy, there have been repetitions, disconnections, digressions, but none out of the point. Seen across the ‘chapters’ (the text is usually divided into) we have a remarkable consistency and precision. Krishna clearly indicates the various universes of discourse, defines terms that occur, points out their applications, critically examines prevalent views and rectifies confusions, all through driving at a philosophy which is comprehensive as it also illumines the topic He discusses.

Instead of the usual order in which the text is presented, here is an attempt made to select and arrange the dialogue between Sri Krishna and Arjuna under four major themes around which the discourse revolves.

They are:

i. The Super-knowledge of Self-being,

ii. The Enlightened Attunement,

iii. The Dimensions or Dialectics of the Infinite Being, and

iv. The Dynamics of Recoilless Action

There is a view that the Gita is a jumble of many ideas, mostly repetitive and sometimes contradictory. However, once the arrangement is made on the lines attempted here, it would be seen that the text is consistent throughout; and where a repetition occurs, it will be seen to be purposive, that is, to emphasize the points made. It also becomes evident by this arrangement how clear the exposition of the thought is, how precise the definitions of the concepts are and how they fall into a pattern related to the rest of the thought structure.

It is sometimes urged that the Gita is a difficult text. There is a point here. However, the difficulty in understanding the unity of thought in it may be entirely due to the way in which the dialogue is presented, usually interspersed first by the chapter-headings, and second by the intellectual digressions that come up. The present attempt tries to overcome these possible reasons which create the difficulties by avoiding both the usual chapter-headings and the digressions.

Confusion is likely to occur by the obvious impressions the chapter-headings leave on the minds of the readers and by the loss of links that occur between the long dialogues. And so, the entire thought of the Gita is taken here as one unit, i.e. in one gestalt (as even suggested by Sri Krishna by the use of the significant term samagraṃ – 7.1). Accordingly, the whole theme is projected in four aspects, covering the whole range of the thought, as against the eighteen chapters we are accustomed to.

The four aspects are highlighted here by suitable titles, focusing our attention on the consistently developed themes. The reduction, however, into four sections only of the thought of the Gita should not be taken as an attempt at discovering a minimal or ‘original’ Gita, as some scholars has done. The entire text is sacrosanct, and the selection as well as the rearrangement have the limited objective of just focusing the attention on the themes.

With regard to the translation, it is submitted here that more than being prosaic and literal, it aims, while still keeping close to the text, to express the inner meaning of the terms within the context of the themes. The terms in the Gita such as karma, dharma, yoga, vibhūti, māyā, ātma, either singly or in combinations like ātma-yoga, ātma-vibhūti, yoga-māyā etc. are used to convey specific meanings relative to circumstances in which they occur, and in the spirit of the general philosophy of the text, as understood in the present attempt. They do not convey identical meanings in all occurrences. And so, an attempt is made here to feel the pulse of the thought, as it were, behind the use of the terms, and to convey the inner sense approximately.

Keeping in view the general philosophy of the text, interconnections are shown by means of parenthetical words or phrases to complete the meanings. The Gita is its own commentary, and the parentheses are aimed only to unravel it. No extra commentary is necessary, as the text stands rendered here.

In the text of the translation, the mutual addresses by Sri Krishna and Arjuna by their actual names, titles or alternatives are omitted.

I. The Super-knowledge of Self-being

2.10. Hṛṣīkeśa (i.e. Krishna) then, smiling, as it were, (at Arjuna’s condition) said to him who was despondent (and still) in the midst of two armies.

Krishna:

2.11. You grieve for them who should not be grieved for – and yet, you speak words of wisdom! The (really) wise (knowing the truth of life and death) grieve neither for the living nor for the dead.

2.12. Never was there an occasion when I did not exist, nor you, nor these lords among men. Also, never shall we cease to be in the future.

2.13. For the one who has the body is there childhood, youth and death. So, also, change of body. The one who knows (the dialectics of being) never is baffled (by the changing occasions).

2.16. Of the asat (the non-existent) there is no occurrence. For the sat (the existent) non-occurrence is not. Verily, the seers of the ‘that’ness of things see the secret of both.

2.17. Know, then, that by which all this is pervaded is indestructible. Of that which is undiminishing no destruction is made possible by any force.

2.18. These bodies (growing, dying and changing) have their destruction. But the one who bears the body is eternal. Of which is said: indestructible, incommensurate. So (understanding this truth,) you may fight.

2.20. This is neither born, nor does it die by any means. This (principle, so described,) has not occurred, nor is going to occur. It is unborn, eternal, unceasing and basic. (And so,) when the body is slain, it is not slain.

2.21. The one who knows this to be indestructible, eternal, unborn, undiminishing, how can he (ever) think of affecting or killing it?

2.24. Uncut, unburnt, unwet, undried (is this principle, spoken). It is eternal, indivisible, all-pervading, stable, unmoved, and ever is.

2.25. Indeterminate, unthinkable, non-mutable, it is said to be. Knowing it as such, you ought not to grieve.

2.29. If one sees this as the mysterious, another speaks of it as the mysterious, yet another hears of it as the mysterious. Still, having heard of it (this way) none understands it.

2.30. The one who bears the body is not killed in any body. He is eternal. Therefore, no being which into comes to being is worthy of your concern.

2.39. This – what has been said – is the Super-knowledge of self-being (i.e. Sāṃkhya).

II.On The Enlightened Attunement

2.39. Now listen to what follows of the enlightened attunement (buddhi yoga). With that enlightenment you are redeemed from the bonds of contingencies (i.e. of contingent events and actions).

2.40. Here, in this (scheme of attunement), a work when begun does not become futile, nor is there a jarring (even). A little of this bearing (i.e. the truth) saves us from the great terror (of destruction).

2.41. The intelligence that is oriented this way is fixed in the One (theoria). But the non-oriented intelligence is verily divided in its attention.

2.47. (In this scheme) you have freedom or authority for doing, but none whatsoever about the consequences (of what you may do). Let yourself not feel responsible for the result (of your action). But this should not make you think you can be (irresponsibly) indifferent (and so think of relinquishing responsibility for action).

2.48. Established in this condition of attunement (yoga) perform action with detachment, treating equally success and failure. Equanimity is the state named (if it is done so).

2.49. Mere (mechanical) work (however,) is inferior to work performed with enlightened attunement. Crave to surrender (at the altar of this) enlightenment. The small-minded are those who seek the result (only).

2.50. The one of enlightened attunement abdicates both the moral merits and sin (in this scheme of dedication). Therefore, for serving the state (i.e., yoga, mentioned above, or samatvam) you strive. The state (as well) is dexterity or art in action.

2.51. Verily, a person of enlightened attunement abandons the fruits of action, and so, is released from the bonds of birth, and attains a tensionless state.

2.52. When the snares of delusion are overcome by your enlightenment, then you attain objectivity with regard to whatever you will have heard (about your seeking) and whatever you may hear (of them later).

2.53. When your understanding gets stabilised (about this), overcoming the confusions of whatever you will have heard or will hear, you attain to the undisturbed state of equanimity (yoga samādhi).

Arujna:

2.54. What is the insignia of him whose understanding is steady (and similarly, what is the insignia) of his state of equanimity? How does he, whose understanding is set (on his truth), talk of things and conduct himself (in his life)?

Krishna:

2.55. He who has dismissed all desires of all things of the mind and finds consummation in the Self alone is said to be established in enlightenment.

2.56. One who is not distressed in pain nor enjoys (being) in pleasure, and is free from fear and anger, is stable-minded and is known as one who is silent.

2.57. He who has no (carnal) love for anything, who does not rejoice getting good (things), nor hate receiving bad (things), his understanding is well stabilised.

2.61. He whose senses lie well controlled, and who sits firmly oriented towards Me has his understanding well stabilised.

2.69. Whatever is night for all, for this self-controlled person, it is day. And when all other creatures keep awake (about things), the self-controlled sees darkness (therein).

2.70. Ever getting filled by the inflowing waters, but unchanging and established in itself, the ocean remains. Even so, befall all fulfillments into the one who wins peace, but not into the one who craves all desires.

2.71. Throwing all desires (to winds), the man (of steadfast understanding) moves about all existence, with no attachment or love or ego. It is he who wins the state of peace.

2.72. This is the state of the Infinite: (brāhmī-sthiti). Winning this, one is never deluded (by anything). Established in it, he remains (when he lives here), and at the time of passing, he is absorbed into Infinity.

5.7. One who is in the attuned state (yoga) is pure of soul, selfconquered, sense-conquered, the Self of all selves. And him, no work that he does taints.

5.8. The one who lives in the truth (of the infinite dialectics) and is established in it, thinks he does not do anything – even though he sees, hears, touches, smells, eats, goes about, sleeps, breathes,

5.9. talks, excretes, receives, blinks, etc. (as we all do). And these are the works he does (to live in the body), and he behaves as though the senses are (just) responding to sense-objects.

5.10. Whoever thus offers up all actions to the Infinite and does them with no attachment is one who is not tainted, even like the lotus leaf in water.

5.11. For overcoming the impurities of the ego of finiteness (in attitudes and behaviour), the attuned do function by their body, mind, intelligence and even the senses, but without any sort of attachment.

5.13. The one who resides in the body of nine openings knowingly offers away all actions (in this way). Self- controlled, he sits enjoying, neither doing nor causing to do.

5.14. (The dialectics of Self-existence is such that) the Lord (residing in the body) does not create the doer-ship, nor the deeds, nor even the cause-effect relationship. The Infinite moves by is own nature.

5.15. (In this dialectics of Infinite Being) the Infinite (Self within the body of nine openings) receives not the sins of others, nor their good. (If one thinks not so,) it is ignorance enveloping knowledge, by which creatures are deluded.

5.16. (As opposed to this,) if one’s wisdom destroys the ignorance (of doer-ship, deeds and accruing results, etc.), then such wisdom, like the brilliance of the Sun, reveals the transcendent reality.

5.17. With that wisdom, whoever is attuned with devotion to the infinitude of the Self, he, cleansed by the wisdom, never gets back (into the chain of births).

5.18. (Understanding the dialectics of the Infinite Being,) such a wise man looks at all existents with equanimity (and does not differentiate the value of beings from the point of view of their Self), be it a highly cultured Brahmin, a cow, an elephant, a dog or a meat-eater;

5.19. moreover, has his mind fixed in such equanimity, and has conquered the chain of rebirths here itself. Verily the Infinite is equally pure in all existents, and therefore such men (who see thus) exist in the Infinite itself.

5.20. At the occurrence of the delightful, they are not delighted, and (equally,) at the occurrence of the undesirable, they are not agitated. With stability of understanding (about the relativity of these contingents), they are not deluded. The knowers of the Infinite exist in the Infinite.

5.21. The one who moves about or established (thus) in the dialectics of Infinity is unattached to external feelings, and has his delight in/of the inner Self, and attains the undiminishing bliss (of Infinite Being).

5.22. The wise one (who is established in Infinity, thus) never delights in things born of the contact of the external senses, which cause pain (and are relative), as they arise and disappear.

5.23. Before casting off the body (which one is carrying), if one has the ability to bear the intensity arising out of desire and anger, he is a blessed man who is attuned to the dialectics of the Infinite.

5.24. Whosoever finds delight internally in the inner Self finds comfort in it and illumination too. Such one is attuned, and at casting of the body, attains absorption in the Infinity.

5.25. Those sages, whose dirt (i.e. sin) is washed and who have broken through dualities (and divisions of existence) and are self-controlled, revel in the delight of all existents and are lost in the rhythm of the Infinite.

5.26. Those who know the dimensions of their own Self (to be infinite thus) are freed from desire and anger, and are mind-controlled, sense-controlled. They attain liberation here (in this empirical life).

6.15. The attuned is self-controlled, mind-controlled, and attains peace, the transcendental bliss, My state.

6.27. The attuned, whose mind is still, gets the highest joy, passionless peace and attains the taintless infinitude.

6.28. In this way, the attuned who is self-controlled and is free from all taints, with no difficulty attains the highest of bliss, viz. the living contact with Infinity (brahma saṃsparśaṃ).

6.29. One who is attuned (with Infinity), whose nature of being is to look at things equally, sees the Self in all existents and all existents in the Self.

6.30. Whoever envisions My Being everywhere, and everything having being in Me, him I do not lose, nor he ever loses Me.

6.31. Whoever adores Me as existing in all existents in an unalienated state of being (ekatvaṃ), in whatever condition he may be, is the attuned (yogi) and lives in Me.

6.32. Whether it is pleasure or pain, the one who sees the same everywhere, as like unto himself, is the highest attuned, according to Me.

Arjuna:

6.37. What happens to one, who, though losing control over the mind, yet has faith (in the enlightened attunement), but cannot attain to that perfection of attunement, as his concentration is not (yet) fixed in it?

Who longs for the real (knowledge) of the ways of the Infinite Being, but is confused by the divergent ideas (that he might have heard about it), and, overcome by their fascination, is confounded?[28]

6.38. Is he not destroyed, fallen from both – ubhayaṃ – (i.e. faith in the enlightened attunement and knowledge of the real), like a torn and splintered cloud (destroyed by the winds), and, finding no stay anywhere, gets confused about the way of the Infinite?

Krishna:

6.40. Neither in this (world) nor in that is any destruction of him who has done something (in the direction of the good). Good is never met with ill-fate (or destruction).

Arjuna:

12.1. Of your devotees, who are the better adepts in the attunement to your Being: those who by constant absorption worship Thee thus (i.e. in Your pleasing form, now taken by You – 11.51) or those who also (by constant absorption) worship the immutable (in all existents) and the invisible (awe-inspiring mysterious form of Your Infinite Being you made me see earlier – 11.17, 20)?

Krishna:

12.2. Those with emotion-filled mind but constant in devotion and intense in faith are more ecstatically absorbed (in Me.)

12.3. Even those (others) who worship (Me in My impersonal universal form of Infinitude) the immutable, the undefinable and unmanifest condition, and (treat me as beyond all categories of thought but basically present (in all) constantly,

12.4. by restraining and subordinating all senses (unlike, mind only, as in the previous case), treating everything in the order of existence with no alienated feeling, and rejoicing at the consolidation of every entity, realise Me only.

12.5. (However,) their involvement is (obviously) more, as they are intending to catch the dialectics of the unseen. Having a physical body (with all its delimiting disadvantages) to keep track of the formless is really strenuous.

12.6. Still, whosoever (as the above devotees) offer all their activities to Me, and by an unswerving application, meditate and worship Me, for them, soon I become the redeemer of their chain of death (and birth).

12.13-14. Whosoever has no hatred towards any being, except that of friendliness and sympathy, with no selfishness or ego, and is balanced both in hardship and comfort, whosoever is always forgiving, content, controlled, firmly resolved, having an understanding (about the truth), and attuned always to Me, such a devotee of Mine is very dear to Me.

12.15. By him the setup of the cosmic law is not disturbed (as he is always attuned to it.) He is freed from joy or sorrow. (He) is free from the fear of anything. Such a devotee is dear to Me.

12.16. He wants nothing (for himself), is chaste, an adept (in doing things), yet unattached, with any sorrow of failure thrown off. He does not boast of any work as having been initiated by him (for it is already done by the cosmic law); such a devotee is dear to Me.

12.17. He neither rejoices (over his success or glory) nor angered (at failure). He neither grieves nor desires. (He) is always unattached to the good and bad of things. Such a devoted soul is dear to Me.

12.18,19. He is equal (in his reaction) both towards his friend and enemy, (for he has none of these). Even so, at times of his being praised or ridiculed he is calm, and (unaffected) when the wind blows cold or hot towards him. He has no preferences to make (in this relative life). He is equal to both blame and praise, and is silent, for he knows (the truth), and is satisfied with whatever comes by. He has no private home (to call his own), being unattached. He is firm in his resolve about his cosmic bearing) and is devoted (to the universal). Such a one is dear to Me.

12.20. Whoever, without exception, with devotion to Me, the Highest, partakes of this immortal cosmic truth, as taught by Me, such a devotee is dearest to Me.

III. On The Dimensions And Dialectics Of The Infinite

Krishna:

7.1. With a mind pining for Me, practising attunement, seeking refuge in Me, how you could know Me (i.e. My infinite dimensions and dialectics) as a whole (samagraṃ, i.e. as a gestalt), listen to Me (as I narrate).

7.2. I shall teach you this wisdom, along with its analysis, in full. Knowing this there remains nothing more to be known.

7.3. Of a thousand men, one strives (with concentration) for perfection (in understanding). Of these successful men, scarcely one knows the truth (of how I exist and operate).

7.4. My nature (prakṛti) is eightfold: earth, water, fire, air, ether, mind, egoism and intellect.

7.5. This constitutes the inferior stratum (of My being). Know My higher stratum of nature, which is different and is the enlivening element, by which the whole cosmos is sustained.

7.6. Understand that existents (or creatures) have their source in this. But (do not mistake), I am the originator of all creation, as well as of destruction.

7.7. Besides my Being, there exists nothing whatsoever (in itself and by itself). By Me all this universe of beings (living and nonliving) are linked like the thread holding the beads (in a wreath).

7.8. In water, I am the taste. In moon and sun, I am brilliance. Among the Vedic (formulae), I am the praṇava (i.e. Om). In space, I am the sound. In the male, I am virility.

7.9. In the earth, I am the sweet smell, and (I am) radiance in the fire. In the living existents I am life. In tapasvins, I am their ardour.

7.10. Know Me to be the eternal seed in all beings. (I am) intelligence of the intelligent, the glimmer in all that shines.

7.11. Of the strong, I am strength. Free from all carnal desires and lust, I am love, which does not go against the real or right nature of creatures.

7.12. Whatever that is soft (and nice), dynamic (and raging), dark (and obstructing), know them as rooted in Me. But (understand fully well), I am not (rooted) in them (as they are in Me.)

7.13. This world of human beings is deluded by these guṇas (enchanting forces), and (consequently) does not recognise Me the transcendent (link and root of all beings) and the unaffected principle.

7.14. Verily, this is the uniqueness of My divine potency (daivī māyā), and it is difficult to escape its power (and transgress its law). But whoever is attuned to My way of being, he alone can cross over the delusions (or snares) of these (distracting) forces.

7.15. Their intelligence or wisdom stolen by (the aforesaid) divine potency, the evil doers, the idiotic and the worst of men working on evil designs, do not seek my (redeeming) shelter.

7.24. The unmanifest has now become the manifest, so think the unwise of Me. They do not comprehend My transcending state (paraṃ bhāva) of My undiminishing and unsurpassable being.

7.25. Shining from within My creative mystery (yoga māyā), I am not visible to one and all. Me, the unborn, the undiminishing, the unwise of the world do not comprehend.

7.26. (Being eternally Myself,) I know the past, the present and the future of all existents. But none comprehends Me (who is eternal, and the ground and continuity of all these phases of being).

7.27. Even as they are born, all the creatures are deluded by the dualities arising out of desire and hate (caused by the infatuations created by My daivī māyā).

7.28. But those whose sins get diminished by their good deeds are freed from the infatuations of dualities and seek alignment with My being (i.e. My plan of things) with firm conviction.

7.29. Striving to be delivered from disease and death, those who seek refuge in me (by attuning to Me) can know everything, viz. the Infinite, the Self and the dynamics of Being.

7.30. (Besides,) whoever knows Me along with the basically elemental, basically divine and the basic sacrifice (or offering) are attuned in mind (and so,) comprehend (and consequently are absorbed into My being) when they depart from here.

Arjuna:

8.1. Which is the Infinite, the essential Spirit, and the basically elemental (to which you have now referred)? What is that which is basically divine here (spoken of by you?)

8.2. What is that which forms the basic sacrifice? (Tell me, again,) how You are understood by the disciplined men, at the time of their departure.

Krishna:

8.3. (I shall tell you in order.) What exists beyond all mutations and destructions is the Infinite. Its essential nature is spiritual. The bringing in of all existents is the dynamis.

8.4. What undergoes mutation and destruction is essentially the material (or elemental). The resident (in all existents) who experiences is the essential divinity. (And the truth of existence and its mode of operation is) the basic sacrifice, which is Me alone.

8.5. Whoever, while departing from here, has the intuition of this dialectics of My Being, leaving his body, enters My Being – about which there is no doubt.

8.18. At creation, all unmanifest things come to be manifested, and at destruction, they are re-sunk into the condition of the unmanifest.

8.19. Beyond their own powers, these creatures are put forth and withdrawn, time in and out, at creation and destruction, respectively.

8.20. But verily, there is yet another (principle, which is not subjected thus, and is) beyond the unmanifest (from where creatures emerge and into which they resolve), which is eternal and unmanifest (to the categories of knowledge and experience). It is that which remains when all the mutable and the destroyable pass away.

8.21. That they say is the Transcendental Being (the sat or ontos) unmanifest to knowledge and is indestructible (as Being). Attaining this state, none relapses (to the deluded life). That is My state, which transcends all.

8.22. Within which all existents find their locus, and by which all existents are pervaded, that transcendent is the resident, which is realisable only through unswerving devotion (or loving commitment).

9.1. (Now) this knowledge, with its practicability, I shall narrate to you. It is a great secret, knowing which you will get liberated (provided you put it into practice).

9.2. This is the best (from the scientific point of view), as also, it is sacred (from the religious one). It is the royal science (or truth), and the royal secret (to be initiated into). It is realisable here and now as a religious truth and practicable with ease in one piece.

9.3. Those men, who do not have faith in this (royal) truth, do not get Me, and so get back to the chain of deaths (and births).

9.4. (The mystical teaching is this:) Mysteriously hidden, all this existence is pervaded by Me (the Infinite). All existents are based in Me, but not I (the incommensurate) in them.

9.5. Look at my mysterious state of existence: the existents do not exist in Me (the way you think things exist in. The dialectics of My Self-existence is) that it bears all existents, conserves, yet is not borne by them.

9.6. Like the great wind existing in space and moving about eternally, so the entire existence lies in Me (and moves about).

9.7. All existents tend to My condition or state. At creation, I put them out, and at the end of the period, I withdraw them.

9.8. In keeping with the law of My nature, I put them forth again and again, and all these in toto lend themselves to the dialectics of that law of nature, with no ingrained power to go against.

9.9. The (cosmic) doings do not bind Me. But in all this dynamics, I sit untainted like an objective witness.

9.10. Under My witnessing, the law of My being (i.e. nature) puts forth the moving and the unmoving; and so, the universe moves on.

9.11. Those who are ignorant (of this secret law of My being and modus operandi) do not know Me who has taken up this human form. They do not understand My transcendent state (paraṃ bhāva). I am the Supreme Lord of all existence (but not a creature born).

9.12. (The ignorant are) vain in their aspirations, vain in their efforts, vain in their knowledge (of reality) and vain too in their senses. Deluded, they stay in their fiendlike (designs) and evil nature.

9.13. (But unlike them,) the noble-souled find their shelter in My dynamis. Knowing the secret of all existence in a jiff (i.e. in one piece, as I narrated,) they are devoted with no distraction (from the Truth).

9.14. Ever glorifying Me, they are controlled and firm in their practice. With deep absorption, they participate in My dynamis (i.e. dialectics of being) and surrender to it (as their only resort.)

9.15. Yet there are others (who with a religious devotion) offer all their knowledge to Me (the goal) and worship Me in manifold ways: sometimes as one, and sometimes as taking many forms.

9.16. (But know the secret, the goal of all meditation and worship.) I am Myself the will behind all offerings. I am the sweet libation too. I am the herb and the sacred formula (Om), as well. I am the ghee (that you pour as oblation) and the fire (you pour into, as well). (And what’s more,) I am the burnt even.

9.17. I am the father, the mother, the support and the grandsire of the entire cosmos. I am what is to be known as the sacred Om even. I am (the Vedas, that is) the Ṛk, the Sāma and the Yajus.

9.18. The consummation, the protector, the Lord, the witness, the locus and the shelter. I am the friend, the source of all creation, and (the cause of all) destruction. (I am) the store house (from which all energy and meaning are drawn). (I am) the seed of all production, and in short, all (that you may see, and may not see).

9.19. I am the heat (in the universe, which sustains it). I pour down and withdraw rains. I am immortality, as even I am death. I am also what is and what is not (in this universe of yours).

9.29. In all existents, I am fully found (but not in a diminished way). For Me no one is an enemy, none a friend. Whoever worships Me with devotion is resting in My order of being, and I am with them.

9.30. Even if he is of mean character (from the point of view of others), if devoted to Me, he is to be taken as the good-souled, as he is fixed in the right goal or theoria.

9.31. They soon become noble-souled (by their choice dedication) and get everlasting peace. Know (it for certain) My devotee is never lost.

9.32. Let them be sinfully born, be women, tradesmen, or of low caste – even they, by attuning to Me, get to the highest State of My Being.

9.33. (If so,) is it necessary for Me to proclaim what would happen to the noble-bred, the devoted and the noble kings? You may get (the kingship of) this world, which, however, is transient and joyless. But you be devoted to Me (for overcoming all sins of acquisitions and conduct).

9.34. Be My-minded, My-devotee, My-worshipper. Salute Me and surrender to the law of My self-existence. If (you do) so, you will attain Me.

10.1. Listen, again, to my ultra dictum (paramaṃ vacaṃ). Wishing your welfare, I declare it to you, My beloved (friend).

10.2. Neither deities nor seers know my roots, for I am the root of everyone – the deities and the seers.

10.3. He who knows Me, the unborn, the uncaused, and the great Lord of the universe, is the clear-headed among the mortals, and is freed from all blemishes.

10.4. Reason (or logic), wisdom, non-delusion, forgiveness, truthfulness, self-control, happiness, misery, coming into being and going out of being, fear and fearlessness,

10.5. non-injury, equality, contentment, meditation, charity, fame, infamy, and whatever other dispositions and moods that may occur among the creatures you know, arise because of Me only (as the root).

10.6. The seven great sages, the ancient four Manus, originated by My thought only. From them proceeded the entire world and the creatures.

10.7. Whoever knows the secret of My self-projections and self-existence (vibhūtiṃ ca yogaṃ ca), is absorbed by the dialectics of My Being, if his attunement is unfaltering.

10.8. I am the originator of all existents and by Me they move. Knowing this the wise worship Me with ecstacy.

10.9. Always thinking of Me, living in tune with My Being, mutually enlightening each other (on My dynamics of being and operation) and always dilating upon My glory, they are delighted and (they) enjoy the bliss (of being and participation in it) (tuṣyanti ca ramanti ca).

10.10. To them, who are incessantly attuned to this (mode of living), and who with love pray to Me (with a sense of dedication), I shall bestow (the most potent) enlightened way of identification (with My Being) by which they come to rest in Me.

Arjuna:

10.16. Please enlighten me fully about Your divine Self-projections (vibhūtayaḥ), pervaded (or covered) by which these universes exist.

10.17. Oh, Yogin, how should I understand You, reflecting upon You? By what varied feelings should You be meditated on?

10.18. Please repeat to me in detail Your state of self-existence and the state of self-projection (yogam vibhūtim ca). There cannot be any satiation in listening to your words of ambrosia (which immortalise anyone).

Krishna:

10.19. Let Me narrate to you My divine Self-projection (and Self-existence). But as there is no end to the ways of My Self-existence, I shall only tell you the most prominent or typical (of them).

10.20. I am Self-established as the core (or foundation) of all existents. (Being Infinite existence,) I am the beginning, the middle and the culmination of all existents.

10.21 I am Vishnu among the ādityas. The radiant Sun among the luminaries. I am Marīci of the maruts. I am the Moon among the (twinkling) stars (in the night).

10.22. I am the Sāma Veda of the Vedas. Among the divinities, I am Vāsava. Among the sense organs, I am manas. I am life among the existents.

10.23. Of the rudras, I am Śaṃkara. Of the yakṣas and rākṣasas, I am Kubera. Of the vasus, I am Fire, and among the peaks, I am Meru.

10.24. Among the household priests, know Me as Bṛhaspati, the revered one. Of the generals, I am Skanda. Of the vast waters, I am the Ocean.

10.25. Of the great sages, I am Bhṛgu. Of syllables I am that One Syllable (Om). Of the offerings (i.e. sacrifices) I am the silent repetition (of the mantra). Of the unmovable entities, I am (the very) Himalaya.

10.26. Of all the trees, I am (the sacred) Aswattha. Of the divine sages, I am Nārada, and of the gandharvas, I am Citraratha. And of the siddhas I am Kapila.

10.27. Know that among the (mighty) horses, I am Uccaiḥśravas. Of the elephants, I am Airāvata, the nector-born. And of men, I am (the royal) king.

10.28. I am Vajra among the weapons, Kāmadhenu among the cows, and of the serpants I am Vāsuki.

10.29. Of the nagas, I am Ananta. Of the water-deities, I am Varuṇa. I am Āryaman among ancestors. And of the subduers, I am (none but) Yama.

10.30. Of the daityas, I am Prahlada. I am Time of the measures. I am the lion among the wild animals, and Vainateya among the birds.

10.31. Of the purifiers, I am Pavana (Vāyu). Of the wielders of weapons, I am Rāma. I am Makara among fish, and of the streams, I am Jāhnavī.

10.32. Of creation I am the beginning, the middle and the end. And of all knowledge, I am the knowledge of the Self. I am dialectics of the dialecticians.

10.33. Among alphabets, I am A, and of compounds, the dual. I am the everlasting time and multifaceted supporter of beings.

10.34. Of the destroyers, I am Death. Of the things that come up in future, I am (their very) commencement. Of the feminine terms, I am fame, prosperity, memory, intelligence, firmness and forgiveness.

10.35. Of the hymns, I am the great Sāma, and of the metres I am Gāyatri. Of the months I am Mārgaśīrṣa. Of the seasons I am spring.

10.36. Among the gamblers, I am fraud. I am brilliance of the brilliant. I am success, determination and goodness of the good (men).

10.37. Of the vṛṣṇis, I am Vāsudeva. And among the pāṇḍavas I am Dhanaṃjaya. Among the sages I am Vyāsa, and of the poets I am Uśanā.

10.38. Among the controllers, I am scepter. In the seekers of success, I am moral law; and among the secrets I am silence. And of the knowers, I am knowledge.

10.39. Whatever being there be, I am the seed. Leaving Me out, there cannot be any existent moving or unmoving (in the way you have heard Me declare).

10.40. With regard to My divine forms and projections, there is no end whatever. Therefore, the instances that I have narrated now are only a few samples of My extensions of self-projections (vibhūtervistaro mayā).

10.41. Whatever is glorious, good, beautiful and mighty (in a nutshell) you know (very clearly) issue forth from a fragment of My splendor.

10.42. Of what use is the knowledge of all these details to you (if it does not become part of your experience)? Having enveloped this vast universe only with a fragment of My being, I remain what I am.

Arjuna:

11.1. To grace me, you have initiated me into an extremely secret and symbolic spiritual science (i.e. metaphysics). By what You have revealed, this delusion of mine (which bothered me till now) is destroyed.

11.2. In great detail, I have heard from You the dialectics of the truth of creation and destruction of existents, and also of the secret of your unchanging Being.

11.3. Even as You gave the word picture of Your Self-projections (description of vibhūtis), Great Lord, I desire to see (and participate in) the dynamics of your splendorous state, oh, Supreme Puruṣa!

11.4. If you think I can stand the vision, oh, Lord, then, show me that indivisible dimension of your self-existence.

Krishna:

11.5-7. See My multiforms (I described to you) a hundredfold, varieties of divine forms, in various colours and dimensions. (Here) see the ādityas, vasus, rudras, aświns, also the maruts. See many more things you have not seen (or heard) hitherto, and which are all mysterious. See how the whole range of the cosmos, the moving and the unmoving, and whatever you want to see, embedded in one inalienable piece in my being.

11.8. Verily, you are not capable of seeing Me with your ordinary eyes (as you have rightly realised). I shall give you divine eyes, so that you may see my splendorous state of existence.

Saṃjaya:

11.9. So saying, Hari, the great Lord of Yoga, revealed His Highest and Magnificent state (or dimension).

11.13. Then, Arjuna saw in the unity of a single being (ekastham), the body of the divine of the divinities, the whole expanse of existence analysed in many forms

11.14. by which (revelation or vision) Arjuna was mystified, and stood in horripilations, reverently saluting with folded hands, and bending his head down (in surrender) to the Divine Being.

Arjuna:

11.15. I recognise in thy divine body (in a piece) all the divinities: Lord Brahma seated on the lotus, the riṣis, the divine serpents; even so, all creatures of peculiar and strange forms (I could never imagine or fathom).

11.16. I see Your infinite form of being everywhere (in each bit of existence) with infinite hands, stomachs, faces and eyes. I see no beginning no middle and no end to your cosmic dimension.

11.17. I see You, Oh, God with crown, mace and discus filling all existence with your abundant glory and luminosity, shining from all sides, like the sun and the moon – a sight invisible of the incommensurate.

11.18. (I see) You are the imperishable and the highest to be known. You are the ultimate stay of this universe. (I see you) unexpended (with all your expansions). The eternal preserver of the cosmic law, You are the most fundamental being, viz. the resident in all, as I am seeing.

11.19. (I witness) the beginningless, middleless and endless infinite, potency. I see you with hands infinite, a face illumined and blazing, warming up this existence with the brightness of your own Self.

11.20. By your single being, you are pervading all directions, linking up the skies with the worlds. The worlds are taken aback seeing Your mysterious terribly expansive dimension, endless as it is.

11.38. You are the primal (or the basic divinity) and the most ancient (i.e. having nothing prior to You) principle residing in all things. You are the ultimate stay of the universe. You are the knower and also what is to be known, the goal of everything, the Infinite Being by whom all this existence is pervaded.

11.39. You are Vāyu, Yama, Agni, Varuṇa, Śaśāñka, and Prajāpati, the Grandsire (of all existence). My salutations to you a thousand times, again and again.

11.40. I salute you from the front and from the back. Let me salute you from all sides. You are everything. You are everywhere, pervading all. You are infinite potency and infinite power.

11.41-42. Not knowing your greatness, and this (your Infinity), if I had called You the incommensurate, a friend, Krishna, Yādava (as if You are an ordinary being like me), either consciously or by mistake, either with affection or to ridicule, either while dining with you or at play or at rest, either when alone or in company, I crave your pardon.

11.43. You are the father of all beings moving and unmoving. You are the most worshipful world teacher. You are the incommensurate power in all the three universes. There is none equal to you. If that is so, how can anyone be superior to you?

Krishna:

11.47. By My grace and self-design, this transcendent dimension of the luminous basic infinitude has been revealed to you, a form none except you has ever seen.

11.52. What you have seen as My form is the (limit of the) impossible. Even the Gods are eternally crazy to have a glimpse of it.

11.54. I am that Form (of the impossible). However, with an unswerving devotion, it is possible really to intuit (jñātum) (the dimension of My Infinity), envision (draṣṭuṃ) (its identity with all existence) and authentically participate (praveṣṭuṃ) (in its rhythm).

11.55. Whoever submits to my infinite dynamics and attunes himself to it understands me as the ultra dictum, and whoever is never opposed to the consolidation of any (value or being of) existent, and has no attachment to particulars, attains Me.

13.1. This is the body and it is called the field (kṣetra). Whoever knows this, him the knowers of the truth call ‘the knower of the field’ (kṣetrajña).

13.2. In all the fields, know Me as the knower. Whatever knowledge there is of the dynamics of the field and the knower is in the line of My design.

13.3. How to identify that field, what its form is, what its modifications are, what comes out of what and what that (designer) is, and what his power can be – all these, listen to in brief from Me.

13.56. In brief, the field and its modifications are (the following): the great elements, the ego, the understanding, the unmanifest, the ten senses and the five sense-objects; the aggregate of the will, hate, pleasure, pain, mind, stability, etc. (Now listen to what constitutes knowledge in the context of śarīra or body, wherein lies the confluence of the field and the knower, so that an evaluation can be made for an attunement to My rhythm.)

13.7. Humility, non-pretension, non-injury, forgiveness, uprightness, devotion to teacher, purity, steadfastness, self- control, indifference to the (lure of) sense-objects, having insight into birth and death, old age and illness, pain and even unattachment, not losing objectivity in the company of children and wife and at home, having a balance of mind always in circumstances both likeable and unlikeable, living in undisturbed places and enjoying the crowds, cultivating unfluctuating devotion (to the cosmic order and purpose), having faith in the eternal verity of the spirituality of existence, and contemplating to discover the dialectics (of the spiritual order) in every detail – all these are declared to be knowledge or wisdom.

And things which are not these are non-wisdom.

13.12. Now, what is to be known (as the truth) I shall declare, knowing which one attains immortality. (That truth is) the beginningless ultimate Infinity. It is said to be neither sat (existence) nor asat (non-existence, in the ordinary sense).

13.13. It is all hands, all feet, all eyes, heads, ears that are found in the universe. It exists covering all things (i.e. exists being everything.)

13.14. It shines with the qualities of everything, (but at the same time) it has no qualities of things. It supports everything, but in none it is confined in its interest. It enjoys the qualities, but is itself qualitiless.

13.15. It exists both inside and outside of things (i.e. immanent and transcendent). It is unmoving yet dynamic. It is unknown, being the subtle (truth behind all knowing). It is far, yet near (being the very soul).

13.19. Know prakṛti and puruṣa to be beginningless. Know the modifications (of prakṛti, the vikāras) as well as the guṇas to be born of nature (prakṛti).

13.20. With regard to the incidents of cause and effect, it is said that prakṛti is responsible, and with regard to the enjoyment of pleasure and pain, it is said that the puruṣa is responsible.

13.21. Verily the puruṣa, rooted in prakṛti, enjoys the prakṛti-born guṇas. A being associated with the enjoyment of the guṇas or qualities, he is made to take birth in good or bad wombs.

13.22. The Supreme Puruṣa, the highest spiritual principle in the body is called the seer, the consenter, the sustainer and even the enjoyer.

13.23. Whoever knows the puruṣa, the prakṛti, and the guṇas as well, in whatever condition (of empirical life) he may be, is not reborn.

13.26. Whichever entity comes into being, whether moving or unmoving, arises because of the confluence of the kṣetra and kṣetrajña (or the field and the knower).

13.27. Whoever understands the dialectics of the Great Lord existing equally (samaṃ, i.e. with no diminution) in each and every being (that arises of the above-said confluence), whether destructible or indestructible, has seen the truth.

13.28. Whoever encounters the Lord in every being, at every time (samaṃ paśyanti sarvatra samamavasthitaṃ īśvaraṃ), never indeed destroys the Self by the Self. By this wisdom he attains the highest state of existence.

13.29. He sees the operations of Reality as it is, who understands the Self as the non-doer, and the prakṛti as the cause of all movements, whatever they may be.

13.30. When one envisions the varied existents (and their doings) rooted in the unity of one’s Being (ekasthaṃ) as also its expansions (vistāraṃ), he attains then the fullness of the Infinite Being (brahma saṃpadyate).

13.31. The Supreme Self – whose dimensions he sees – is beginningless, undiminishing (with all the said expansions, for they are only revelations to consciousness of the ever-existing Infinity), and as such, even though residing (as the puruṣa) in the body, He neither acts nor is He tainted.

13.32. As the all-pervading ākāśa is not tainted, being itself subtle, so spreading over/about/in the body, the Self is not tainted.

13.33. As a single Sun shines and illumines the whole of this universe, so the kṣetrī (one in the field), illumines the whole of the kṣetra (the field).

13.34. Whoever sees the secret of the field and the Knower (of the field) by the eye of wisdom, and (also) the way of freedom from the elements of nature, goes to the highest limits of Being.

14.1. I shall narrate to you, again, the peak (cream) of all wisdom, which being known, the sages attain their consummation.

14.2. Adopting this wisdom, those have entered into My state, and so they do not emerge at creation (which goes on periodically) nor are troubled at destruction (for they have gone beyond these cosmic states).

14.3. The great expanse of existence is my womb, and I fecundate it (at anytime and anywhere), and so from this all creatures come out.

14.4. (On this terminology of ‘production’) whichever forms emerge from any womb, you know for all of them the Primal Nature is the Infinite expanse (mahad-brahma) and I the fecundator.

14.5. From prakṛti (called mahad-brahma above) are born the guṇas or qualities: sattva, rajas and tamas (goodness, passion, and darkness). They bind (even) the indestructible ‘Dweller-in-the-body’ (to experiences and the consequent fruits).

14.6. Of these, goodness, being itself pure and having no defect (or sin), gives out (only) illumination (and joy). (Still) it too binds (the Dweller) by making him feel pleasure in enlightenment.

14.7. (On the other hand,) know that passion is desire-oriented, and springs from (carnal and worldly) thirst and attachment; and so it (naturally) binds the Dweller through actions (and to their fruits).

14.8. Know that darkness is born of ignorance. It binds the Dweller in all the bodies in error, laziness and sleep (both literally and functionally).

14.20. Transcending these three (prakṛti’s) qualities – which actually give rise to the bodies – the Dweller wins immortality, freedom from the chain of births and deaths, old age and pain.

14.26. He who serves Me (and My purpose) by unswerving and attuned devotion, overcoming the (binding) qualities (incidental to the physical situation), becomes fit for the state called the Infinite.

14.27. I am the foundation of all (ideals and goals of aspirants), viz. infinity, immortality, indestructibility, eternality and absolute bliss.

15.1-2. They say the undecaying Fig Tree has its roots reaching up and its branches reaching down. Its foliage are the hymns. The branches spread all over – upward and downward – fostered (and tended) by the guṇas of prakṛti (the way indicated already). The buds are the sense-objects (which ripen into fruits and breaking up again into seeds, thus never breaking the continuity of the cosmic tree). The roots (as even they reach high to receive its sap, so too) come down in capillaries twining up the human species with the law of karma (i.e. the action-result series, both subtle and gross). He who knows the secret is the knower of the truth (of the cosmic play).

15.3-4. However, the full dimension of it (i.e. the truth of the cosmic tree and the law of karma) cannot be available here (in the limited field) of the human region. For, it has not begun here, nor does it end here. Nor is its base traceable here (so that it could be snapped, as one may wish). This mighty and sturdy rooted Fig Tree (of saṃsāra) will have to be destroyed (for winning immortality) by the unbending weapon of non-attachment. And that state beyond (the region of the Fig Tree) is to be sought. Reaching that there is no returning (to bondage). That state is the Transcendent Person from whom originate the dynamics of immortal life (of the Fig and the human species).

15.5. With no delusion of pride, with the vice of attachment conquered, freed from desire (but not of) the realisation of the eternal Self, freed from dualities, from attachment to the pain-pleasure complex, the wise (i.e. the knowers of the truth mentioned above) reach that indestructible state.

15.6. There neither the Sun nor the Moon nor the Fire shines. (For all these luminaries grow in the brilliance of the Self). Reaching there, the wise do not return (to bondage). That is my highest state.

15.7-8. In the world of living beings, an aspect of mine is concentered, enlivening nature and drawing around itself the six senses, including the mind. While the Lord (i.e. His aspect) gets a body, and while crossing it, gets hold of these (senses) and marches with them as the wind takes away the smell from their natural spots.

15.9. (The Lord) enjoys the objects of sense (i.e. the buds of the Fig Tree) by residing in the ear, eye, skin, tongue, nose and also in the mind.

15.10. When He gets out, or when He resides in, or even when he is enjoying, the ignorant one, clouded by (the limiting) guṇas of prakṛti, does not see.

15.11. The Yogins trained in the dialectics of the Self, see Him (i.e. the Lord) at all stages of His movement (in the body). But even with the training, the unwise and the unoriented do not identify Him at all.

15.12. Know that the luminosity in the Sun illumining the whole of cosmos, and that in the Moon and the Fire, is all Mine.

15.13. Pervading all existents, I support them with My vitality. Becoming the saving juice (the nectar), the sap of their very life, I foster all herbs.

15:34. Becoming the digestive fire (vaisvānara) seated in the bodies of living beings, associated with life-breaths, I cause the digestion in four ways.

15.15. In the hearts of all beings, I am established. Memory, knowledge, (even) skepticism, etc. arise on account of Me. The object of all knowledge, which the Vedas proclaim, is Me alone. Know for certain that I am responsible for the very Vedas, and (if there could be anyone knowing them,) I am the knower of the Vedas.

15.16. (In this universe of life) there are two persons (forms), the destructible and the indestructible. All beings that become (from the little worm to the vast mountain) are the destructible (kṣara). Only the firmly established in them is called the indestructible resident (kūṭastha).

15.17. Even as the aspect of the resident is hidden in the hearts of beings, there is the other transcendent ground of the cosmic person. It is said to be the Super Soul or Self.

15.18. For this reason of its transcending the destructible and the indestructible aspects of the Resident, the Super Self is proclaimed both in common usage and in the Veda as Puruṣottama (the Transcendent Being).

15.19. With no delusions (about My dimensions as the transcending and immanent Self), whoever knows Me as the absolute (Real), indeed, knows everything that is to be known. And he does adore Me with all absorption (for he is attuned to My Being).

15.20. Thus the most secret of the sciences (or the dialectics of the Absolute Being – how It is and how It operates) is narrated to you. Knowing this, a person becomes illumined (and so, freed from ignorance and bondage,) finds his consummation.

IV. On The Dynamics Of Recoilless Action

Krishna:

3.3. Two courses of devoted participation (in the dynamics of the) universe have been enunciated by Me earlier: participation through enlightenment, as in Sāṃkhya, and participation through practical attunement, as in Yoga.

3.4. A person does not win freedom from action by keeping away from it. Nor does he win perfection by abandoning all (including action).

3.5. None whosoever can remain idle (if by ‘idle’ he means abandoning all action) even for a second, because everyone is overpowered by the guṇas or forces of Nature, and is made to engage himself in action.

3.9. Except for such activity oriented towards (selfless) sacrifice (intended to serve all or the cosmic purpose), all other acts involve men in bondage. That is the meaning of karma (or action). Disregarding all (other implications of it), engage yourself properly.

3.10. (The Lord, in the form of) Prajāpati created creatures and (prescribed) sacrifice (yajña, in the above sense of selfless participation in the cosmic design) simultaneously at the beginning (of creation) and said: “By this shall thou produce (i.e. continue). Let sacrifice be your source of fulfillment.”

3.11. By sacrifice satisfy the divinities (that matter) and they shall fulfill what you require. By mutual fulfillment, attain the highest (purpose and existence).

3.12. Satisfied or fulfilled by your sacrifice, the divinities grace you with what you need. What one receives from them, if he does not offer back, he (wrongfully) enjoys fruits (given by them) like a thief.

3.13. By receiving what remains of the sacrifice, the good-souled are freed (from all taints). But the evil-minded, who digest in greed (what is not earned rightfully), get back only sin (as the reward of not offering back).

3.14-16. The creatures are shaped and nurtured by the food and matter; and these by (the heavenly downpour of) rains; and these by the (collocation of elements in their act of) sacrifice, which, again, waits for fructification (karma), which is linked with the wider (dynamics of the) cosmos (brahma); and this, on the unalterability of the cosmic law (akṣara); and this, eternally engaged in self-sacrifice or regeneration, i.e. yajña. And so, rotates the cosmic wheel. In this context (of cosmic dynamics), whoever does not submit to the law of the wheel, becomes sinful. Such (non-submitting) sneaky men lead a wasteful (and wasted) life.

3.17. Whoever finds his object of fulfillment in his Self, his consummation in the Self only, and satisfaction too, has nothing else to wish for or to do.

3.18. Neither for any action done by him, nor for any non-action of his, is (attached) any significance at this level (of highest orientation and being), and no contingent existent can keep him satisfied (and so, bound).

3.19. Therefore, always engage in action, performing it with no desires attached. Whichever person sees his work (considering it to be the sacred sacrifice) with detachment attains the highest state of consummation.

3.20. By working (in this sense of sacrifice) Janaka and the like attained the highest perfection. You ought to, yourself, from the perspective of serving cosmic consolidation (loka-saṃgraha).

3.21. An ordinary (and unthinking) man does (things simply imitating) what the best of men will do. That is, whatever he, i.e. the best of men, will do with an authentic authority (of his understanding and perspective), (ordinary) people will do it by following him faithfully.

3.22. (Believe it.) I have no work (or function, as you have) to do whatever in the three universes (of the animal, human or divine), for I have nothing that I do not possess, or yet, seek to possess. Still I exist functioning (in the sense of cosmic sacrifice).

3.23. If ever I do not engage thus in (what happens to be) action with care, men follow Me too (thinking I am not doing things) in being inactive.

3.24. If I do not function, the worlds will collapse, and I will be responsible for all the dislocation of cosmic functions, and I will have destroyed all creation.

3.25. If the unknowing engage themselves in action with attachment, you, the knowing, should engage with attunement to serving cosmic consolidation with no attachment (i.e. in the spirit of sacrifice.)

3.26. However, do not create confusion in the minds of those who engage themselves in action with no understanding (of the implications of action or non-action in the cosmic scheme). Make them only love their work (and renounce the fruits thereof, which is what is needed). Knowing (the cosmic design, as you do,) involve yourself (in cosmic oriented action) with deep devotion.

3.27. In such people who do not know the secret of cosmic sacrifice, what keeps them working, at least, is the cosmic power of Nature. They are better, at least, who work unknowingly, than those befooled egotists who think they do all the work.

3.28. But the one who knows (the dialectics of Nature, which forces every being to act,) is sure that, by the inherent qualities and dynamism of Nature (guṇa and karma), qualities play on qualities (and so, they are themselves not involved in the natural dynamics). Knowing the objective dynamics of Nature (thus) and how it acts, one is not involved (with the fruits that come about).

3.29. One (however) deluded by the qualities of Nature (thinking that he did all action) involves himself in the effects of them. Enlightened (now) that you are fully of the dialectics of Nature, do not bewilder these half-knowing idiots (from performing at least their routine work they are engaged in).

3.30. Through understanding the spiritual truth, with no desire (for fruits), nor with egoism in what you do, offer to Me all you do, and be freed from the fever (of delusions you have) and fight (the battle that is facing you).

3.31. Human beings, whoever they may be (without distinction), having faith (in Me) and having no greed (or egoism), always put my teaching into action and get absolved from the bonds of work.

3.33. It is immaterial if one is a knower or not. He also works according to the objective dialectics of his own nature. All existents follow Nature’s law. What can control do?

3.34. Love and hate are lodged well in the sense-organs and also in the sense-objects. Let none be caught by them, for they are the enemies in the way (of one’s freedom).

3.35. Even if lacking merit, if one applies to one’s own natural functions, it is better than adopting functions alien to one’s nature and performing them perfectly. It is good if one were to die in the course of performing one’s own natural functions. For, functions alien to one’s nature are dangerous (to oneself, as they are not in accordance with the cosmic design).

4.1. This dialectics of application to duty, as a truth-constant, I declared to Vivaswat (of yore), who conveyed it to Manu, and in turn, Manu conveyed it to Ikṣvāku.

4.2. Thus, continued through tradition, this truth, the sages among kings know. But the knowledge of dialectics got blunted in the passage of time (and by lapses of people).

4.3. But the same knowledge of the ancient law is being restored to you, as that (knowledge) happens to be the best of secrets (for one’s redemption), and as you happen to be My devoted friend.

Arjuna:

4.4. Your birth (i.e. manifestation) is obviously recent, whereas the origins of Vivaswat are untraceable (in antiquity). If you say, you have taught this to Vivaswat, how should I understand (the mystery of the disparity in time)?

Krishna:

4.5. I have had many manifestations, as you too had your births. But I know them fully (as I am the originator of all beings, being eternity Myself), and you do not (due to the obscuring power of My Māyā).

4.6. Though I am unborn and unchanging (even through the varied manifestations), and though I am the Lord of all existents (not a creature like you), standing on My Nature, I manifest (as and when I like) by the dynamics of self-existence (ātma-māyā).

4.7. As and when the cosmic order is slackened, and disorder gets stronger, then by the very dynamics of My self-existence (ātmānāṃ) I manifest Myself. (I am not born, as you may think of Me.)

4.8. To save (or salvage) the good and to destroy the evil-doers, i.e. to consolidate the cosmic order (dharma saṃsthāpana arthāya) I manifest from time to time (in a way and fashion that cannot be comprehended ordinarily).

4.9. My manifestations and modus operandi (janma ca karma ca) are divine (divyaṃ, not human). Whoever knows this in truth (which is the secret of My dynamics of being and expression), casting off his body, never takes it again, but attains to My state (of universal Being).

4.13. Based on qualities and functions natural to beings, the four-fold classification has been designed by Me (in the scheme of cosmic consolidation). For that (cosmic planning and designing) consider Me as the executor. Still, you (should discriminate and) know I am the unchanging principle of the causal agency.

4.14. (Do not consider Me as an ordinary doer of things like a man), for I do not have any desires for fruits of actions, and so, actions, i.e. cosmic doings, do not taint Me. He who understands (Me and acts in the same spirit of cosmic sacrifice) is not bound by actions (in the world).

4.15. (This is the way of liberation). Thus knowing (the dialectics of recoilless action) the lovers of liberation did act in days of yore. Therefore engage yourself in the objective dynamics (of nature) in the same way (and get liberated).

4.18. Whoever discovers the truth which makes it a recoilless action, and in the recoilless action a duty, he, among his species, is the wise. (By dint of catching the pulse of the cosmic dynamics) he is absorbed in the universal dynamis).

4.19. One whose every move is bereft of self-desire, and whose every action is burnt by the fire of wisdom, him, the knowers (of the secret) identify as the wise.

4.20. Such a (wise) man detaches himself from the fruits of action. Eternally contented (in doing well what he does), and independent (of all other considerations), though engaged deeply in duties, he is not doing anything really (that binds him).

4.21. He is a being (ātman) with no ambitions (as they are burnt away in him). With mind well controlled, he receives nothing and works for the simple maintenance of the physical organism, and so does not get defiled (even though he is seen to live from ordinary standards).

4.22. He is satisfied with whatever he finds (for his living), transcends dualities (of empirical existence) and has no avarice. Always established in equanimity, he sees success and failure (as of no importance). And so, ever engaged in action (which, for him is cosmic action and not individual or personal), he (in My own manner) is never bound.

4.23. He whose mind is established in this wisdom is free (in life, and lives beyond the dichotomising effects of his normal action). Having no attachment to the fruits of action, he performs all functions (as duties) in the spirit of sacrifice. He has all the bonds of karma destroyed.

(The entire way and the spirit of his living can be analysed thus:)

4.24. The sacrifice (of the above description) is the act of the Infinite. What is sacrificed is the Infinite. What burns (as the offering) is the Infinite. What is burnt (too) is the Infinite. And what is aimed at by absorption in this infinite dynamis is the Infinite only.

4.31. Whoever partakes of what remains of this sacrifice (yajña) reaches Infinity or eternity. Whoever does not offer himself in sacrifice (like this) has no place in this existence; why think of a future for him hereafter?

4.35. Once you know (the picture of the Infinite being, and consolidation through sacrifice, which is the name for the cosmic operation), you never can have any doubt (about the meaning of life and its functions in the universe). By that wisdom you will see the infinite existence in you. If you do, how can you miss it in Me, the Cosmic Person?

4.41. One who is attuned to detachment or the way of performing actions (in the sense of sacrifice) has broken off all doubts through his wisdom. He is ātma rata, i.e. who enjoys the being of his Self. Him no necessity of action binds.

18.2. (According to those who know the meaning of selfless or recoilless action in the spirit of sacrifice,) renunciation (saṃnyāsa) is to drop out from all desire-oriented activities. Surrender (tyāga) is surrendering all fruits of action. So say the discriminating men.

18.3. However, there are thinkers who say that all actions (without any exception) should be dropped as evil. But others there are (who have an understanding of the dynamics of Being, as outlined above,) who say that sacrifice, gifting and doing penance are not to be abandoned.

18.4. With regard to surrender (and renunciation) listen to My definite position. As acclaimed by Me surrender is three-fold.

18.5. There is no abandoning of sacrifice, making gifts, and doing penance. These should be performed always. What purifies (and sublimates) one who merely reasons are verily (these:) sacrifice, gifts and penance.

18.6. However these functions must be done by surrendering the associated fruits. They are thus to be taken up as duties (obligatory). This is my wise counsel.

18.7. Abandoning of the obligatory duties cannot make it renunciation (saṃnyāsa). However, if one were to abandon them with a false understanding of renunciation, it is nothing but ignorance (tamas).

18.8. If one were not to undertake action for fear of physical strain (or exhaustion or injury), it is not only passionate (rājasa) renunciation, but it gets no merit of surrender of fruits (and so, it recoils).

18.9. That obligatory action done with a sense of duty which ought to be performed, and that action done with no attachments to the fruits, is (real) surrender. It is (verily) a noble (sāttvika) action.

18.10. He does not resent at an ill-performed action, nor does he rejoice over a well-performed one. He who is established in nobility or purity, and is (also) wise, with no doubts at all (about the dynamics of recoilless action), is a person who has really renounced.

18.11. For the wearer of the body, (circumstantially) it is not possible to do away completely with actions. And so, whoever renounces (in the manner stated above) the fruits of action is said to surrender.

18.12. The one who has not renounced thus gets three kinds of recompense: the undesirable, the desirable and the mixed.

8.13-14. Hear Me telling you, what is said in the wise counsel (Sāṃkhya) about all actions oriented to attain consummation:

There are five factors for the consummation of all action: The nature of the field, the nature of the doer, the various instruments of action, their actual functioning, and the fifth, the divine element.

18.15. Whatever activity a man does, whether by his physical body or by his mind, whether it is just or unjust, these five are the causal factors.

18.16. It being so, one with imperfect knowledge (of the cosmic dynamics) sees that he is the sole doer. He, the unwise, does not see the truth (of the composite factors).

18.17. He who, not having the idea that he is the sole doer, and has the right wisdom (of the cosmic dynamics and of recoilless action), even if he were to destroy these worlds, does not really destroy (for he will have done it in accordance with the objective law of cosmic dynamics, and therefore), and is not really bound or tainted.

18.18. Knowledge, the knowable and the knower form the threefold activising ingredients behind any action. The instrument, the action and the doer form the threefold aspects in a (wholesome) action.

18.19. Depending on the differences of guṇas (qualities operating in individuals), knowledge, action and the doer are of three kinds. Hear Me say of these, as laid bare in the Analytics of Qualities (guṇa saṃkhyāna, i.e. Sāṃkhya).

18.20. Know that knowledge to be noble (sāttvika) which discovers the existence of the one indestructible Being in all existence, the undivided and the divided.

18.21 Know that knowledge to be passionate (rājasa) by which one understands the (single) being as manifold, on the logic of division.

18.22. That knowledge is ignorant (tāmasa), which takes a part as if it is the whole of action, and so with no reason, as it does not grasp the (whole of) truth, and grasps it partially.

18.23. That action is noble which is done as obligatory, but with no attachment, with no love or hatred (involved), and with no desire of the fruits thereof.

18.24. That action is passionate which is done verily with a desire, with egoism, and with much effort.

18.25. That action is called ignorant, which takes action with related fruits and expends the strength of the doer, involving cruelty and wasted energy.

18.26. That doer is called noble (sāttvika) who is unattached, egoless, combining firmness with eagerness and not disturbed in success or failure.

18.27. That doer is said to be passionate, who is full of desire, anxious about the fruits of work, is violent, miserly, unclean and swayed by happiness and pain.

18.28. That doer is ignorant, who is inept, rude, inert, adamant, having no responsibility of action, lazy, despairing and delaying.

18.29. Now, listen to Me on qualitative understanding and steadfastness. They are threefold. I shall tell you of them in detail and in full.

18.30. Whichever understanding knows the dialectics of involvement and liberation, of right action and wrong action, of the fearful (empirical condition) and the fearless (transcendental state), of bondage and freedom, is noble.

18.31. Whichever understanding makes for righteousness, good action and bad action, not as they are (but differently), is passionate.

18.32 That understanding which is covered by ignorance, takes unrighteousness for righteousness, and all right meanings by their opposites, is ignorant.

18.33. That steadfastness (dhṛti) by which the activities of the mind, senses and vital organs are held with firmness and unshaken discipline, is noble.

18.34. That steadfastness by which activities of dharma, kāma and artha are held associated with fruits incidental to them, is passionate.

18.35. That steadfastness by which the wicked-minded is not allowed to overcome sleep, fear, grief, despair, arrogance, etc. is ignorant.

18.40. There is no being on earth or heaven, or (even) of gods, who is free from the three qualities or guṇas of prakṛti.

18.41. The functions of brāhmaṇas, kṣatriyas and śūdras are differentiated, and arise out of the guṇas of prakṛti.

18.45 Engrossed in the natural functions of each, every man attains perfection. Listen now (to what I say of them, and how) by following one’s natural functions, each attains perfection.

18.46. Through performing one’s natural functions, one who worships Him from whom all existents emerge and by whom all this is pervaded, attains perfection.

18.47. Though destitute of merits, highly redeeming it is to follow one’s own natural functions than by practice taking to functions natural to others. Keeping to functions determined by one’s own nature, one does not incur sins.

18.48. Even if one’s natural functions are defective, they are not to be abandoned. For verily, in the nature of things, all (finite or imperfect) actions are covered by deficiencies, as smoke covers fire.

18.49. One who, with an attitude of non-attachment to anything (except to his natural functions as duties to be done by him), has conquered his senses and has no egoistic love, attains by such renunciation the transcendent state of no-action.

18.50. Attaining to perfection, how one realises the Infinite and what exactly is the orientation of such wisdom, learn from Me in brief (as I tell you).

18.51-53. With pure understanding, controlling the self with steadfastness, renouncing objects of senses, leaving out both craving and aversion, avoiding crowds, living on minimum food, controlling mind, speech and body, being inclined towards meditative attunement, adoring always detachment, overcoming egoism, physical use of power, arrogance, lust, anger and love of property, and being at peace both within and without, one becomes fit for the Infinite condition (of the transcendent state of no-action).

18.55. One who attains to the Infinite state is always tranquil, neither worried about nor desiring anything. He treats every being with equal regard (for that is the indication of his) having attained the highest love for Me.

18.56. Even while engaged in doing his (natural) functions, he depends upon Me (as the strength of all his actions) and by My grace attains to the state, eternal and indestructible.

18.57. (This is My word to you:) Depend on the essential wisdom of attunement (to action natural to you). Constantly keep Me in your thought (as the foundation and strength of all existents), and willingly offer all your doings to Me.

18.58. If so, by My grace and will, you will crossover all hurdles (you are experiencing now).

If, on the other hand, you are not listening to My counsel, by dint of your egoism (or any other reason of false strength etc.), you get yourself destroyed.

18.59. Depending on (the strength of your) egoism, if you are to think you are not going to fight (the battle in which you are), this, your determination, is going to be falsified (and shattered by the mighty power of the cosmic law which has decided things already). As you are goaded to action (i.e. to fight) by your own (kṣatriya) nature (be contented you are doing it).

18.60. (Let Me tell you once again:) If by any delusion you do not want to fight, bound by the law of your own nature, you will engage yourself helplessly in fight (about which you have no choice).

18.61. In the hearts of all beings the Lord exists and spins every being (round their natural functions) set on the wheel of cosmic motion.

18.62. In every way surrender to Him (i.e. the Lord, in the heart). If so, by His grace, you will attain to the highest state of eternal tranquility.

18.63. This wisdom, the secret of all secrets, has been unfolded to you by Me (for your fulfillment). (Deeply) think over (this picture of the cosmic force acting), critically analyse it and fully (comprehend the truth of it), and (later, if you want to go against it,) do as you will. (The best choice is given to you: either get your existence fulfilled or get yourself destroyed by the cosmic dynamis).

18.64. Listen again, to My highest and most secret of words:

18.66. Abandoning all other (false) resorts (like egoism, pride of position, physical prowess, military strength, etc.) surrender to Me (as the only resort) and I shall free you from all taints (or misgivings). Grieve not (and be assured)!

Arjuna:

18.73. Oh, Acyuta! By your grace, my delusions (about myself) are set at naught. My mental bearing (or discernment of my position in the cosmic theme) is rediscovered. I come to be myself, burying my doubts. (With absolute submission) I carry out your orders. (I realise therein lies my fulfillment.)

OM TAT SAT

1.This becomes evident later.

2. We are seeing below the exact meaning of these two terms as understood in the context of the Gita.

3. Reality is not made through the process of time, but that time is processed by Infinity, which is Reality. The Lord is Kāla-kāra, the Maker of time, as the Śvetāśvatara Upaniṣad puts it, (6.2). He is Kāla-kāla, the Destroyer of time (Ibid. 6.16), Trikālātῑta, Beyond the three times, (Māṇḍūkya Upaniṣad, 1).

4. This becomes clear when we discuss the meaning of ‘yoga’ which Krishna names ‘his own’. See further on.

5.This applies generally to the treatment of the entire text. The teaching is not relevant only to the context of when and where the words are spoken. It is the philosophy of life and action linked up with Reality as a whole.

6.“Those ignorant (of the Secret Law of My being and operation) do not know Me who has taken up this human form. They do not understand My transcending dialectics. I am the Supreme Lord of all existence (not a creature born),” (9.11).

7.Or the universe; and how many of this there are and of what magnitude, we cannot imagine.

8.One is invited to refer to the usual renderings of this verse which take away the dimensions and potentialities of the cosmic law when they make it apply to the narrow sphere of human social or ethical order only.

9.At the absolute level, epistemology and ontology are fused – they are identical.

10.“The creatures are shaped and nurtured by food and matter; these (in turn) by the (heavenly downpour of) rains; and these (in turn) by the (collocation of elements in their act of) sacrifice; which again waits for fructification (karma); which is linked with the wider dynamics of the) cosmos (brahma); and this (in turn) with the unalterability of the Cosmic Law (akṣara); which is eternally engaged in self-sacrifice or regeneration (yajña). And so rotates the Cosmic Wheel. In this context (of cosmic dynamics) whoever does not submit to the Law of the Wheel becomes sinful. Such lazy men lead a wasteful life (3.14-16).”

11.Ṛg Veda, X, 121-2; Śatapata Brāhmaṇa, X.2.2.1; XI.1.8.2-4.

12. A Haṭha-yogin who may demonstrate successfully the stoppage of pulse, breath etc. has only learnt an art or craft by which he slows down the katabolic process, but ‘why?’ is the question. He attains nothing beyond it, for, when once death is on, there is no getting up. We shall see of this further on.

13. If jñāna is theoretical understanding, jñāna-yoga is application of it in practice.

14.“Find this entire universe (the moving and the unmoving) existing in a unity in my bosom, and whatever else you want to see! (10.7)” Also: 11.11; 13.30; 18.20 etc.

15. “My Nature (prakṛti) is eight-fold: Earth, Water, Fire, Air, Ether, Mind, Egoism and Intellect. This constitutes the inferior stratum. My higher stratum is different and is the enlivening element by which the whole cosmos is sustained. All existents have their source in this. But I am the originator of all creation and the cause of all destruction. Besides My being there exists nothing whatsoever. By Me all this universe of beings is linked (7.4-7) ….”

16. The significance of a yoga-bhraṣṭa getting back to life is seen here. 6.37, 40-45 and 46 give the finale. And the Lord says, “Be a yogī!”

17.And the four castes are created to serve this Law and in according with this Law (4.13).

18.It is a demand to live, but not to live again; to die, but not to die again.

19.The body of the individual and also the larger objective universe outside.

20.We come across repeated descriptions of such a person: 2.54-72; 12.13-19; 13.7-11; 14.22-26; 15.3, 5; 16.1-3; 17.11; 17.14-16; 18.20-23, 33, 42, 49, 51-54.

21.“If the splendor of a thousand suns were to blaze at once in the sky, that may resemble the glory of the great Self.”

22.It is in the estimation of this, i.e. linking our being with Reality that the Vedāntas differ from each other.

23.It should be noted with great care that nothing is brought into being which was non-existing. But what was unavailable to our awareness is now made available to consciousness. This operation is in consonance with the Infinite Being, and with the use of the terms avyakta and vyakta, i.e. ‘unmanifest’ and ‘manifest’.

24.That we should not go by the divisions of the text of the Gita into chapters thinking that they present different topics is evident here. We will have to gather the statements of Krishna on puruṣa and prakṛti from more than one chapter distributed over the text of the Gita.

25.We devote ourselves to this aspect in the next section.

26.The organic or dependence relationship of the selves and the world to the Brahman in the schools of Vedānta are vindications of a natural difficulty in maintaining the uniqueness of Brahman as the Absolute against the eternal being (ontologically) of the selves and the world.

27.The Lord speaks, for example, of a jīva-loka, the ‘universe of life’, and applies the dynamics of the species to each individual in it, as seen earlier.

28.This verse, not usually found in the Editions of the Gita, is found in the Kashmir Recension. It is included here, for it makes clear the meaning of the word ‘ubhayaṃ’ occuring in 6.38. The Kashmir Recension gives the verse thus:

lipsamānaḥ satāṃ mārgaṃ pramūḍho brahmaṇaḥ pati, aneka citto vibhrānto mohasyaiva vasaṃgataḥ.